<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A triumphant arch erected and consecrated to the glory of the feminine sexe: by Monsieur de Scudery: Englished by I.B. gent.</title>
            <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 263 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1604_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208446</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867400</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 203:E1604[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A triumphant arch erected and consecrated to the glory of the feminine sexe: by Monsieur de Scudery: Englished by I.B. gent.</title>
                  <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
                  <author>I. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 229, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Hope, and Henry Herringman, at the blew Anchor behind the Old Exchange, and at the blew Anchor in the lower walk in the New Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRIUMPHANT ARCH ERECTED and CONSECRATED to the Glory of the FEMININE SEXE:</p>
            <p>BY MONSIEUR de SCUDERY:</p>
            <p>Engliſhed by I. B. Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>Dum Spiro Spero</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Hope,</hi> and <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> at the blew <hi>Anchor</hi> behind the Old Exchange, and at the blew <hi>Anchor</hi> in the lower Walk in the New Exchange, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:2"/>
            <head>To the LADIES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Illuſtrious Ladies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe following <hi>Harangues</hi> are ſo many pillars of that Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Arch, erected by the skilful hands of the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Monſieur <hi>de Scudery,</hi> to the glory of your excellent Sex; which I, not only out of thoſe common principles of Civility, which obliges all men to render you ſervice; and in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the commands of two moſt noble La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which were ſufficient to prompt the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſpirit; but out of that earneſt deſire I have to proclaim my infinite reſpect and veneration to your Illuſtrious Sex, have adventured to tranſlate, and do now proſtrate them before
<pb facs="tcp:119710:3"/>you with the moſt profound reſpect that can be. And though my diſ-joynted and unpoliſh'd verſion does ſo abate their native luſtre, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Original, as might deſerve your cenſure; yet when you ſhall be pleas'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of what importance it is to your fame and honour, and that none abler have yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred to undertake it; I do not believe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that your natural ſweetneſs will be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to grant a pardon, but am induced to think it were a ſin to doubt of your fair acceptance. Look but on it, Illuſtrious Ladies, as it truly is, a glorious Trophy, compoſed of the <hi>Arms, Scepters,</hi> and <hi>Crowns</hi> of ſo many Monarchs, which your beauties have ſubdued; and no doubt but it will become as grateful as it is magnificent; and be received with as much delight and ſatisfaction, as it is tendered with deſire and paſſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:3"/>
            <head>THE SUBJECTS Of the following HARANGUES.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The first Harangue.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>HElena</hi> to <hi>Paris:</hi> That beauty is no reall good.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Angelica</hi> to <hi>Medoro:</hi> That Love proceeds from the inclination.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The third.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Amarillis</hi> to <hi>Tityrus:</hi> That the Countrey life is to be preferr'd before living in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The fourth.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clorinda</hi> to <hi>Tancred:</hi> That the affection ought not to die with the beloved.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The fifth.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Erminia</hi> to <hi>Arſetes:</hi> That the affection ought not to goe beyond the grave.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſixth.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cariclia</hi> to <hi>Theagenes:</hi> That thoſe who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:119710:4"/>ſuffered troubles, cannot truly tell what pleaſure is.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſeventh.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Polixena</hi> to <hi>Pyrrhus:</hi> That death is better than ſlavery.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The eighth.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Penelope</hi> to <hi>Laertes:</hi> That abſence is worſe than death.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ninth.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Briſeis</hi> to <hi>Achilles:</hi> That one may be both Slave and Miſtris.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119710:4"/>
            <div type="harangue">
               <head>HELENA TO PARIS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know full well (ô too lovely, and if I may ſay it, too much beloved <hi>Paris</hi>) that you will not eaſily condiſcend to the diſcourſe I ſhall now ſhape; that you will hardly ſuffer I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that which you approve; that I blame that which you have ſo much praiſed, and that I ſlight that which you doe even yet adore. You beleeve, without doubt, that I cannot offend my beauty, without offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your judgement; and that ſince I owe all my glory to it, in owing it your conqueſt, I have no reaſon to make an aſſault againſt that. And truely he that looks on the thing but on this ſide, would ever be a ſtranger to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119710:5"/>my opinion: but as they have all double faces, if you will, your ſelf, conſider both the one and the other without intereſt, and preoccupation; I aſſure my ſelf that your ſence of it wil not be at diſtance from mine: that you will break down the Altar where you have committed Idolatry, that you will acknowledge that you have taken an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol for a God, that you will ſubſcribe to my opinion, and that in fine you will ſay as well as I that beauty is not a real God. But to prevent you from making me any objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I will propound them my ſelf; yes, my dearly beloved <hi>Paris,</hi> I my ſelf will range all your troops in battalia, that ſo I may defeat them afterwards: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all ſubject of complaint, I will not ſpeake till after I have made you ſpeak: I am not then ignorant, that the partiſans for beauty, ſay that it is the cheifeſt work of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and its laſt effect: that the planets, and the ſun it ſelf have ſomewhat a leſſer brightneſſe; that from that admirable mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of colours, and for that exact proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of features which compoſe a beauty, there reſults ſomething that is divine: that there are none but the blind can deny this truth, and thoſe ſtatues which feele not its power:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119710:5"/>that that marvellous and proud object con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually triumphs: that Kings take a glory in following its chariot: that they preferre its chaines to their crownes, and that the moſt brave take a vanity to ſigh at its feet, and to caſt down their trophies there. They ſay likewiſe that the Empire of this beauty is far more noble and more glorious than that of the great Monarchs, ſince they reign over the bodies only, and this reigns over the ſpirits. They ſay that they are her eyes only that may be called King of Kings, ſince they alone ſubject them, and that only they make thoſe dye ſlaves, who were not born but to command. In fine, they eſtabliſh this beauty Queen of all the Earth; they make her reign ſoveraignly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the rational world; and maintain with as much ardour as they reſent; that ſhe is alone the ſoveraign good. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, O my dear <hi>Paris,</hi> how deceitfull are the appearances! &amp; how true it is at leaſt, that if beauty be a real good for thoſe that ſee it, it is an evil to thoſe in whom 'tis ſeen. To make this paſſe for a ſolid advantage, were to make bloſſomes paſſe for flowers: flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers forme it of lilies and roſes, and do not dream that the lilies and the roſes are of no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119710:6"/>durance, and that the faireſt flowers are of no price but amongſt the curious, that's to ſay amongſt thoſe that are not wiſe. And then who does not know that we accuſtome our ſelves to behold beauty, as we do all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things? that after that it moves our eyes no more than the moſt vulgar? And that as ſoon as it hath loſt the grace of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new, it hath almoſt loſt all?</p>
               <p>Can one behold a light more reſplendent than that of the Sun it ſelfe? Is there any object in Nature ſo marvellous as that, and whoſe pompe and magnificence can come near it? Nevertheleſſe becauſe his luſtre is ordinary, and that 'tis ſeen every day, few people mind to conſider it, how worthy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be of it: Whereas if in a ſad night a Comet make his threatning beams blaze in the ayre, all the world runs forth to ſee it; all the world beholds with admiration; ſo true it is that things, which are common, moves but little, and that extraordinary ones do powerfully attract our minds. It is thus <hi>(Paris)</hi> with thoſe admirable flowers of which we ſpake already; of that fair or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of the ſpring which nature paints with ſo much art, and which ſhe enamels with ſo rare a diverſity: they ſeeme alwaies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119710:6"/>beautifull to us, becauſe we do not alwayes ſee them: it being certain, that if we beheld them continually, they would not ſeeme ſo to us. One ſeaſon beſtowes them on us, another raviſhes them away, and another brings them again: and from thence it is that our eyes are never glutted. Add again to theſe reaſons, that the flowers, which adorne the Earth, and thoſe which compound the skin, are but a ſhadow of beauty; but a pleaſing vapour; and but an illuſion which delights. It is of beauty as of the rainbow, it is ſomewhat, and it is nothing; it appears what it is not; and equally deceives him that admires it, and that lets it be admired. Lawfull Reigns may be long, but Tyranies are ordinarily ſhort. The moſt faithfull ſlaves do ſometimes remember their liberty, and when the chains are not ſtrong, they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome faile of weakening them. Judge then whether this forſaken queen be very glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and whether one can fall from a throne ſo elevated without falling dangerouſly? Suppoſe likewiſe, that thoſe ſlaves are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſo, that their chains be of dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and that is to ſay, as durable as they eſteem them precious; do you not know that it is a general order eſtabliſhed in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119710:7"/>that the effect cannot ſubſiſt when the cauſe is ceaſed? Beauty paſſes, the love which it engendered paſſes with it, and they are after left both without lovers or beauty. The glory which is left us, is the glory of an Epitaph: They ſay ſhe obtained a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand victories, ſhe gained a thouſand Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies; ſhe appeared in a thouſand Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs; but after all, ſhe is no more: here lyeth the beauty of <hi>Helena,</hi> although <hi>Helena</hi> be not dead; ſhe ſees her ſelf intombed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; ſhe hears her ſelf ſpoken of as of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon, and by a particular unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhe ſeems to be obliged, to enter twice into the grave. Ha me <hi>Paris,</hi> lets tell the things as they are; the privation of that glory is more ſenſible than that glory it ſelf ever was. It is more ſupportable to miſſe alwayes ſome good, than to looſe it after we have had it: and without doubt 'tis bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be borne unhappy then to become ſo. It is better (I ſay) to have alwayes been in the myre, than to fall therein from the height of the throne: and thoſe which are borne ſlaves are not half ſo unhappy as thoſe Kings which become ſo. Now if to fall from the throne be a great misfortune, Judge what that is then to be caſt from an
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119710:7"/>Altar? To looſe the Incenſe is more than to looſe the Crowne; and to ſee ones ſelf ſleighted by thoſe which adored us, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt a diſpleaſure which muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable. You may poſſibly tell men, that this inevitable evil is ſo farre off, that one cannot perceive it: that nature ſhall change its whole face fifty times before this beauty change, and that the ſun ſhall ſee its glory a thouſand and a thouſand times before it ſhall behold its diſgrace. O <hi>Paris,</hi> how if you meaſure the time, if you meaſure it thus! a thouſand accidents may raviſh it from us every day; It is expoſed to a thouſand dangers; and there are not more eyes which ſee it, than there are evils which can make that it never more be ſeen. And if yet it could reach as far as can be; that it ſhould laſt to the utmoſt limits which nature hath preſcribed it; and that this ſun ſhould yet be unclouded at its ſetting: there is ſo little ſpace from the cradle to the ſepulchre, and from the beginning of the life to its period, that one cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſtrong injuſtice ſet any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble price upon ſo fraile a thing. In a word 'tis to take glaſſe for diamond, and to make that eſteemed for pretious, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119710:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119710:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119710:9"/>is not at all ſo, though it appear ſo.</p>
               <p>I know you will tell me that the true lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver does not derive the cauſe of his paſſion from the beauty only of the body, but that the mind hath its ſhare; and that thus this laſt ſubſiſting alwayes his love may ſubſiſt in deſpight of the others ruine. But <hi>Paris,</hi> how rare are theſe Philoſophical lovers! and how few men are found which behold a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs only in the beauties of her ſoul! there are found ſome indeed, which ſwear that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is able to ſhake their conſtancy, which proteſt that their fidelity is above the power of fortune, and more ſtrong than time it ſelf; which maintain that this beauty ſhall change, and yet we ſhall not ſee them change; and that in fine they ſhall yet think the ruines handſome, and will even adore a Temple, though deſtroyed. But <hi>Paris,</hi> when they ſay all this their Miſtreſſes are not yet decayed; nor can their imagination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that they can become ſo. They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, without knowing what they promiſe, and without intent to obſerve it; and all thoſe unprofitable ſpeeches proceed, rather from the weakneſſe of their minds, than the meaning of their hearts. But ſuppoſe yet that they think all what they ſay, and that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119710:9"/>the lips do expreſſe only the pure intentions of the ſoul: ſhe whom they deceive in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving themſelves, is not much the more aſſured, ſince by the revolution of time and and things, there is often more difference betwixt us and our ſelves, than there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and ſome other: And that thus we cannot promiſe any thing on our faith, ſince we cannot tell our ſelves, what we ſhall be. O how much eaſier it is to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine brave projects, than to put them in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice! The pooreſt architect, ſo long as he traces his deſigne but upon the ſands, finds all his lines with a great facility; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding when it comes that the maſſe of ſtones muſt be piled, and the ſolidity of the marble muſt be hewen, the moſt skilfull finds himſelfe troubled. It is eaſie to thoſe who have the art of ſpeaking with a good grace, to make faire pictures of conſtancie, as of other vertues; nevertheleſs all painters are not vertuous, becauſe they are painters: and when they draw thoſe handſome I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, they do not alwayes make their own pictures. Now my dear, and dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Paris,</hi> do not imagine, that 'tis but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the fear of the future that we muſt ſeeke the diſadvantage of beauty: that ſun
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119710:10"/>hath eclipſes in its higheſt elevation: that queen hath her diſquiets under the purple, and on the throne: her ſcepter, as it is of gold, is heavier than Iron; and her Crowne has not ſo many flowers as thornes. I know well that to judge of her by the pompe, and by the ſplendour which environs her, it is impoſſible to have any other than very high thoughts: her beames dazle the judgement and the ſight; her majeſty ſtrikes feare; her ſweetneſſe inſpires love; ſhe is pleaſing to thoſe whom ſhe murders; ſhe findes all ſubmitted to her will; her imperious looks makes a thouſand illuſtrious ſlaves to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſhe impoſes laws and receives none; in ſhort ſhe ſees nothing above her ſelfe but heaven. Do not however judge, I conjure you, by theſe falſe marks of greatneſs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that this queen elective is not without trouble; and on the contrary, the leaſt of her ſubjects is more happy than ſhe is. Yes <hi>Paris</hi> it is with her domination as 'tis with thoſe great Empires which are only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of Conqueſts, and of uſurped pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; and which for this reaſon require ſo much care to keepe them, that their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour becomes a ſlave, as ſoone as ever he makes himſelf King. In all other ſtates
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119710:10"/>few rebells are founde: and in this of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty all aſpire to tyrany; all will from ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects become maſters; and not one reſolves to ſerve, but with the unjuſt deſigne of commanding. I know, lovely <hi>Paris,</hi> that you are the exception to this rule; that I ſhould be unjuſt my ſelfe, if I complained of your reſpect; and that in you a ſhepheard worthy to command Monarchs, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes taken a glory in obeying me. But as you are incomparable, do not draw any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence from your ſelfe of others: and without oppoſing your ſelfe againſt reaſon, or my diſcourſe, ſuffer me to continue it. As the Planets ſhine as well upon the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill as upon Jewels, and the moſt ſtupid ſee the ſun as well as others; ſo beauty makes ſhamefull conqueſts as well as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable; and its power extends ſometimes farther than ſhe deſires: a thouſand im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate people perſecute it: a thouſand diſpleas'd aſſaſinate it; and all oppoſe its good. One comes and praiſes it unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly; the other comes and rather extolls himſelfe; the one is alwaies muſing by her, the other is ſo gay that he hath loſt his wits; the one is jealous, another is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; one laughs at what the other ſighes;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119710:11"/>one comes and ſings her praiſes, another powres forth injury; the one calls her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, the other ſayes ſhe is a tygreſſe; the one offers her incenſe, the other, if he durſt, would throw durt at her; one raiſes an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar to her, and ſets her up an Image, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afterwards endeavours to raze both the Altar and the ſtatua; in fine, to conſider theſe things well, hell it ſelf hath not a greater nor more ſtrange torment than beauty which ſo many enemies beſiege. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs (can you believe it?) theſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are not the moſt to be feared, if they aſſault the quiet, there are others which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the honour: and by an unexampled cruelty, beauty it ſelfe endeavours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy beauty. O <hi>Paris,</hi> you will eaſily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this riddle, and will eaſily know my thoughts, if you obſerve what envy makes my ſex to do for the intereſt of this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py beauty. As ſoone as ere a woman con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders this, ſhee no more conſiders any body elſe; the moſt holy amity is not inviolable with her; the bonds of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity are not ſtrong enough to hold her; and of all the devoirs which binde us to one another, and which makes ſociety, there is not one which ſhe does not deſpiſe;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119710:11"/>ſlander (that poiſon as ſecret as dangerous) expands its ſelfe inſenſibly on the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a perſon who hath no other defect than that ſhe hath none, than that of being too handſome. She receives a thouſand wounds which ſhe feeles not; they ruine her when ſhe cannot perceive it; they ſtrike her when ſhe cannot ſee the arme nor the blow; and all theſe diſaſters happen to her only becauſe of her beauty. From thence more tragicall events yet draw their deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſource: from thence proceeds the quarrels of rivals, the diviſion of families, irreconcilable hatred, bloody and wofull cumbats, and the utter deſolation of houſes: But my dear, and as I have already ſaid, my too deare <hi>Paris,</hi> you, and likewiſe my ſelfe know it but too well what the effects are of this fatal beauty! you cannot caſt your eyes from this very place towards the ſigean gate, nor towards the banks of Xan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus without beholding the deplorable works of thoſe evils it can cauſe. 'Tis this alone (to ſpeake rationally) which covers this ſea with the enemies gallies; 'tis this alone which pitches ſo many tents and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilions about this famous City; 'tis this alone which diggs the deep trenches that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119710:12"/>begirt her, and which robs her of her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and 'tis this alone which raiſes to an equal height with our walls the proud and high ramparts which cover the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Camp. Yes <hi>Paris,</hi> 'tis this alone which hath cauſed the firſt blood to be ſpilt, with which the fields are died which hath diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the quiet, and the old age of <hi>Priam;</hi> which hath cauſed the affliction of <hi>Hecuba;</hi> which hath engaged the valiant <hi>Hector</hi> in the perills of combats; and to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what yet more ſenſible to my heart, which hath endangered <hi>Paris.</hi> 'Tis from this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that the Mycenian Mothers, and that the Trojan Women will equally demand their children and their husbands; and by an unhappineſs as ſtrange as particular, 'tis this alone on which both the parties will look as an enemy; whether the raſhneſſe of a Grecian, or the inconſiderateneſſe of a Trojan makes them periſh amidſt the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; the beauty of <hi>Helena</hi> (if it be true that <hi>Helena</hi> have any beauty) will alwayes be the only cauſe of it. She ſhall anſwer for all the events of the warre, and as if ſhe made the deſtiny both of the one, and the other; the one and the other Nation will alwayes demand ſatisfaction of her for the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119710:12"/>calamities they have ſuffered. Yes the Trojan people murmur againſt her; thoſe of <hi>Argos</hi> curſe her; offended <hi>Menelaus</hi> threatens; <hi>Caſſandra</hi> calls her the fatal torch of <hi>Illium;</hi> and to ruine this unfortunate beauty, thoſe people, which are at variance in all other things, agree in this: Nay I fear, (and this is the greateſt of my fears;) I ſay I fear (ô my dear <hi>Paris</hi>) leaſt the diſgrace become contagious; and that you be accuſed of its crime; and that in fine they may hate you becauſe you love it. Nature will complain of you and of love: the intereſt of your Country will ſtrive to overſway that of your paſſion: <hi>Priam</hi> will demand obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of you: <hi>Hecuba</hi> will claim your tenderneſſe: <hi>Caſſandra</hi> will ask for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance from you: the people will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your compliance: and the very Greekes will demand <hi>Helena</hi> of you, to be revenged, and to puniſh her. Well then, content all the world in her loſſe, and content even her own ſelfe, if ſo bee her loſſe may ſerve any way to content you. Extinguiſh this fatal torch, which may inflame your City, reduce your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces to cinders, and r'anverſe your walls,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119710:13"/>this ſo flouriſhing an Empire, at leaſt if you will beleeve the predictions of <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> and the dream your mother hath had, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>Menelaus</hi> who does deſire it, a gueſt which is ſo dangerous; follow no longer what you ought to fly; look on the perilous luſter of this beauty, as on thoſe falſe lights which lead into precipices, and be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dazled with ſuch obnoxious beams. Conſider that its moſt reſplendent lights may perhaps prove to you the ſhining of a Comet, which do threaten Princes and their States with diſorders and misfortunes. Conſider that all that pleaſes ſhould not pleaſe: and that the victory of ones own paſſions is not the leaſt glorious conqueſt, one may obtaine, as it is not the eaſieſt. Confeſſe as well as I, that beauty is no real good, and reject it as an evil. Doe not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten either to pitty or inclination, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver counſel faithfully, and do but flatter to deceive. Follow, follow that ſevere beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I mean reaſon, and preferre it to that of my face. Hearken to <hi>Priam,</hi> hearken to <hi>Hecuba,</hi> hearken to all the Trojans, nay hearken to the very Greeks, and hearken no more to love, which ſpeaks to you in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of this beauty. <hi>Helena</hi> who knowes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119710:13"/>it, and ought to know it, does once more proteſt to you, that ſhe is nothing leſſe than what ſhe is believed to be; that ſhe hath nothing precious but in appearance; and that ſhe is of too ſmall value to be preferred to Crownes, or to ſacrifice your quiet to her. Looſe her then to conſerve your ſelf, that fatal beauty; and if <hi>Troy</hi> will make an ominous preſent to the Greeks, let her make no other than what themſelves demand. Of all thoſe flames, which from the battlements of your ramparts, you ſhall caſt into their Camp, I dare ſay that thoſe of my eyes will be the moſt hurtfull to them; and if they knew what 'tis they deſired, they would give as many battells not to have it, as they give to obtain it. Believe me then, and do not believe your ſelfe, ô my deare, deare <hi>Paris,</hi> and expoſe not either your State, nor your Parents, nor your quiet, for a thing which cannot be eſteemed a reall good, no not in the very minds of thoſe, which do poſſeſs it. But when you have followed my counſell, and reaſons, remember at leaſt, that <hi>Helena</hi> hath ſpoken againſt her ſelfe to ſpeak for you, and that it is no ſlight act for a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to avouch ingenuouſly that beauty is not a reall good. Remember (I ſay) that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119710:14"/>
                  <hi>Helena</hi> hath more than once preferred your ſatisfaction before her own glory; and that the ſame cauſe, which obliged her to follow you, does now oblige her to leave you. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forget this laſt teſtimony of my affection I conjure you, ſince it is the moſt difficult I can give you; and how low ſoever the price is that I ſet on this beauty, which I will looſe with my life to preſerve you; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that your ſelf have often eſteemed it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Thrones &amp; Scepters; and that in this manner, though I beſtow on you but little according to my owne judgment, I give you very much according to yours.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb facs="tcp:119710:14"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAris</hi> was perſwaded enough of the love that <hi>Helena</hi> had for him, but he was not ſo of the diſeſteeme of her Beauty. He hearkened to this reaſon as a Paradox, and judged without doubt that this fair Grecian ſpake of her going, but only to oblige him the more to keep her.</p>
               <p>For mine own part, I who have made her ſpeake no leſſe againſt my own thoughts than againſt beauty; I acknowledge that ſince I have finiſhed this hard taske, for which I have had ſo much repugnance, I beleeve that now when I liſt, I may maintain that ſnow is black, and that Mores are white; ſo true it is, that what I have ſaid has little truth in it, and is ſo little conſonant to my belief.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:15"/>
            <head>ANGELICA TO MEDORO. The Second HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANGELICA,</hi> that faire Indian queen who made ſo many generous lovers run after her, and diſdain'd their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, could not in fine, hinder but that the beauty of a ſimple Souldier triumphed over hers, &amp; her pride: and revenged the unjuſt diſdain that proud one had made of the loves of ſo many kings, and of the vowes of ſo many Hero's, whom ſhe had ſcoffed, and never truly loved. Now we ſuppoſe that after the happy <hi>Medoro</hi> had ſubdued her heart, ſhe had ſome ſhame for her defeat, and judging that ſo
<pb facs="tcp:119710:16"/>extraordinary a paſſion would be condemned of all the World; ſeeing the inequality of their conditions; one day when they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pleaſant ſhades, where they paſſed ſo many ſweet moments, ſhe undertooke to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, through a deſire of glory, &amp; with her u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Eloquence: <hi>That love proceeds only from inclination.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119710:16"/>
               <head>ANGELICA TO MEDORO.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen ever (lovely <hi>Medoro</hi>) you ſhall undertake to entertain me with the grandeur of your affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, never ſpeak to me neither of my birth, nor of my merit, nor of my obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, nor of the glory you meet in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me, nor the advantages nature has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on me, nor thoſe I enjoy by fortune; but to ſatisfy me in this occaſion, ſay only to me that you love me, becauſe your incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation prompts you on to it, and becauſe you cannot hinder it your ſelfe. Believe me <hi>Medoro,</hi> 'tis neither to my birth, nor to my merit, nor to the obligations you have, nor to the glory you finde in ſerving me, nor the advantage I have received from nature, nor to thoſe I hold by fortune, that I will owe all that tenderneſſe which I expect from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119710:17"/>you, and to ſay all, it is not neither from your reaſon, nor from your acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor likewiſe from your will that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the love which you have for <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</hi> If the chains which I have given you were no ſtronger than thoſe, I ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you capable to break them eaſily, and ſhould think my ſelfe but ill aſſured of my conqueſt. But for my own ſatisfaction, I am perſwaded of the contrary, and I verily believe, that though I ſhould not re-aſcend the Throne again whereon I was borne, that although I had fewer good qualities than I have, though you were not obliged to me, though there were no glory in being my ſlave, and though neither Nature nor Fortune had given me neither beauty nor riches, yet you would not ceaſe to love me as perfectly as you now do, provided that your Inclination did prompt you, as I now know it compells you. 'Tis an errour to think that love can be an effect of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or the Will. No <hi>Medoro,</hi> that paſſion would ceaſe, being a paſſion, if it were bred <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n our <hi>ſouls</hi> by knowledge and judgment. One may, and one ought to chuſe their friend: but one cannot nor ought not to chuſe a Lover. We muſt love them almoſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119710:17"/>without knowing them, the firſt inſtant of their ſight muſt be the firſt of our ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, where we engage our ſelves we muſt find our ſelves quite laden with chains, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have had the leaſure to examine, whether or no it be glorious to receive them: the Judgment muſt be blinde, Reaſon muſt be baniſhed, the Will muſt be enchain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in fine, the Inclination we have for the perſon beloved muſt triumph imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly over all the powers of a ſoul, which is touched as it ſhould be with a ſincere &amp; tru paſſion. 'Tis from that alone that love muſt take its birth, and not from that great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of things, where a particular intereſt would ſway us ſooner than Inclination. And truly I can aſſure you, that in the mind I am in, I ſhould rather receive a Crown from your hand, than give it you, as I do intend; I ſhould rather ſee you deſpiſe all the Princeſſes in the world for love of me, than to deſpiſe, as I my ſelfe doe, all the greateſt Princes of the Earth for love of you; ſince in fine, if things were thus, I could never doubt, but that your amity were rather an effect of your Inclination than of your Choiſe. Nevertheleſſe, ſince that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, I am not unwilling to let you ſee,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119710:18"/>that my own cannot be for by-intereſts, but that it is voluntary in effect: if reaſon might freely have counſelled in this buſines: <hi>Medoro</hi> had not found <hi>Angelica</hi>'s heart in a condition to receive now his Image; ſo many Illuſtrious Captives which her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or her good deſtiny had beſtowed on her, would without doubt have engaged her ſoul before. Yes, of ſo many Princes, of ſo many Kings, of ſo many Heroe's which have loved her, and which have followed her; there would have been found ſome which her reaſon would not have judg'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her. If ambition could be a path for love, I ſhould reign over the Tartarian Empire; if valour could ſubject the ſpirit, <hi>Orlando</hi> would be the Conquerour of <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica;</hi> if wiſdome, virtue, birth, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage could ſuffice to inſpire that ardour, or to maintain and preſerve it, I ſhould yet love <hi>Renaldo</hi> more than my own ſelf; if the teſtimonies of a violent affection were pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull enough to produce its ſemblable, I ſhould not have reſiſted my brother, when he would have made me accept of that of <hi>Ferragus</hi> the King of <hi>Spains</hi> ſon; in fine, if this paſſion came into ones heart without fear, and with judgment, the <hi>Circaſſion</hi> King
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119710:18"/>had not left mine in a condition to be given you now; &amp; it would have been almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that of ſo many Crowns which have been laid down at my feet, I ſhould not have found ſome which I had thought faire enough to have ſuffer'd them to ſet it on my head: notwithſtanding, becauſe all thoſe princes, all thoſe Kings, and all thoſe Hero's have only ſatisfied my judgment, &amp; have not touched my inclination I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed them all, and the only <hi>Medoro</hi> without Crowne, without Kingdome, all cover'd with wounds, and extended almoſt dead up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, has had more power ore my ſoul, than all thoſe who by their riches, by their birth, or by their courage have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to conquer me. 'Tis true that one may perhaps tell me that I have found more merit in you, than in all the others: and that he who came from ſhedding his blood, and expoſing his life to give burial to the body of his King, deſerved to be King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to inſpire ſuch ſentiments into the heart of <hi>Angelica,</hi> which others could not infuſe. However to tell things as they are, that Heroick vertue which you teſtified in that occaſion, did not give you the Empire of my ſoul: and if that puiſſant inclination
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119710:19"/>of which I ſpeake, and which is the mother of all loves, had not conſtrained me to affect you, I ſhould only have had compaſſion &amp; eſteem for you. But that ſuperiour power which inclines us, or rather which forces us, to doe what it pleaſes, made that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing you, and without hardly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen you, I had mrore care for your life than for my own, and did beleeve I found in your perſon, that which I had not found in any other. All that you at the firſt inſtant, called compaſſion, and generoſity in me, was already an effect of love; I did not that which I would, but that which I could not forbear to do. I ſought the herbs which ſhould heale your wounds with too much earneſtneſſe and care to believe that I had no other intereſt in your life, but only for compaſſion, and generoſity. No <hi>Medoro</hi> it was not ſo, I had no ſooner ſeene you, but without the help of my judgment, I loved you as much as one can love, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I my ſelfe knew not whether that which I felt in my ſoul for you were love. And in effect, reaſon is rather wont to warre againſt love than to beget it, or to cheriſh it when it is borne, That ſevere and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious Queen, farre from approving the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119710:19"/>bonds the chains, and the follies of lovers, ſpeaks nothing but of liberty of our franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and wiſdome. She will have all our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſubjected to her, and our wills follow her intentions, our memory muſt receive nothing in ſtore but what ſhe judges worthy to be preſerved, and the imagination muſt preſent her with things only that are ſerious and very ſolid. A lover at his Miſtreſſes feet, is to her an object worthy of laughter and pitty: ſhe ſcoffs at his weakneſſe: ſhe condemns all he does: and in fine, ſhe would were it in her power, deſtroy all the Lawes of Nature, baniſh all paſſions from mens hearts, and reign; She alone over all the Univerſe. Judge after this <hi>Medoro,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon can introduce love in a ſoul, and whether I have not reaſon to ſay, that there is ſomething in us more powerfull than ſhe is that attracts us, ſInce in ſpight both of her counſels and power, we often act quite contrary to what ſhe would have us? there is this difference betwixt reaſon and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that one for the moſt part will oblige us to do things that diſpleaſeth us, &amp; this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter never tempts us to any thing but what is gratefull to us. 'Tis that without doubt which makes its power ſo great, that the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119710:20"/>other cannot reſiſt it; ſhe muſt needs yeild, how clear ſighted ſo ere ſhe is, to this amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blinde guide which leads and conducts us as ſhe pleaſes, who makes us love and hate according to her fancy, and who alone inſpires love in the hearts of all men. When reaſon would ſway us to any thing (though ſhe be ſo imperious as I have ſaid) yet ſhe muſt imploy both time and artifice to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade us to obey her: ſhe ſhews thoſe whom ſhe will expoſe to great perills, the glory they ſhall meet with; ſhe repreſents to thoſe who find an occaſion to be liberal, that to give to ones friends, is to put ones treaſure in ſecurity: in fine, ſhe diſcourſes the ill fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourdneſſe of vice, and the amability of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that we may ſhun the one, and follow the other with the more ardour. She does not therefore act with ſo abſolute a power as the inclination, which without pointing out to us either the good or the evil, which can happen by thoſe things whereto ſhe leads us, preſſes us on, or to ſay better, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains us with ſuch violence that we cannot reſiſt. Thoſe natural averſions, which we ſee amongſt reaſonable perſons teſtifies ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently that our judgment is not abſolute maſter of our actions: thoſe that hate roſes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119710:20"/>acknowledge that their colour is faire, and that the ſmell it ſelfe is ſweet; and yet for all the knowledge they have of their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they turne away their ſight with care, &amp; fly from them as another would from ſome fearfull object. This imbecillity of their temperature is the ſame thing, with that which is found in our ſoul, when the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation conſtrains it to do what ſhe will, and not that which its ſelfe pleaſes. When I ceaſed to love <hi>Renaldo,</hi> I did ceaſe knowing that he was yet worthy of my eſteeme; and when 'twas his turne to ceaſe from loving me, yet I believe he did acknowledge that <hi>Angelica</hi> had ſome beauty. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding becauſe it is not the judgment that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets affection, we know one another to bee lovely, and yet love not; and perhaps wee did love without knowing whether we had any lovely qualities or not: So true it is, that reaſon acts but weakly; and ſo certain is it, that inclination is altogether powerful. The firſt makes us obey only, by the ſame means legitimate Monarchs imploy againſt their ſubjects; but the other makes her ſelf to feared and followed, as victorious Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants uſe to do. She imployes nought but force againſt us; but as that force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119710:21"/>is almoſt inevitable, and that ſhe hath no leſſe ſweetneſſe than power, there is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any thing which reſiſts but ſhe overcomes it. Honour, glory, private intereſt, and vertue it ſelfe, are many times too weak an obſtacle to hinder her deſignes, ſhe makes Kings love ſhepherdeſſes, and that ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds raiſe their looks even up to their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns Thrones; and without diſtinction either of qualities or of merit, She makes a mixture of Scepters and ſheephooks, of Crowns and chains, of free perſons and ſlaves; and by theſe extraordinary effects, ſufficiently teſtifies, that we are not maſters of our own will, of affections; or that our reaſon is not alwayes ſo ſtrong as to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her. In effect, ſhould we act but by her counſells, ſhould our love follow only our knowledge, and were it by her conſent only that we ſhould weare our fetters; it is certain that we ſhould weare but one in all our lives. That which we had once found faire would alwayes be ſo to us; we ſhould love till death, what we once thought love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and inconſtancy in fine, would never be found amongſt lovers.</p>
               <p>Since the beginning of the World, the Sun hath given admiration to all men, gold;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119710:21"/>pearls, and diamonds, have never found any that queſtioned their beauty: briefly, all things univerſally known, remain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: why then, if love took birth from perfect knowledge, and by the operations of the judgement, ſhould it not alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the hearts that poſſeſſe it? Ha, no, no, <hi>Medoro,</hi> that cannot be ſo: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis that all thoſe, that are unfaithfull, are not ſo worthy of blame as is beleeved: nor thoſe that are conſtant merit, ſo much praiſe as is beſtowed upon them. The one and the other do what they are forced to do: ſome break their bands, and others preſerve theirs, becauſe they are conſtrained to it. You ſee ſome, who after they have broken their chains, do rivet them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether again with care, and binde themſelves again more cloſely than they were before. There are ſome others, even weighed downe by their burden, who ſigh under the load that preſſes them, and who might never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe diſengage themſelves, but will not, preferring their ſervitude above liberty. Do you beleeve <hi>Medoro</hi> that theſe bizare effects can proceed from a clear-ſighted rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a free will? Or do you not believe on the contrary that the ſole inclination is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119710:22"/>that which unchains us, or unties us, which makes us inconſtant or faithfull, and that which makes us either love or hate? Let none wonder than any more, if we behold queens deſcending from their Thrones to place their Lovers there, though they be not of a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all birth: Let none wonder then any more to ſee Princes deſpiſed, Crowns rejected, and Hero's unfortunate in their amours; ſince 'tis not neither from reaſon, nor from intereſt, nor from ambition, nor from glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that this noble ardour derives its birth.</p>
               <p>But (you will aske) what obligation has a lover to his Miſtres, if it be true that ſhe loves him only becauſe ſhe is conſtrained &amp; cannot chuſe but love him? None, my dear <hi>Medoro,</hi> none, &amp; 'tis for that in my opinion that love paſſes for the moſt noble of all paſſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not mercinary. In common friendſhip and amity it is permitted to count the ſervices we render or receive; and to name a thing, that we do willingly, an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: but in the actions of lovers there ſhould be no ſuch thing. The perſons which love owing all things, there are no thanks owing in returne again, ſo that though I had given you my Crowne, as I have already
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119710:22"/>given you my heart, I do not pretend you ſhould be the more obliged to me, ſince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that know how to love, who ever beſtowes their affections, do at the ſame inſtant beſtow both their Scepters and Kingdomes, and to be ſhort, all that they poſſeſs. And if by misfortune it had hapned, that your inclination had been contrary to mine; that you had hated me as much as I have and do love you, do you thinke, my dear <hi>Medoro,</hi> that I ſhould have blamed you? No, I would have bemoaned my ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out accuſing you: and as by my own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience I know one cannot love through reaſon, I would not have murmured againſt you, though you had refuſed <hi>Angelica's</hi> love, with as much rigour as ſhe has refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſervices of all the Kings in the world to accept thoſe of the amiable, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Medoro.</hi> Some might perhaps ſay to me that I am not very ingenious, but rather ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill adviſed, to entertaine you with theſe diſcourſes: that I take off your fetters by perſwading you that you may leave them without a crime: and that I inſtruct you in ingratitude, when I avouch my ſelfe that you owe me no obligation; although for the love of you I have done all what I was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119710:23"/>capable to do, in giving you my kingdome, and which is more my affection, which I preferre before the Scepter that I mean to give into your hands. But to anſwer that objection, I muſt tell you, that ſeeing the condition, wherein I found you, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of your birth from mine, if I could have hindred my love to you, I ſhould be guilty if I had not done it: and being ſo rational as I know you to be, you would your ſelfe ſecretly have condemned my affection, though it were advantageous to you. You would have more eſteemed in me the quality of Queen, than that of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and have rejoyced more for conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my kingdome than my perſon. So that to perſwade you all at once, both of the greatneſſe of this affection, and that I am not unworthy of your eſteeme no more than of your love, I ſhall never be weary with telling you, that 'tis a ſuperiour po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that cauſes us to love; that all the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and all the human prudence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring any obſtacle; and that in fine, 'tis only the inclination alone, which may bee ſaid the true mother of all loves. There is I know not what ſecret charme, which paſſes from the eyes of the lover into the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119710:23"/>heart of her whom the deſtinies do chuſe him for her beloved, whoſe power is inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as the moone governes the Sea, the north attracts the loadſtone, and the ſun formes the metals in the bowels of the earth, by means which are unknowne to us, ſo does the inclination conduct our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, attract our will, and formes the love in our ſoules, by waies of which we are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ignorant. She makes that wee often love, that which we do not know; and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to, that which is not very lovely, and which we would not love if we could help it. From whence thinke you does ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive ſo many ſtrange events in the world, of which Hiſtories are filled if it be not from that puiſſant Tyrany, which ſurmounts all others? If <hi>Anthonies</hi> Galley (whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures I have told you, and whoſe amours I learned ſince I left <hi>Aſia,</hi> and ſince my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Europe</hi>) could have (I ſay) been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by reaſon, and that it had not beene whirled away with violence, by the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that that Roman had, for the faire E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptian whoſe charmes hee did adore; do you believe he would not have ſtay'd in his army at the battel he loſt, or that at leaſt he would not have diſputed that victory
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119710:24"/>with his enemy? Yes <hi>Medoro,</hi> he was too wiſe, and too valiant, not to endeavour to winne, or to fly ignobly before thoſe, whoſe conquerour he might have been. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, though he were ambitious, though he were almoſt aſſured to have all the advantage of that day, and though it concern'd and ſtood upon the Empire of the whole World, his inclination was more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant in him than the deſire of glory, or of dominion. One may ſay moreover, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the illuſtrious example, that 'tis by the power of this inclination that ſo many bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have become enemies, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Rivals; that ſo many ſubjects have revolted againſt their Princes; that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Citizens have betrayed their Country; and that ſo many Hero's have committed faults of judgement, or done actions which were unworthy of them. All thoſe people <hi>Medoro,</hi> had not loſt their reaſon in the things which did not concerne their loves: they ſpake after the ſame manner as they were wont before, they were tainted with ſo great a malady; they acted in the ſame ſort, they thought of their owne affaires, and of their friends with the ſame prudence: wherefore then ſhould not the ſame reaſon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119710:24"/>be found in their love, if there had not been ſomething in them more powerfull than that was? Ha, no, no, <hi>Medoro,</hi> this truth cannot be doubtfull: and though I ſeeme to prejudice my ſelf in perſwading my ſelfe in ſatisfaction, that I finde nevertheleſſe ſo much ſatisfaction, that I cannot omit. For as I think I am certain that you love me, in the ſame manner as I would be; I hold my ſelfe more aſſured of your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than I ſhould be, if I believed that I held it by your acknowledgment rather than from your inclination. I love rather that you ſhould love my perſon than the throne whereto I wil lead you: and I had rather you ſhould eſteeme the tenderneſſe of my amity than the conqueſt of my kingdome, which I call no more ſo, but only to let you ſee that I can beſtow it on you. But (may one ſay perhaps) this ſame inclination, which makes you love to day, may alſo make you love no more too morrow: ſince in fine, you have been ſeen to love and hate <hi>Renaldo</hi> ſucceſſively, and that <hi>Renaldo</hi> hath likewiſe been ſeen both to love and hate <hi>Angelica.</hi> I acknowledge ingeniouſly; that this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is ſtronger than the other; and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe likewiſe that this thought has given
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119710:25"/>me ſome trouble in the firſt dayes of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. What (ſaid I in my ſelfe ſometimes when I conſidered the power of this inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which cauſed me to love you) ſhould it be poſſible, that one day I ſhould no more love <hi>Medoro?</hi> Should it be poſſible that <hi>Medoro</hi> one day ſhould love <hi>Angelica</hi> no more? and that this ſame inclination which unites our hearts and wills, ſhould diſunite them for ever? After ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a meditation, there ſucceeded a more pleaſing thought: for coming to conſider, that all thoſe that love, do not change their inclinations alwaies; I perſwaded my ſelfe, that we ſhould be of thoſe choſen lovers to ſerve as an example to poſterity. Yes <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doro,</hi> I beleeved that our affection never ſhould diminiſh: and I beleeve at preſent that in making you King, I do but only augment the number of my ſubjects; that by beſtowing my Crowne on you, I gain a faithfull ſlave; and in giving you my heart, I receive yours, never to be diſpoſed of again. 'Tis in this manner <hi>Medoro,</hi> that we muſt at leaſt flatter our ſelves in ſuch things to which we cannot abſolutely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: for if it happens as we wiſh it, it were a wrong to afflict our ſelves, without cauſe:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119710:25"/>and if it happen that the inclination do change its object, there is no need of being comforted for the loſſe of that, which we do no longer eſteeme to be worth our love. Lets then enjoy in peace the preſent felicity, without putting our ſelves in trouble for the future: let us leave the knowledge of things to come to deſtiny, ſince as well we cannot prevent them, neither by our fears or endeavours; lets imploy all the moments of our lives to ſpeake advantageouſly of the power of this inclination, which has created all our felicity, ſince it hath created our love; let us leave ſome marke of it in all places we paſſe by; lets make all the trees which lend us their ſhade, lend us likewiſe their barks to engrave the names of <hi>Medoro</hi> and <hi>Angelica,</hi> that all thoſe which ſee it, may admire and envy our happines; and to be ſhort, never let us ſpeake but of the pleaſure there is in hearts thus united, which inclination alone does beget; in compariſon of that, where reaſon or intereſt do mingle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or contribute any thing. Such who love only by thoſe two ſentiments, do not at all know the ſweets of love; reaſon is too ſage to ſuffer any of her ſubjects to ſet all their joy, in the poſſeſſion of a miſtres:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119710:26"/>how perfect ſoever ſhe may be; &amp; intereſt is too mercenary to ſuffer any one to make his greateſt treaſures conſiſt in the leaſt favour that can come from a Lady. If I were beloved by any of thoſe ſage lovers, who alwayes conſult with their judgments, and who oppoſe their inclination as much as they poſſibly can, whithout doubt they would love my Crowne, rather than a bracelet of my haire, and would preferre the luſter of my throne before that of my lookes. O <hi>Medoro</hi> how little do thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple know the nature of love? and indeed to ſpeake rationally, they ought not to be put amongſt the number of true lovers. All men are ot always equally touched with all paſſions: thoſe which are borne covetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and who ſometimes thinke they love, do wrong themſelves: for if we examine the thing well, we ſhall finde that they love their Miſtreſſes mony, and not the charms of her perſon. They follow their inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I confeſſe, but that which that inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion regards is not love, but 'tis avarice. An ambitious man acts in the ſame manner; a valiant man will wiſh for many rivals, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to have the glory of fighting and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming them; and briefly all thoſe, which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119710:26"/>are beleeved to be lovers, are not ſo ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily but in appearance: and 'tis this without doubt which makes ſo many be inconſtant and faithleſſe. For as their ſtrongeſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is not that which makes them love, there may happen a hundred things, which ſatisfying their covetouſneſſe, their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their vanity by other means makes them forſake their Miſtreſſes, as uſeleſſe to their felicity. But thoſe, who above all paſſions, are ſtrongly inclined to love, are more aſſured of the duration of their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and more happy in their ſervice. They part neither their cares, nor their hearts; Scepters and Crownes are not the ends of their deſires; but the certainty of being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly loved is the only thing they pretend to. Think a little (lovely <hi>Medoro</hi>) on the happy life that we have led in theſe woods, ever ſince that by the force of our inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we began to love. This cottage has ſerv'd me in lieu of a Palace, the freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this graſſe has ſeemed more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to me than the magnificence of the Throne, and the melody of theſe birds more charming than all the muſick that ever I heard in Europe. I have preferred the ſands of theſe rivulets, which environ us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119710:27"/>the mines of Gold in our Country: and the dew which we behold on theſe flowers: before the faireſt pearls that ere the Orient did produce. And all this <hi>Medoro</hi> becauſe I love you, becauſe we ſee together all theſe things, and becauſe both my inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that which you have for me, makes me, that I can ſee nothing with you which does not pleaſe, and which does not produce ſome joy. 'Tis that is (my dear <hi>Medoro</hi>) the true marke of an ardent paſſion: whoever can finde any part of his pleaſure elſewhere than in the perſon he adores, is not at all capable of this noble weakneſſe? and whoere is beloved and not being abſent from what he loves, does not think himſelf happy, ought to be blotted out from the number of lovers. For to ſpeak of things as they indeed are, thoſe that be lovers after the manner as I underſtand it, I mean in ſpight of their reaſon and wills, can never do ſo; where-ever they find their Miſtreſſes, they have nothing to deſire, and where-ever ſhe is not all is wanting, and nothing ſatisfies them. They would be weary in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt ſplendid Courts, although they were even ſeated on the Throne: and would eſteeme themſelves happy in a horrid
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119710:27"/>deſert, were they but bleſſed by the light of thoſe eyes they adore. Now as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their content is more limited than that of others, it is likewiſe more facile to content them; but for the reſt of men which cannot love, whoſe minds are a prey to ſo many paſſions; they need almoſt that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of this world ſhould contribute ſomething to ſatisfie them fully. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, would have in their diſpoſing, all the gold which the ſun has produced ſince the beginning of Age: the Courageous would have overcome all the Hero's, that nature ever brought forth in all the world: nor would ambitious Conquerours have leſſer then the Empire of the whole Univerſe. To ſatisfie the people there muſt be very much; or to ſay better, they muſt have either inchantments or miracles to make them become happy. But as for thoſe that know to love, and who lock up all their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity in the hearts of a ſervant, or a Miſtres they never have nothing to fear but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For, provided their Inclination do not deſtroy their felicity by changing its object; they neither fear the malice of men, nor the capricios of Fortune, nor any other of thoſe misfortunes, which may happen in the courſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119710:28"/>of their lives; ſo true it is, that their minds are diſintangled from all other thoughts, but ſuch as directly concerne their love. By this you may ſee, (my dear <hi>Medoro</hi>) of what nature that is, which I have for you. and that which I beleeve you have for me. You are to me inſtead of Parents, of Kingdome, and Crowne; and if I had not a deſigne to place it on your head, I think that without any deſire of re-aſcending the Throne, I ſhould oblige you to paſſe the reſt of our dayes, in this pleaſing ſolitude. But ſince I am confident you will more eſteeme the hand that ſhall crowne you, than the Crown it ſelfe, how glorious ſoere it may be; we muſt think of leaving this lovely deſert; we muſt return to the Kingdom of <hi>Cataya,</hi> we muſt make all the earth to ſee what the power of this Inclination can do; we muſt ſhew it what that is which ought to be called love; and make it behold in you, a lover without ambition, which this love has made a King; and in my perſon, a Queen not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent, which yet this ſame love, has made to become a ſubject.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb facs="tcp:119710:28"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANgelica</hi> was too witty not to perſwade, and <hi>Medoro</hi> too Amorous not to bee perſuaded. So that although <hi>Arioſto</hi> hath not told us what happened to them in the Indies; and though he have hardly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they Imbarked to goe; we may believe that the power of Inclination, rendered their love eternal; and as that alone had given it birth, ſo that alone made it last ever after.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:29"/>
            <head>AMARILLIS TO TITYRUS. The Third HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>THe great <hi>Virgil</hi> introducing himſelfe in the Eclogues of his Bucolicks, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of a Shepherd called <hi>Tityrus;</hi> does regret <hi>Rome</hi> and the Court of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> from whence he was abſent; and teſtifies he is little pleaſed with the woods and plaines. That hath given me place to introduce, likewiſe the ſhepherdeſſe <hi>Amarillis</hi> his Miſtres, who ſurpriſing him in this thought reproches him of the diſeſteeme he makes of their abode; repreſents its beauties to him; and comparing them to the defects of what he regrets, ſtrives to make him acknowledge, that the Country life is preferrable before that of Cities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119710:29"/>
               <head>AMARILLIS TO TITYRUS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Eaſe Illuſtrious Shepherd, ceaſe to regret the magnificence of <hi>Rome;</hi> do not diſturbe the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of our woods by unjuſt and inutile complaints; and be perſwaded, that whether for the pleaſingneſſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for the purity of manners, for the innocency of pleaſures, for the felicity of life, or for true vertue; our villages ought to be preferred before the pompe of the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Cities; and the ſimplicity of our Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, to the ſeats of the proudeſt Palaces. I acknowledge that the picture, which you have made me of that proud one, which dares vaunt to ſubject all the earth, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry different from that which I deſigne to ſhew you this day. In the one we ſee naught but Scepters and Crownes, and in the other
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119710:30"/>only Garlands of flowers and Sheephooks. In the firſt we ſee every where gliſtering the gold, pearls, and diamonds; and in this I am going to ſhew, you ſhall behold no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gold, than that of the beams of the Sun; no other pearls, than thoſe the dew drops on the ennamel of our meads; nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diamonds, than the liquid chriſtal of our fountains. But (ô <hi>Tityrus</hi>) how pure is that gold! how gratefull a luſter thoſe pearls do caſt! and how delicious is that morning chriſtal to thoſe, who do not let themſelves be deceived by deluding appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; who can diſcerne as they ought, the beauties of art and nature; and preferre with judgment a laſting felicity before a fading one! You will tell me (perhaps) that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me ſpeake in this manner, it would ſeeme that I have but little conſidered that magnificent daughter, which you have ſhewed me, of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Court; becauſe I do not condiſcend to agree, that you have cauſe to complaine for being abſent from it. It is true notwithſtanding, that I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of every ſtroake; and I confeſſe alſo, that at the inſtant thoſe great buildings of Marble, of Jaſper, and of Porphiry brought me in doubt whether I ſhould not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119710:30"/>preferre them before our Grotts. But I was not long in that errour; and although with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the portrait is a little flattered, that hath not hindred me from finding that you are in the wrong to ſpeake of <hi>Rome,</hi> as of a place to which nothing is wanting that may render an honeſt man happy; and of our forreſts, as of a dwelling where one can find nothing which might reaſonably ſatisfy a man of ſpirit. Let us examine all theſe things in order, I conjure you: and to oblige you to hear mee more attentively, and to perſwade you with greater power, I ſhall let you ſee that <hi>Rome</hi> is in my Imagination, ſuch as you have deſcribed it to me: that ſo by the oppoſition of the life at Court, and the Country life, I may by making you ſee the advantages and defects, draw you with the more facility to my judgment. You have told me (unleſſe I am deceived) that the beauty of the places we inhabit, does ſerve very much to render men happy; that brave objects does elevate the ſpirits; and that this being ſo (as I confeſſe it) <hi>Rome</hi> is the moſt charming abode upon earth, ſince 'tis there that the greateſt riches are found. You have (I ſay) aſſured me, that all the Temples are filled with the workmanſhip of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119710:31"/>the beſt Maſters of antiquity; that all the houſes are placed; that all the furniture is ſtately; that all the publick places are adorned, either with braſſe ſtatua's, or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant arches; and that in fine, ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſes within her walls, all that art can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce as marvellous, and all that is moſt rare in the univerſe. Lets ſee after this, unjuſt Shepherd, if in our ſolitude I can find ought wherewith to make you forget thoſe gallant things; and wherewith to make you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the Country life is to be preferred before that in Cities. I perceive that you find my deſigne too bold, and that you are troubled to comprehend, (you I ſay, who are out of love with the place where you were borne, and who have forgotten them) that out of <hi>Rome</hi> one can behold any thing that is wonderfull. Nevertheleſſe it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that there is a notable difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt all thoſe ornaments which imbelliſh that, and theſe of the places we inhabit. But is all that makes them brave, contrary to us, who enjoy all the beauties of nature. In fine that is but the works of men, and our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode is the maſter peece of the Gods. It is true, we have no Palaces, but if our Cottages be leſs magnificent, they are by
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119710:31"/>their low roofs, the more diſtant from thunders, and ſtormes. And then to ſay the truth, whoever ſhall ſtand to conſider the marvellous ſtructure of that rich Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py which covers our heads, will not regret the proudeſt ſeelings which are at <hi>Rome.</hi> But (you will tell me) it ſeems by your ſpeech, that the ſtarres, and the ſun do not ſhine on the Capitol each in their turns; and that <hi>Rome,</hi> is onely a place of obſcurity, and darkneſſe; I acknowledge it ſhepherd, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, and to make you acknowledg it your ſelfe, ſuffer me to ſhew you that, which without doubt you do not now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to have ever ſeen; I mean theriſing and ſetting of the Sun in our plains, either when we are in our woods, or that we walk along the margent of ſome of our rivers. Ha ſhepherd, if it be true, that brave ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects raiſe the Spirits, and that the marble, the jaſper, the porphiry, pearls, diamonds, and gold, raiſe pleaſing thoughts, what ſhould not the arrival of that faire planet do, when he appears in the horizon, he which hath communicated to all thoſe things, the little beauty they have? In effect, is there any thing more lovely in the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, than the magnificent entrance hee
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119710:32"/>makes each morning towards us? At <hi>Rome</hi> he is hardly ever ſeen without clouds: the foggs and the ſmoake vaile a part of his beams: one would ſay he were angry, to be imployed in that place, only to give light to cheats, flatterers, and to voluntary ſlaves. One would think (I ſay) that he hides a part of his light, becauſe his heat ſerves but to dry the myre in the ſtreets; whereas with us, when he begins to appear, he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe, but to diſſipate the innocent vapours which ariſe from the earth; and to dry up the pearls of dew, which moiſten our fields; to make our Roſes to blow, to give a freſh enamel to all our flowers; to paint the wings of our butterflies; and to receive the wiſhes of all the Shepherds of our Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage. And indeed it appears to us every day, with ſo much magnificence, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can equall his triumph: no ſooner do the firſt of his beams begin to ſhed the purple, the gold, and azure in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the skie, but all nature ſeemes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. The obſcurity of the night does diſſipate; the ſtars with reſpect diſappaer; the birds awake ſinging; our flocks are willing to go forth to the folds, &amp; all our Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes, who are never wearied
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119710:32"/>to behold the ſame thing, when it is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, alwayes admire more and more, that wonderfull treaſure of rich and lively co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, which overſpreads the clouds at his arrival. They admire (I ſay) thoſe faire im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of light, which he communicates to all the objects which are capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them: he guilds the crowns of our luminous beams, he pierces the thickneſſe of our forreſts, only to make them more pleaſant, and not to take away their freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or to diſſipate our ſhade. In the morning he permits us to look on him; at noone he ſuffers our woods to defend us from his ſcorching; and in the evening he ſhews us his Image in the rivers, and in our fountains, but ſo ſparkling, and ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that all the diamonds in the world cannot equal the beauty of the leaſt of his beams. When he renewes the day, he puts us in hope we ſhall quickly behold him by the proud preparation which fore-runs him: and when he robs it from us, he ſeems to aſſure us by the abundance of his riches, which he imployes to paint the heavens with Roſeat, ſhaddowed gold, and with all the colours the moſt lively, and others moſt ſhady, that his abſence ſhall not bee
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119710:33"/>long; and that in few houres we ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him again as bright as ever. Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge now ſhepherd by this weake draught I have traced, that there is nothing in <hi>Rome</hi> which is ſo handſome as this which I have repreſented to you. Yet this is not the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing that renders our habitations plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; there are places into which the ſun never comes, and yet they give delight; we have Grotts ſunke ſo deep into the conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of works, that the day hardly arrives there, and the night, who mingles her ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble complexion with his luſter, is never quite baniſhed thence. They are onely tapiſtred with moſſe, and yet the ſilence and cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which one meets, creates a pleaſure. There are muſes with tranquility and with ſweetneſſe: and if one were alone in Nature, may peaceably enjoy all the charms of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude. At the going forth from thence, you ſhall alwayes find a fountain, whoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ſo pure, it permits through its ſtreams to behold the diverſity of pebles, which are in the bottome of its bed. It makes but a weake murmur, fitter to rock aſleep with voluptuouſneſſe, than to keep awake with anger. The waters which flow thence from a rivulet, which ſerpentinely creeps
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119710:33"/>with a ſoft tread amongſt the pebles, reeds, and flowers, till it ſteals into a mead, where confounding it ſelfe amongſt others, which likewiſe moiſten it, they unite, and with their mingled waters, make a great and large river, whoſe ſtream and brink, cauſe a new divertiſement: and whoſe purity without doubt ought to be more gratefull to the ſight, than the muddy waters of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> Now if from theſe peaceable beauties you will paſſe to thoſe whoſe charmes are mingled with I know not what that's terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and which ſtrikes a horrour in their divertiſements; we have fearfull precipices; we have rocks, whoſe heads do reach the heavens; and from whence ſuch furious torrents deſcend, that their fall makes as great a noiſe as the thunder, or the Sea. One would ſay that they are mountaines of ſnow precipitating themſelves upon one another, ſo much thoſe waters foame, and to ſee them rowle, and bound with ſuch abundance and impetuoſity would make one beleeve they would overflow the whole earth. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, they are no ſooner diſgorg'd into a gulfe which is at the foot of that rock whence they Iſſue, but they hide themſelves in the cavernes, to go and render their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119710:34"/>without doubt to thoſe, from whence they proceed. Going from thence, ſhepherd, ſhall I conduct you into one of thoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, where we find a large tapiſtry of different flowers that overſpreads it; where you may ſee a hundred criſtal ſprings; where on the one ſide is ſeen a delightfull river; and on the other many willowes, Alders, and Lote trees, which by their ſhadow make their ſweet abode pleaſing, though the ſun ſcorch all beſides, and invites the ſhepherds to ſleep ſecurely? But perhaps you will not ſtay ſo long, lets go then (ſhepherd) lets go into one of thoſe foreſts, whoſe obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſilence, and antiquity ſeems to imprint reſpect in all thoſe which walk there. If that ſhady forreſt were at the gates of <hi>Rome,</hi> it would be filled only with theeves, or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive criminalls: whereas here we ſhall find none but ſtaggs, hinds, roe-bucks, and deers, you may gueſſe alſo by their numbers, that we do not often make toiles to catch them, and you ſhall ſee by the ſmall care they take to hide themſelves, that that place is a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary for them. All thoſe great ſpaces, whoſe deep ſhade is ſuch, that in the day you can hardly diſtinguiſh colours, and where one may almoſt doubt whether the foliage
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119710:34"/>be not black rather than greene; are not yet deſtitute of ſomwhat wherewith to divert the mind, and ſight of a melancholy ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd; and when by ſome windowes where the trees are leſs thick, the rayes of the ſun appears and diſſipates a part of that pleaſing night; there was never any thing ſo lovely as thoſe long twiſts of ſilver beams, which ſeeme as if they would force the obſcurity to yeild place to light. One would ſay by the agitation of the leaves, that they preſſe together, to hinder its entrance; but the more the wind makes them tremble, the more eaſie paſſage do they give to thoſe enemies of darkneſſe. Going from this Forreſt, will you let me guide you to the brink of a great pond, whoſe tranquility ſeldome failes to give reſt to thoſe minds which do but ſtop to admire its beauty? <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirus</hi> only curles its billowes; and he ſtirs them ſo ſoftly, that one may with eaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all the fiſhes which are at the bottome of thoſe waters, as clear as they are ſmooth. Some of them ſwimming with precipitation to ſeek their food; the others bound, and raiſe themſelves above the water: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more timorous, runne to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the leaſt noiſe they hear. If from
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119710:35"/>the bottome of this criſtal, you aſcend to conſider its ſurface, you ſhall behold it all cover'd with ſwans: admire (Shepherd) the whiteneſs of their plumage; the gravity they keepe in ſwimming; and the noble pride which ſtill appears in their looks: would one not ſay, they deſpiſe all they look on? and would not one Imagine alſo, that at ſome times they have a deſigne to pleaſe; when they make ſails of their wings only to delight; and ſwim about only to be admired? Ha, Shepherd, how farre are the inhabitants of <hi>Rome</hi> from theſe innocent pleaſures, and what delights does their troubleſome life rob them of! Nevertheleſſe I am not yet at the end of the deſcription of the places we inhabite; I muſt needs lead you up one of thoſe great mountains, from whence at once we diſcover the Rivers, Forreſts, Plains, and Paſtures; where the ſight is ſo unlimited, that the objects may ſeeme to ſteale from our view by their great diſtance, and the skie to kiſſe the furthermoſt parts we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. But perhaps you do not love an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of ſuch a vaſt extent: let me then ſhew you the way on our banks, and in our val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, that ſo I may make you acknowledge
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119710:35"/>that their fruitfulneſſe ſhould be preferred before the ſterility of <hi>Romes</hi> ſeven hills. Thoſe little corners of earth are ſo much favoured by heaven, that they ſeeme to be ever ſheltered from all the injuries of the ayre: the wind does hardly breath there; the hayle does not deſtroy the vines: the greene is eternal: and I truly believe, that if one ſhould not manure them, the Sun alone would produce and ripen, all what ever Agriculture brings forth elſewhere; not without much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and care. Now that we may not yet forget that which makes the liberality of our Shepherds; and that which is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent love of our ſhepherdeſſes: can you compare the Perfumes of <hi>Rome</hi> with the ſweeet odour of our Violets, of our Roſes, and our Gilliflowers? At leaſt there is this difference, that the one does but ſatisfie the ſmell; and that the other, beſides its gratefull perfume, pleaſes the eye infinitely. In effect, was ever any thing more faire to behold than this prodigious quantity of flowers, which fills our Gardens; either for their forme, for the briske and lively
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119710:36"/>colours, or the variety there is amongſt them? Believe me (ſhepherd) the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Tapeſtry which is at <hi>Rome</hi> does not ſhew any thing that is ſo wonderfull. The purple is not ſo faire, as the Incarnat of our Roſes: the Pearls of our Crowns Imperial, are more worth than Orient pearls: and the leaſt of our flowers deſerves more admiration than all that human art can invent. Now after I have made you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that which I call the ſuns maſter-piece follow me into this neighbour grove; 'tis there that you ſhall find that which is not to be found at <hi>Rome;</hi> 'tis there that you ſhall hear, that which is not heard in any City; and 'tis there you will be forced to confeſſe, that you muſt be inſenſible of pleaſures, if you preferre not the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try life before that of the Court. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then (I conjure you) that great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſhepherds, and ſhepherdeſſes, who daring the heat of the day, have led their flocks into the ſhade under the cloſeneſs of this grove: and without admiring the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe of ſome, or the beauty of others; ſince 'tis not in this place that I intend to ſpeak of that, hearken onely to what they liſten too; I mean that great quantity of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119710:36"/>birds, who by their different tones, make ſo pleaſant a conſort. Hearing them ſing ſo early, one would ſay they did ſtrive to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether who ſhould obtain reward of the victory. But amongſt others admire that learned maſter of muſick, who ſurpaſſes them all by the leaſt of his notes. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are all aſhamed of their unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; they leave off through impuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance and reſpect; and only the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales his fellowes try with equal armes to vanquiſh him, &amp; to overcome each the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hearken how admirably this does paſs his cadences; how he lets fall his voice; how he maintains it, how he renews it, and with what regularity he animates his ſong. That other which anſwers him, hath a particular charme, he is more lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and more amorous; but as he is more feeble, ſo I believe he will be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. Liſten how they redouble their ſtrengths; and you may even diſcerne a kind of joy, in him that finds he hath the advantage, and ſorrow, and anger in that which finds his ſtrength diminiſheth. Look ye (ſhepherd) he can ſing no more; his ſtrains are not ſo equal, though they be more frequent, the ſweetneſſe of his voice
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119710:37"/>does change; he ſings now onely out of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire; I can diſcover through thoſe leaves, that he ſtaggers, his clawes can no longer graſpe the branch, which upholds him; I ſee him tumble with vexation, and he in falling murmers yet ſome languiſhing notes, and does almoſt looſe his life before his voice. Thoſe (Shepherd) are the onely ambitious ones of our Country: compare thoſe with them of <hi>Rome</hi> (I conjure you) and although the deſtiny of this poore Bird bee worthy of pity; acknowledge that 'tis better am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition cauſe only the death of Nightingales, than that it ſhould ranverſe Thrones and Empires. Yet more (Shepherd) 'tis not in the ſpring time onely, in ſummer, and in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne, that we have the advantage above Cities, winter it ſelfe, how fearfull and ſharp ſoever 'tis diſcribed, hath ſomewhat amidſt its rigour which is fine, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in our fields. The ſnow, which in the Cities, looſes all its whiteneſſe, as ſoone as ere 'tis fallen, ot at leaſt conſerves its purity only on the houſe tops; does here make rich and curious plumes of the branches of our Cypreſſe, Cedars, and Firres. Thoſe trees (I ſay) whoſe leaves do not ſhed, mingling their verdure with its whiteneſſe, makes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119710:37"/>without doubt as pleaſing an object, as the ſummer can beſtow: and then, when th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> froſt, and ſharpeneſſe of the cold hath converted all our rivulets into Criſtal, we behold likewiſe all our trees laden with dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds. You will tell me, (it may be) that thoſe diamonds do not make us the richer: and that the Sun deprives us of what the cold beſtows. But (ſhepherd) if thoſe dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds do not enrich us, however they doe not make us become guilty: We cannot corrupt the fidelity of any one with them: nor imploy them in ſo many unlawfull uſes as you know they do at <hi>Rome.</hi> There is one thing more yet in the Cities, which ſeems to me not to be indured: which is, that one would ſay there is but one kind of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all the year long, to thoſe that inhabit them. They alwayes behold the ſame things; they have the ſame imployments; their houſes are alwayes alike; their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures do not vary: and except only that they have cold and heat, according to the divers temperatures of the ayre, there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens no change in their life: contrary to us, to whom nature every year renues four times, all the beauties of our dwellings. Each ſeaſon gives us a different occupation:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119710:38"/>The ſpring with its flowry chaplet calls us to take care of our medowes and flocks. The ſummer with its Coronet of wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ears, obliges us to the reaping of our harveſt: Autume with its garland of vine, invites us not to leave our grapes any longer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the pillage of paſſengers: and the winter all covered with ice, will have us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, render to the earth the tribute which each one owes it: that ſo another time ſhe may returne with intereſt thoſe graines, which we have ſowed in her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. O Shepherd, how innocent is this uſury; and how little it reſembles that which they practiſe in Cities, this beggars no body, by thus enriching ones ſelfe in this manner; one cannot either envie you for it, nor reproach you, nor accuſe you of any crime: but farre otherwiſe, the more you are carefull, the more you are praiſed: whereas the others care is alwayes blame-worthy, if they are not alwayes bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. They have more paine and leſſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; that which is acquired by unjuſt ways cannot be without doubt, poſſeſſed without diſquiet. They fear their enviers, their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and theeves; but for us we have neither enviers, nor enemies; Nor do we
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119710:38"/>fear any other robbers of our riches, than the birds, which ſteale ſome of our fruits: and which for all this, we would not baniſh from our Campaniaes, ſo much thoſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent criminalls, do give us delight in other reencounters. But to let you ſee, that for all your magnificent ſtructures of your Temples and your Palaces; for all your Marble, Jaſper, and Porphirie, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dornes them; and for all your aqueducts your Statuas, and your Triumphant arches we are however the true poſſeſſors of the braveſt things of Nature. You need but conſider, that <hi>Rome</hi> beautifies it ſelfe but with that which the earth locks in her bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells, and which ſhe conceals from the eyes of men: whereas we enjoy all that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe dreſſes her ſelfe, and with all that ſhe ſets forth to the view of the whole World. No Shepherd, they are not her treaſures, thoſe metals which are now a-dayes the Tyrants of the minds, and the corrupters of the moſt wiſe: If that were ſo, we ſhould behold trees laden with gold, with pearls, and jewels; ſhe would dreſſe her ſelfe with her faireſt ornaments; and would not leave imperfect, that which you call her chief works. The gold ſhould not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119710:39"/>need to be refined; we ſhould need no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidaries to cut the diamonds; nor no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which knew how to poliſh the pearls. All thoſe things would be in ſight, and would be as well finiſhed, in the inſtant they were produced, as are our flowers, our woods and our fountaines: Ceaſe then (ſhepherd) ceaſe to maintaine that the abode at <hi>Rome,</hi> is pleaſanter than that in our Country: and prepare your ſelfe in the remainder, to ſee the magnificence of your divertiſements, yeeld to the ſimplicity of ours. Of all the publick feſtivalls with which you have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained me, thoſe of the triumphs, and the combats of the Gladiators, are the moſt celebrous: But (ô <hi>Tityrus</hi>) thoſe feaſts, and playes, have ſomewhat that is tyrannical and wofull! and how hard it is to reaſonable people to rejoyce, in ſeing ſo many unhapy! that which is called delight, ought not to be mingled with bitterneſſe. Smiles and tears ſhould not be ſeen together: and blood ſpill'd in a battle it ſelfe, ſhould not delight how much leſſe then in paſtimes. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the moſt pleaſing which they have at <hi>Rome,</hi> is to ſee Kings in chains; and four thouſand gladiators cut one anothers throats for the pleaſure of Roman people.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119710:39"/>O Shepherd, what muſt thoſe people be, who delight to ſee rivers of blood &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of carcaſſes! for our parts, we who afflict our ſelves, when any of our lambs are ſick, we ſhould be far from rejoycing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thoſe miſerable ones dye ſo cruelly: or be ſatisfied to ſee Princes, and Princeſſes laden with fetters. For my part (Shepherd) ſhould I ſee ſuch a ſpectacle, I ſhould have more compaſſion for the vanquiſhed, than eſteeme for the vanquiſhers: In fine, to tell you the things as I believe them, I can ſee no innocent pleaſures in <hi>Rome;</hi> they inſulte over the unhappy, and they cauſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate ſlaves to periſh: they lead Kings captives, after they have uſurped their Kingdomes: and they heare, and they look on, not only without horrour, but with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, the laſt complaints and actions of dying men. <hi>Ceſar</hi> (as they ſay) wept after the Pharſalian Battel, over thoſe great numbers of bodies, which he beheld with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, and motion; but in <hi>Rome</hi> they laugh at that which made him weepe; and they call it a feaſt of rejoycing, which rather ſhould be named a publick mourning. See Shepherd, I intreat you, whether we are cruell or innocent in our paſtimes; and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119710:40"/>whether in reminding you of them, you will not acknowledge that if there be leſſe pompe, there is more wit, more skill, more equity, and alſo more pleaſure. Repaſſe then in your imagination, one of thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral holidayes of all our hamlets, or one of thoſe ſacrifices, after the reaping of our harveſt: did you ever ſee any thing more pleaſing, than to ſee, not Kings manacled in fetters; not Gladiators all covered with blood and wounds; but an innumerable number of Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes, with coronets and garlands of flowers; with ſuch a joy in their countenance, as is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to all that behold them? ſome have their bag-pipes, others their flutes; ſome of them lead the victimes, the others carry the conſecrated veſſels; the one raiſes an altar of turfs, the other puts the fire which enkindles it; and almoſt every one hath ſheephooks imbelliſhed with mottoes, figures, and ribons. The neatneſs of their cloaths, ſerves alſo to make them the more amiable; 'tis not proud indeed, but it is gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. The purple and the jewels do not ſhine there; but their pure whiteneſs, &amp; thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding jewels, which the ſpring, the ſummer, &amp; autume, beſtowes each year upon us, does
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119710:40"/>make amends enough for that want, and for the reſt, the beauty of my companions (if I am not deceived) ought not to yeild to that of the Roman Ladies: you will tell me (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) that though it were true, that the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of their faces were as ſweet, and their countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces as pleaſing; at leaſt I ſhould not deny, that the tan of the fields ſpoyles their skins, and deſtroys its freſh colour. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the thick umbrage of our forreſt, defends them from that enemy; I muſt alſo tell you, that the tan is more becoming, and ſupportable, than painting, and that nature is more charming than artifice. For our parts, Shepherd, we appear ſuch as we are: we have no other looking laſſes than our fountains, no other Fucus than the dew; and yet there are maids amongſt our woods, whoſe complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo wonderfull, that it out-vies, and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies the whiteneſſes of the lilies, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate of the faireſt roſes. The modeſty of their actions; the ſincerity of their diſcourſe; &amp; the ſerenity which appears in their looks, are ſuch things as are only fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in our filds, Every where elſe there is nothing but diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation &amp; art; they ſee to be ſeen; they make no conqueſt without deſigne; that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears faire, is not ſo; and one is ſometimes as much deceived in the perſon as the mind.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119710:41"/>
               <p>But let's return, Shepherd, let's return to that faire aſſembly, where our ſage Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who are the witneſſes and judges of our ſports, do already prepare the rewards for thoſe which ſhall overcome in this holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. You ſhall know by the ſimplicity of their worth, that it is not through a deſire of coveteouſneſſes, that they deſire to win: ſince thoſe prizes, which are ordained for the Shepherds (as you know better than my ſelfe) are only baskets, and ſheephooks, and pipes, and bag-pipes, and darts: and for the Shepherdeſſes, crowns of flowers, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of reeds, noſegeys, and ribons, and yet we take as much care to winne, as if it were to conquer the whole world. But Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, we need no weapons to obtain this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; we need not ſpill blood to defeat theſe enemies: we do not lead thoſe in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, over whom we have had the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; on the contrary, we embrace them, inſtead of enchaining them; we tell them they are the sillfulleſt, though they were not the happieſt; and in fine, we ſtrive to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them of this ſmall diſgrace. Running, wraſtling, dancing, poetry, and muſick (if I be not deceived give more divertiſment, than all the combats of Gladiators. He
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119710:41"/>whoſe courſe is nimble; he that wraſtles with the greateſt ſleight; he who dances with the beſt grace; he who makes the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt verſes; and he who ſings the trueſt, gives without diſpute more ſatisfaction, than thoſe combates of Tigers, and Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of which you make ſo much. Think Shepherd, think ſeriouſly, whether you ſhould not love rather to ſee the Shepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Galathea</hi> dance, or to hear the fair <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coris</hi> ſing, than to behold a lyon tear out the throat of a Tiger, or an Elephant over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw a Rhinoceros? Yes Shepherd, you would love it better, I read it plain enough in your face, that you will agree to what I ſay; and I think likewiſe, that you had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee thoſe two handſome maidens (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they otherwhile captivated you, than to be ſpectator of the moſt magnificent Triumph that ever <hi>Rome</hi> did ſhow, though <hi>Augustus</hi> ſelfe were Conquerour. Do not bluſh Shepherd, for that little reproach I make you; do not repent you of all the brave verſes, which you have compoſed for their glory; and be not aſhamed that you have ſo often carried away the prizes of our exerciſes againſt the cunning <hi>Melibeus,</hi> the active <hi>Coridon,</hi> againſt the daring <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalcus,</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119710:42"/>and againſt the ingenious <hi>Mopſus,</hi> in the ſight of our ſageſt ſhepherds; and if from the publick holy-dayes, you will paſs to thoſe innocent warres, which makes one of our greateſt pleaſures; I mean our hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and fiſhing: you will again bee forced to acknowledge, that <hi>Rome</hi> is not acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all that is capable to pleaſe; ſince ſhe cannot give theſe gratefull occupations, to thoſe which inhabit there. And yet 'tis certaine, that one can hardly find any thing fitter to delight, than to behold many Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſes with angles in their hands, and all keeping a profound ſilence, for fear leaſt the noyſe they ſhould make ſhould fright away the fiſhes they would catch, and make them ſhunthe ſhore. The one makes ready her bait on the brink; the other caſts her line into the river, and appears almoſt her own ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua, ſo attentive ſhe is to what ſhe is about. This by an action as quick as it is pleaſant, lifts up her arme, drawes the line, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced at her prey, caſts a fiſh upon the ſhore, which bowes it ſelfe, ſtretches, turns, winds, and beats, makes divers leaps and bounds upon the graſſe, and makes its rich ſilver ſcales to gliſter, amongſt the emeralds of the field. The other hoping for the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119710:42"/>ſame ſucceſſe of her fellow, drawes hers without drawing any thing; at which the reſt laugh or are comforted, for having a like fortune. But that which is the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, is to ſee our Shepherds laden with nets, to draw ſome fiſh-pond; there 'tis that when they are happy, you ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold when they draw their nets a living wave which ſpreads upon the brink, by the multitude, and the diverſity of the fiſhes they take; ſome of them skip up above the net; others break it; ſome bound upon the greene; others more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſave themſelves; others again entangle themſelves the more by ſtriving to diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage themſelves; and altogether do their utmoſt to ſave their lives, and to eſcape from that which does detaine them. But 'tis in vain they beat; as ſoone as they have changed their element, they muſt dye, the freſhneſſe of the graſſe is not to them, ſuch as is the freſhneſſe of the water. This paſtime how ſimple ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is, is not yet ſo poor, but that queens as well as ſhepherds have imployed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with it; <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> who had had the glory to catch the hearts of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and <hi>Mark Antony</hi> in her nets, did not ſcorne to fiſh,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119710:43"/>to caſt the line, and made it one of her moſt ordinary gallantries. But Shepherd, if there be any pleaſure in deceiving the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent fiſh, there is no leſſe, in deceiving the birds; ſometimes in hiding from them that which ſhould take them, under the heap of grain which is throwne to them, that ſo in coming to ſeeke wherewith to live, they find their death; ſometimes in ſhooting them with bolts; and ſometimes in ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them on the trees, by lyming the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which hold them by the wings, the more they flutter and ſtrive to flie, the more they are entangled amongſt thoſe dangerous twiggs. After theſe harmeleſſe exerciſes either of fiſhing, or bird-catching, you ſhall ſee the one and the other return with their prey; the Shepherds returns with great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier baskets filled with fiſh; the Shepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes carry cages of reeds, where they have kept alive ſome birds which have pleaſed them; and altogether not forgetting the care of their ſheep, return to their cottages. Thoſe which have beene ſucceſsfull, though laden with their ſpoile, do not omit to ſing ſome Eclogue, or play on their pipes; the flocks follow their maſters, or their miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; the doggs by their fidelity, take care
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119710:43"/>that no ſheepe ſtraggle; and the ſheep and oxen, by their loud clamours, advertiſing thoſe that are in their cabins, that the fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or chaſe is ended; they all come with much haſte and joy to know the ſucceſſe. But 'tis too much, Shepherd, 'tis too much ſpoken of our innocent warre, which (if I do not deceive my ſelf) ought to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to thoſe which have cauſed the proudeſt Trophies to be raiſed, and whoſe Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours have obtained the moſt magnificent Triumphs: Let's come then (if you pleaſe) to ſomewhat that is more ſolid; and let's compare the vices of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the vertues which are ſeene amongſt us. Firſt, <hi>Rome</hi> is filled with adulators, and we know hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what adulation is: at <hi>Rome,</hi> falſhood, and mediſance reigns; and in our woods the truth appearing alwaies, we never faile to praiſe that which is praiſe-worthy: at <hi>Rome</hi> all men are ſlaves, either to their ambition, or avarice; and in our campaniaes, we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe more goods, than we deſire to have; nor are we covetous, but only of time, which we would alwayes well imploy at <hi>Rome,</hi> there are thoſe people which make their treaſures of the greateſt poiſons which are in nature, either to make away their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119710:44"/>or to make away themſelves, if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that they are to be puniſhed for their crimes; and amongſt us, we make our dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt treaſures, of ſalutary herbs, which can heale the bitings of ſerpents, or any other venemous beaſt. At <hi>Rome,</hi> all the world thinks only upon their owne intereſt; here, they only thinke on their own pleaſures, provided it be harmeleſſe. At <hi>Rome</hi> all thoſe which inhabit it ſeeke to aproach near the Prince: in our woods we only ſeek our equalls. At <hi>Rome,</hi> they will have no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and yet deny not to kiſſe the hand that inchains them; and in our hamlets, we obey our ancient Shepherds, with as much affection as freedome. At <hi>Rome</hi> thoſe which make the Lawes ſcoffe at them, and do not obſerve them; and in our forreſts, the ſageſt Paſtors inſtruct by their examples, rather than by their words. Yes we doe what they doe, ſooner than what they tell us: nor doe we know amongſt us, any infringers of our lawes, or our cuſtomes. At <hi>Rome</hi> the riches alone, makes the difference twixt men: and in our Groves, vetue and merit only makes the price and the diſtinction. In fine Shepherd, at <hi>Rome,</hi> all the world is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119710:44"/>buſied to deceive others; or at leaſt to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that they bee not themſelves cozened; whereas we are only carefull to ſeeke the occaſions to ſerve our ſelves. If any of our Sheperdeſſes have ſometimes ſtragled that ſheepe from her flock which ſhe loves beſt; you ſhal ſee all our Shepherds with care, and earneſtneſs ſeek to recover again, that which ſhe loſt. They enquire with diligence; they tell to thoſe whom they meet, all the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that prety creature, that thereby they may know if they have not ſeen it. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe its whiteneſs, its marks, the flowers &amp; the ribons which are tyed to its hornes, and forget nothing which may ſerve to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, and if it happens that they find it, they return with as much joy, as your Conſuls, when they have gained a battel; ſo true it is, that we ardently love to ſerve, not onely our friends, but all thoſe that have need of it. As for <hi>Rome,</hi> without doubt it is not ſo there; all the world rejoyces at anothers misfortune: thoſe whom the Prince does not behold with a pleaſed eye, are forſaken by thoſe whom they have moſt obliged, what vertue ſoever they have: &amp; thoſe on the contrary whom he favours, ſhould they be the moſt vitious, and imperfect of men, ſhall not want however,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119710:45"/>not onely to have friends, but adorers and ſlaves. It does not go in this ſtrain in our Campaniaes; we ſee nothing above us but the heavens; we have neither Princes, nor favorites to fear, or follow; we live with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality; we love thoſe that love us, and hate none. For the reſt, I had alwaies heard ſay, that the Shepherds were the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Soveraigns; that they ought to governe the people as we govern our flocks; and that the Scepter and the Crooke, ought to have much reſemblance. Nevertheleſſe after the manner that things are reported to us, there is a notable difference betwixt them; or to ſay better, there is nothing at all alike. We love our flocks with tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; we have no other care than to make them happy; we chuſe them the ſweeteſt paſture, the cleareſt waters; we give them a couragious and faithfull keeper, which is our dog; and we defend them our ſelves with the hazard of our lives, when the wolves do aſſault them; we take care not only to nouriſh and keep them, but to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them likwiſe, both from the extream cold and the extream heat: in winter we leave them ſometimes in the folds, when the froſt hath glazed all the paſture: and in ſummer
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119710:45"/>when the ardour of the ſun ſcorches them, we ſeek ſuch ſhades as may defend them from all inconveniences. When they are ſick, we get ſuch remedies as are proper for their maladies: and when they are health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, we adorn them with ribons and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. It is not thus with many Princes, who ought to be Paſtors: they will not love their flocks, nor care to be beloved by them, provided they be feared; they make uſe of the ſheephoke rather to affright than to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, or defend them; in lieu of chuſing the paſture, and waters for them, they make their flocks ſeve their needs, and their mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence: inſtead of keeping them as we do, reverſing the order and rule; 'tis the flocks that muſt keep the Sheperds; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (I ſay) it ſhould be their parts to preſerve them from all harmes; 'tis they who on the contrary are the cauſe of all evils every day unto them, when they are ſick, they are ſo far from ſeeking remedies for them, that they augment their trouble by their tyrannies: and when they are ſound, they do not uſe to adorne them, but rather ſtrip them even of their natural ornaments. We indeavour our flocks ſhould be fat, &amp; they will have theirs lean &amp; feeble; in fine, Shepherds, not content
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119710:46"/>to take off their fleeces, wherewith they after make their richeſt robes, they tear them from their bodies with ſo much violence, that one may ſay, the purple which adornes them borrowes its colour from the blood of their flocks, rather than the induſtry of thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent artiſans, of whom they make ſo much eſteem at <hi>Rome.</hi> Ha, Shepherd! If we had ſuch Paſtors amongſt us, we would baniſh them from our meadows; we ſhould eſteeme them worſe than the wolves, which are the declared enemies of our ſheep; and we would degrade them from that honourable employment, by taking away their ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hook, their ſcrip, flute, bag-pipe, and all the glorious marks of our innocent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Ha, <hi>Tityrus</hi> (yet once more) what a dangerous thing 'tis for one to be a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, that is not a good Paſtor! and how much better it were to take a ſimple ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd to be King, than to have a King that could not be a Shepherd! I know you will tell me, that we have now gotten a Prince, whoſe ſweetneſs, clemency, and goodneſs, deſerve that we ſhould give him the name of Paſtor, rather than Tyrant: and that <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſince he hath gathered his flock, is one of the beſt Shepherds that ever bare
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119710:46"/>a Sheephook. But tell me a little, how many flocks has he deſolated, to make this one? How much blood hath he ſpilt, how many Paſtors hath he throatled? how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wolves, Panthers, and Tigers have bin imploy'd to make deſerts of the faireſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of this Empire? &amp; how many innocent lambs have felt his fury, before they taſted his clemency? Speak Shepherd, I conjure you, and anſwer me punctually. No, no, I perceive by your ſilence, that you cannot contradict me; and that you are conſtrained to acknowledge, that there might be found more Paſtors which would be good Princes, than Princes capable to be good Paſtors. In effect, the felicity of the country life, hath not been ſo much unknown in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, but that thoſe whom ſhe files in the ranks of her moſt Illuſtrious Hero's have imbraced it, with ardour. Yes, thoſe who after they had gained battels (as you know better than my ſelfe) have manured the ground with their own hands, and have alſo in the preſſing affaires of the Republick, been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called from thence to rule the reyns of the Empire; and from the plough to the head of an army; and from their ſolitude, to the Court. And yet, thoſe people, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119710:47"/>they have done, that's great, or good, have never been praiſed more, than when they had governed the publick, taken Cities by force; leſſened the bounds of the Roman puiſſance; gained Battels; and merited the honours of triumph, they have been ſeen to refuſe thoſe honours, return from the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to their ſheepcoat; from the head of an army to the plough; and from the Court to their ſolitude again. After this Shepherd, complain no more of your deſtiny: and be not ſo unjuſt as not to think any thing ſo pleaſing as the magnificence of of <hi>Rome:</hi> ſince our ſimplicity, is as much worth as their artifice. And if from their manners in general we paſſe to the paſſions in particular; you ſhall find, that of all thoſe that uſe to cauſe the grandeſt diſorders, we know but one onely, and which produces none but gratefull effects amongſt us. Firſt, ambition does not torment us; we are Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds Children, we will be only that, and can be no more. Our deſire having no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, we wiſh for nothing, we live without diſquietneſſe as without pride; and ſeeing nothing beneath us, nor nothing above our heads but the Heavens; we are free from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſolence; nor would we exchange
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119710:47"/>our ſheephooks, for all the Scepters in the world. It is eaſie for you to judg that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ambitious we know not either, avarice, nor envy, ſince theſe are two paſſions, which are almoſt inſeparable from the other. Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is but little more acquainted with us: nor does hatred finde any entrance in a Country where all deſerves to be loved. But (you will aske me) what is then that paſſion, which uſeth to produce ſuch ſtrange diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Cities, and makes known no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than pleaſing effects in your Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niaes? For as for me, 'tis ſo long that I have not lived there, that I have loſt the remembrance? It is <hi>Tityrus</hi> the moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, and nobleſt of all: 'tis that which made <hi>Hercules</hi> ſpin; which fired <hi>Troy;</hi> which hath r'enverſed ſo many Empires; which hath cauſed ſo many ruins in all the corners of the world; which hath made ſo many warres; which gave <hi>Antony</hi> to <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra; Auguſtus</hi> to <hi>Livia;</hi> and 'tis in fine, that paſſion, which is borne amidſt delights flowers, woods, brooks, meads, Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, and Shepherdeſſes, with more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and leſſe bitterneſſe, than on the Throne, and in the Palaces of great Kings. 'Tis in thoſe elevated places, that this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119710:48"/>which they call love, is almoſt always dangerous: a lover that gives law to all the world is not very fit to receive it from a miſtreſs. He will have the things which he deſires, more magiſtically than others: and when he encounters any obſtacle in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, that crowned ſlave that is not accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to obey; and is wont to be obeyed of all that approach him; that ſlave (I ſay) quits his chains, revolts, remounts the throne, and becoming a Tyrant to her, whoſe captive he was, he oftentimes makes her ſuffer ſad and funeſt adventures. But amongſt us on the contrary, that little god, whoſe puiſſance hath no limits, never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in our woods, but with the ſociety of his Mothers graces: he inſpires none but reaſonable deſires in the hearts of our Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds; we ſee them kiſſe their chains, even when the rigour of their miſtreſſes makes them ſeeme moſt heavy to them; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their favours with raviſhment; and when they are ill entertained, their diſcretion and patience, does oblige them to undergoe that misfortune, with reſpect and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They are alwayes our ſlaves, and by conſequence they never are our Tyrants. We have Shepherdeſſes which are rigorous,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119710:48"/>but we have no Shepherds which are indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet; they dare hardly proclaime their complaints, with their bagpipes and on their reeds; their verſes, their ſongs, and their entertainments, are filled onely with our praiſes; all our trees are engraved with their inſcriptions, and ours mixed together: and all their ſpeeches, gives us every day new marks, either of their eſteeme, or of their affection. Conſtancy (that vertue which ſo few practice in the Cities) is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly found amongſt us; the equality of our conditions, and of our riches, makes that the weakeſt do remain conſtant; there is neither ſcepter, nor gold, nor diamonds, which can dazle, or bribe them; the wiſe amongſt us deſpiſe them, and the reſt do not know what they are: We doe not ſee a husband here repudiate many wines as at <hi>Rome,</hi> the lovers do not ceaſe to be ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven after marriage: they will not obtain us to ſlight us afterwards; they take a care of the conqueſt they have made, and think themſelves glorious to wear but one chaine in all their lives. Nor are our Shepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes likewiſe more unfaithfull: their ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and their freeneſſe is the cauſe they do not diſguiſe their thoughts. They are
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119710:49"/>modeſt and ſincere; and if a little jealouſie (in ſpight of ſo many vertues which ſhould hinder it from ſpringing) did not diſturb the tranquility of our meadowes; all our Roſes would be without prickles, &amp; al our pleaſures would be without mixture, and without bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe. This paſſion nevertheleſſe does not act here, as at <hi>Rome;</hi> in that place, they have recourſe to violence. The poyſons, and ponyards are put in uſe; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſerve equally againſt the Rivall, and againſt the Miſtreſs alſo. But here, the greateſt hurt which happens to us, is that we perceive the complexion of the faireſt maids to become pale; and the flocks of our carefulleſt Shepherds, to feele the trouble of their Maſter; who paſſing away their ſorrow in the darkeſt foreſts, abandon them to the care of their friends. Yet how-ever this retreat does not make us ſee many mournfull events; and for the moſt part, ſome complaint, ſome ſong, and fome few Poems, is all the revenge, and the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement of the moſt jealous. If it be the Shepherdeſſe that's diſpleaſed, her lover is again brought to her feet, ſad and changed as he is, She hears him, receives his juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, if he be innocent, and pardons him if
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119710:49"/>he be guilty, if ſo be, he repents, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plores his pardon hadſomely, and with a good grace. And if on the contrary ſhe be in the wrong; we condemne her to make with her own hands a garland of flowers for him; and ſometimes alſo we conſent, that he ſhould robb her of a bracelet of her hair, after that, their felicity is founded more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly then before; and the innocency of their life, juſtifying all their pleaſures, they remain the happieſt in the world. The Shepherd takes care of his Miſtreſſes flock they go almoſt ſtill together on the ſame paſtures; they ſeeke out the ſame ſhades; and the ſame fountaines; their ſheephooks have the ſame devices painted; their baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets tyed with the ſame ribons; their ſheep adorned with the ſame colours, and their very doggs ſeeme to have contracted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a particular amity. This happy ſtate conſidered, as it ſhould be, is it not true ſhepherd, that the love of <hi>Rome,</hi> ought to be portray'd otherwiſe than ours; it ſhould be repreſented like a fury; he ſhould have more than one bow, and more than one torch given him, ſeing the diſorders he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: he ought to beare a Scythe, as well as Saturne, and death, ſince he deſtroyes all
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119710:50"/>that time and death deſtroy. He orethrowes all as well as they; he never inſpires the deſires of love in a heart; but that hatred, jealouſie, and anger, ſteps in preſently after. But for that love which inhabits our woods, he never muſt be repreſented but upon flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; his wings muſt be enamel'd with the ſame colours of the Rainbow, and his eyes ſhould be hoodwinkt with a very thin vail, his ſhafts and quiver adorned with roſes and peſſeminds, his skin muſt be white and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnadine, the pleaſures and graces muſt not abandon him, his innocency muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in all his actions, and his torch ſeem to be in his hands, rather to lighten than to annoy us. Judge, Shepherd, after all this which I have ſaid now to you, whether <hi>Rome</hi> ought to be preferred to the Countrey life? we inhabit natures faireſt ſeats, we poſſeſs all the true riches, we enjoy the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of all innocent pleaſures, we are not too diſtant from the moſt ſolid vertue, our cuſtomes are not unjuſt, we are free from ambition, and behold nothing above us; what can we wiſh for more, or what more can you deſire? yield then, Shepherd, yield to reaſon, to my prayers, to my perſwaſion, and to your own knowledge, who without
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119710:50"/>doubt would not indure, that I ſhould give you the quality of Shepherd, if you did not eſteem it glorious. So many Verſes and Eclogues which you have made do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie better than I can, the advantages of the Countrey life; it will ſuffice, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member one day, that <hi>Tityrus,</hi> after he hath ſung the great acts of <hi>Aeneis,</hi> (as he hath deſigned) hath not diſdained to accord his Reeds and Bag-pipe with our skilfulleſt Shepherds: do not then remember any more to be perſwaded of what I deſire you, neither the Sun which I have deſcribed ſo luminous, nor our Rivers whoſe waves are all ſilvered, nor our Fountains of Cryſtal, nor the Emeralds of our fields; nor thoſe lofty Mountains, whoſe proſpect is ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; nor thoſe Torrents, whoſe falls, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſeem fearful, do yet afford di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement: do not ſo much as think any more, I ſay, of our gloomy Foreſts, nor of thoſe ponds cover'd with Swans, nor of our Hillocks, nor of our Valleys, nor of the lovely diverſity of our Flowers, nor our Woods, or the Muſick of our Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingales, nor of the advantage we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Cities in all the Seaſons of the Year. Forget, I ſay, if you can, the beauty
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119710:51"/>of our Shepherdeſſes; cancel the memory of our holydayes, of our ſacrifices, of our Chaces, of our Fiſhing, of the innocency of our Manners, and of <hi>Amaryllis</hi> her ſelf. But remember at leaſt, that you may never ſpeak any thing againſt the Countrey life; that at your departure from <hi>Rome</hi> you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Shepherd as you were before. That you have born the Scrip, and Sheep-hook; and that with the ſame hand with which you are going to write <hi>Dido's</hi> complaints, and the <hi>Trojan</hi> Princes praiſes, you have written <hi>Tityrus</hi> his moans to the Shepherdeſſe <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea,</hi> and the praiſes of the Countrey life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb facs="tcp:119710:51"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>THe Reader may believe that this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was perſwaſive; ſince <hi>Virgil,</hi> who is the ſame with <hi>Tityrus,</hi> regrets <hi>Rome</hi> but only that one time in all his <hi>Buco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> though he were <hi>3</hi> years compoſing them. He imployed again afterwards ſeven more in compoſing his <hi>Georgics,</hi> a Work of the ſame nature, and the which contains all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Occupations. Thus may one (as I have ſaid) without putting our Imaginations on the rack, believe that <hi>Amarillis</hi> did in ſome ſort perſwade <hi>Tityrus:</hi> and that the diverſity of this great Land-ſcept artificially painted, and boldly traced, diſpleaſed not his ſight.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:52"/>
            <head>CLORINDA TO TANCRED. The Fourth HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>EVery one knows that in <hi>Taſſo's Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem Tancred</hi> kills his Miſtres <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> without knowing her. But every one knowes likewiſe that ſhe knowes him not neither, and dies without hardly ſpeaking. I do not doubt therefore but that I ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of falſifying the History (if at leaſt a fable may have that name) and that I ſhall be found ſtrangely bold, to dare to make a <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine</hi> to ſpeak, which ſo famous an Authour hath ſilenc'd. Beſides that tis to ſay that which he never ſaid, they will finde him yet more judicious then I, for not having put ſo long a Diſcourſe in the mouth of a dying perſon.
<pb facs="tcp:119710:53"/>But I confeſs, that maugre all thoſe objections on the which it is apparent that I have thought, ſince I make them my ſelf before any other offers them; I was not able to reſist ſo pleaſing a temptation. It alwayes ſeem'd to me in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this paſſage of that marvellous Poem, that <hi>Taſſo</hi> had not entirely drawn all that might be drawn: and that ſince he was the Master of <hi>Clorinda's</hi> deſtiny, he might have allowed her ſome moments of life, to render the adventure more tender; and the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Tancred</hi> more pitiful, by the things that ſhe might ſay to him. May the Reader then ſuffer, that as <hi>Bayardo</hi> and <hi>Arioſto</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſaid, that 'tis <hi>Turpin</hi> which hath ſaid what they invented. I may ſay alſo, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Hiſtorian than <hi>Taſſo</hi> aſſures, that the wound with the ſword was leſs great; that <hi>Clorinda</hi> lived ſome hours, and that ſhe ſpake very neer in theſe terms to the Generous <hi>Tancred</hi> to perſwade him, <hi>That the Love ought not to die with the Beloved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:119710:53"/>
               <head>CLORINDA TO TANCRED.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have overcome, illuſtrious and valiant Knight; I reſign my ſword to you with my life: and you have moreover this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to hear from the mouth of that perſon whom you have vanquiſhed, that you are worthy to be her vanquiſher. But whence comes the ſadneſſe which appears on your face, and in your actions? Is it poſſible there ſhould be found a man ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, to weep for his own Victories, and to mourn the death of his enemies? Ceaſe, couragious Knight, ceaſe to regret my loſs; and remember that I wanted but little of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe of yours. But once again, that which I behold, and that which I hear, can it be true? Ha! I do not doubt it, I now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119710:54"/>my deliverer; I hear that ſame voice, which in the midſt of battels hath often appeared to me, ſo terrible and ſo charming: nor do I wonder now to ſee him weep at my death, who had ſaved my life. Yes, generous Prince, I do remember that great day, which gain'd you ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; where, prompted by that noble am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, to overcome in you the valianteſt &amp; moſt couragious of all men, I purſued you ſo obſtinately, that my boldneſſe, or rather my raſhneſſe, gave you an eſteem for me: you did not onely forbear to aſſault me, and neglect to defend your ſelf when I aſſaulted you, but you defended me from all thoſe that came againſt me; you became contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to that party of which you were before, onely in conſideration of me; you purſued your own, as your enemies, becauſe they were mine; and all your actions did confirm to me better than your ſpeeches, that either by the power of your fate, or by your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination <hi>Clorinda</hi> had touched your illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart. Ha! may the heavens grant me ſome moments of life, to return you thanks for ſo much generoſity, and to comfort you for the ſadneſs I have cauſed in you. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive well, <hi>Tancred,</hi> I perceive that you
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119710:54"/>think of going to ſeek ſome remedies for the wounds which I have received from your hand: But if it be true, that I have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny power over you (as your tears ſeem to perſwade me) do not abandon me, I conjure you, to the inſolence of your ſouldiers, at this time, when the miſerable <hi>Clorinda</hi> hath no other arms to defend her ſelf, than her complaints and ſighs. Alſo the wounds I have received are ſuch, that there is no ſhare in life more for me. Ha! would the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens yet once more prolong it in me a little, for ſome inſtants that I might teſtifie my acknowledgment. It ſeems to me my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is heard; for although I feel that the hour of my death is neer, it ſeems to me, I ſay (if I deceive not my ſelf) that I have cauſe to believe I ſhall not expire, till I have related to you a part of thoſe thoughts that are in me: Do not fear, that I ſhall complain of you, or of fate; I have too great a ſoul, too firm, and too reaſonable, to have a reſſentment ſo vulgar, ſo weak, and ſo unjuſt. I know that in Battels one finds as often death as victory; that one muſt equally prepare for the one and the other; and that if ſo be we be overcome without ſhame or baſeneſſe, we ſhould loſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119710:55"/>ſuch a victorie without deſpair, &amp; die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out murmuring. I do not then regret the portion of life which I might yet have had: mine hath been long enough ſince it hath been unſpotted: I have lived little, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, but I have lived with glory, and I die with honour. If <hi>Clorinda</hi> muſt be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, it muſt needs have been by him who uſes to overcome all others: 'tis no ſmall thing for her to have diſputed with him for that illuſtrious prize as ſhe hath done; and not to have yielded, but onlie becauſe nothing can reſiſt him. Do not mourn for me then, more than I mourn for my ſelf; rule your reſſentments by mine; comfort your ſelf as I am comforted, and be not more ſenſible of my misfortune than your own intereſt. If you behold me as your enemy, you will rejoice at my loſs; all <hi>Godfreys</hi> armie will give you thanks for this action, for though I be of that ſex from which ordinarily men can draw no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to fight and overcome us. I think nevertheleſs without vanitie that <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s name is famous enough, to dare believe as I do, that all your Knights would think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fortunate, not onlie to be her conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, but even to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered by her. Do not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119710:55"/>therefore caſt that crown upon my Tomb, which you have acquired by my defeat, as if unworthy of your temples; do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the victory, if you will not diſgrace me: On the contrary, proclaim it to all the world, let all the world know what it hath coſt you; do not hide the blood which you have loſt, onlie hide your tears from <hi>Clorinda,</hi> that her death may be more quiet, ſince it cannot be more honourable. And to teſtifie, that ſhe pardons it with a willing heart to you, ſhe conjures you (if it be true that you have any affection for her) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it even after ſhe is dead: let not her aſhes extinguiſh that noble ardour, which her Heroick actions have kindled in your ſoul; you have loved her an enemy, love her in the grave; you have loved her when ſhe was armed againſt you, love her when ſhe ſhall be dead by your hands; you have loved her, even when ſhe hated you; love her alſo when ſhe ſhal have ended her days, in aſſuring you, that ſhe hath eſteemed your valour and your vertue even ſo far, as to ſuffer her death without murmuring, and to think it a glory to loſe her life by the ſame hand that had preſerved it for her. I die ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs with the ſorrow of not having
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119710:56"/>implied it for the ſervice of my deliverer: but as that ingratitude is not voluntary, ſo let it not hinder you to look upon my death as if I ſuffered it to ſave you, though I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, becauſe I would have loſt yours. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that all the blowes I made at you were directed againſt your enemies, and not againſt your perſon; let the blood which I loſe ſerve for a price for the tears which you ſhed: and in fine believe, that ſeeing the generoſity I have found in your ſoul, if <hi>Clorinda</hi> had lived, ſhe would have teſtified to you by her actions, that ſhe could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reckon you amongſt her enemies. But ſince things paſt cannot be revoked, and that ſhortly there will no more remain of <hi>Clorinda</hi> but her name, her aſhes, and her Monuments (if you have the goodneſs to afford her one) have a care of all thoſe, heighten her reputation if you can, that ſo yours may increaſe, and that you may alſo juſtifie at the ſame time your affection and your ſufferings. Be not ſo weak as thoſe perſons unworthy the light of the day, which ceaſe from loving their friends, as ſoon as ere they are uncapable, or not in a condition to acknowledge their amity: Be not (I ſay) of thoſe in whom the grave
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119710:56"/>ſtrikes an horrour, who dare not follow the perſons they love into the ſhades of death. Thoſe that are ſo weakly intereſted, they ſeek onlie but for the recompence of their affections, and who loves onelie pleaſing things are not worthy the light of the Sun: the great and generous ſouls are not wont to do thus; and to tell things as they are, tis onely within the grave, and 'twixt the very armes of death, that we can aſſure our ſelves certainty of the good will any hath for us; all the ſervices which are rendred to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving may be ſuſpected of ſelf-intereſt; the honours done to the dead cannot be ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, but merit to live eternally in the memory of all men. This is the true mark of <hi>Heroick love,</hi> and of true vertue, tis (as I have ſaid) the infallible Character of a ſoul great, noble, and generous, tis loving for love, and not for the reward; and 'tis in fine, the right means (as I have alſo ſaid) to become worthy of all imaginable honours, to honour the memory of thoſe, who during their lives have merited to be eſteemed by us in a particular manner. Is it not enough that we loſe a perſon ſo dear to us, unleſſe we blot her Image from our memory? Ha! no, no, too generous Prince, you will not do
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119710:57"/>thus, you will viſit her Tomb with reſpect, and her name becomming inſeparable from yours by her deplorable adventures ſhall fly 'ore all the world with luſter and glory: you will conſerve this love which was ſo pure, that hope it ſelf, hath had no ſhare: for truly it would not be juſt, that <hi>Clorinda</hi> ceaſing to hate when ſhe deſcends into the grave, you ſhould begin to wiſh her ill, when ſhe ceaſes to live, and when ſhe begins to know you; and by conſequence to eſteem you very much. After you have been my enemy, be my Champion, I conjure you; defend againſt all the world the beauty of thoſe advantageous Pourtraits which fame hath made of me over all the earth: main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that ſhe hath not flattered <hi>Clorinda:</hi> ſpeak of the grandeur of her courage, of her experience in her youth, of her ſucceſs in combats, of the purity of her ſoul, of the innocency of her life, and of the glory of her death. It concerns me little, that you ſhould publiſh how I was born upon the throne; it ſuffices that you perſwade them I was worthy; and that your ſelf be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that my defeat is honourable to you. I perceive that this diſcourſe redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles your anguiſh, and that you had rather
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119710:57"/>not have vanquiſh'd, than buy the victory by my loſs. Do not however regret ſo much an unhappy perſon, neither accuſe your ſelf to have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſo great a crime. The <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> whom you fought is not ſhe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you behold. The other was an infidel, an enemy of all Chriſtians, &amp; by conſequence yours; and this on the contrary is at preſent better inſtructed, more enlightened, and more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, ſince ſhe dies with a great eſteem and acknowledgment for <hi>Tancred.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever (you will tell me) ſhe dies by the hand of that <hi>Tanered:</hi> it is true (I ſhall anſwer) but ſhe dies for her glory. None amongſt mortals ought to have been her conqueror, but him that was ſo generous as to weep for his victory. The blood ſhe ſhould have loſt in any other encounter would have ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied her reputation; it muſt needs be then for the honour of her arms that ſhe loſe her life by your hand, that ſo ſhe might live e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally: and then, illuſtrious Prince, if the hazard of the war had not made us meet; and chance &amp; your valour had not brought me to theſe conditions I am in; never had <hi>Clorinda</hi> given you any marks of her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments; ſhe had an auſtere vertue which would alwayes have obliged her to treat you like an enemy; you have ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119710:58"/>the haughtineſs of her ſoul by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming her: her pride hath been weaker than your civility: and the death which ſhe receives from your hands cauſes her to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain your love without anger and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, which ſhe would never have done at any other time. Do not then complain of the rigour of the adventure, ſince to it you owe a part of my eſteem. I had admired your courage in battels, but I confeſſe that I had not ſo perfectly known your genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity after the victory. There be more vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſouldiers than merciful and debonair Conquerours; and more men that are able to ſpill the blood of their enemies, than to ſhed tear upon their graves. Ceaſe then, ceaſe from afflicting your ſelf, and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for me: death not being harſh to me, methinks you ſhould comfort your ſelf like me: and in fine, you ought to reſolve to that which you cannot poſſible ſhun. If I had lived longer, what happineſs more could you have expected? you ſhould never have ſeen <hi>Clorinda,</hi> but with her weapons in hand; is not it better (ſince heaven will have it ſo) that you never ſee her more? her Idea will be more pleaſing to you, than ſhe her ſelf would have been in ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119710:58"/>and in the humour ſhe is of, ſhe is content you ſhould love her memory, but perhaps ſhe would not have had you love her perſon otherwiſe. Acknowledge with me therefore the advantages that this victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gives you; and do not murmur inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately for that which you cannot hinder. Moderate your ſorrow, that it may laſt the longer: I receive my death with tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſuffer my loſſe with patience: but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver loſe the memory of what I was. You will reſtore my life, in preſerving my image in your heart; but a life more noble and more glorious, and for the which I have ſo often hazarded the other. All that <hi>Clorinda</hi> hath done, hath been but to immortalize her name; hinder then by your cares that it be not buried in oblivion: and if it be true (as I cannot doubt it) that your ſoul is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generous, do not change your minde, ſince I am going to be in an eſtate, which ſuffers no more change. I die with much admiration for your vertue; live with a great eſteem of my courage; bear even from my grave to your owne the affection which you ſay you have for me; and when miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune will have you quit this life, let it be ordained, that an Image of <hi>Clorinda</hi> be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119710:59"/>in your Tomb; let her be yet found imprinted in your heart, and that nothing be ſo puiſſant as to deface and blot it out. 'Tis in vulgar ſouls that time and abſence deſtroyes the fair opinions which vertue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone had impreſſed: but amongſt Heroick perſons, time, abſence, nor death it ſelf, are not able to change their inclinations. They love in the grave that which they loved in the world; the remembrance of that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing object ſerves in lieu of their perſons; and as they have loved without hope and intereſt, they preſerve without infidelity, and without trouble, the amity which they had promiſed. Certainly, there would be ſomewhat of cruel and unjuſt to loſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the life, the light, and the affection of our friends: we do revive again, if we live in their memory: raiſe up therefore your <hi>Clorinda</hi> in this manner, and do not make her die yet once more in ſo cruel a manner, far worſe than the former. The firſt is an effect of your skill, of your courage, and of her fate: and the ſecond would be one of your forgetfulneſs, of your indifferency, and (if I may ſpeak ſo) of your ingratitude. Yes, generous Prince, I may make uſe of thoſe terms; and I dare believe, that you
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119710:59"/>will not think it ill, if <hi>Clorinda</hi> believes ſhe obliges you ſenſibly, when even ſhe imploys the laſt moments of her life, to teſtifie to you the true eſteem ſhe hath conceived of your extream vertue. Do not then be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of acknowledgment, ſince you ſee I am not wanting in it: receive the regret I have for not having ſerved you, as an undubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proof, that I ſhould have done it, had I lived longer. But render alſo to my aſhes, and to my name the honours and the cares which you would have rendered to <hi>Clorinda,</hi> had ſhe ſurvived longer. Do not fear that her ghoſt ſhall affright you, when you ſhall viſit her grave: nor that with a querulous and moaning voice ſhe will reproach you for her death. No <hi>Tancred,</hi> you ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold no more, neither <hi>Clorinda</hi> nor her ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: you ſhall hear no more, neither her voice, nor her plaints. But alas, I know I increaſe your ſorrow in thinking to cure it! that the teſtimonies of amity which I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you do cauſe more affliction than they bring joy: that I am ſo far unhappy as to trouble you, even when I would ſerve you: that I pierce your heart, when my own is readie to expire: and that I am more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to you dying and diſ-armed, than I was
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119710:60"/>to you in the midſt of Combats. I ſhall therefore tell you nothing more that may augment your tears: I will hide a part of my mind from you, for fear of ſtirring yours, and for fear likewiſe leſt your imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility ſhould take hold of me. Ha! no, no, I repent me of that thought; and ſince I have no more than a few minutes to live, I muſt wholly give them to him, who otherwhile did ſave my life; to him who at this time does weep my death, although it hath hindred his; and to him whoſe cares ſhould immortalize me. As well I do not think that my ſilence would ſtop your moans: and I alſo believe, that you will never be more afflicted, than when this ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhall become eternal. Prepare your ſelf however for it, for I feel my fatal hour approaches, my ſtrength diminiſhes, my voice fails; and I ſhall hardly have the time to tell you, that <hi>Clorinda</hi> dies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other ſorrow, than that which yours does cauſe in her. That ſhe eſteems the end of her dayes for the moſt glorious of all her adventures; that being born upon the Throne, ſhe does not care though ſhe dies on the duſt, ſince 'tis with honour: that having lived with innocency, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119710:60"/>without ſtain, ſhe regrets nothing in the world, but onely that ſhe cannot retali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate that which ſhe owes to you: and that in fine, ſhe eſteems her ſelf happy to have found in the ſame perſon, an enemy ſo courteous, as even to ſave her life; a Knight ſo valiant, as to make her death illuſtrious; a Conquerour ſo compaſſionate as to weep at his own Victories; and a lover ſo paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and ſo heroick, as to make her hope, that he will conſerve that affection very pure, even to his laſt breath. Adiew then Prince, too unfortunate to be ſo generous: My voice fails me, I loſe my ſight and breath. But if it be poſſible, forget not this remembrance, <hi>That the Love ought not to die with the Beloved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:119710:61"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>THe reſſentments that a like Diſcourſe might have inſpir'd, did not miſs of finding place in the afflicted ſpirit of <hi>Tancred:</hi> he wept, and wept a long time for ſo extraordinary a misfortune, and for ſo fearful an adventure; and we may believe that he wept ever. Since <hi>Erminia</hi> (how love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; how much a lover ſo'ere ſhe was) could never comfort him for the death of <hi>Clorin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi> Nevertheleſs, be not you perſwaded, that he was ſo, <hi>That the affection ought not to die with the beloved;</hi> but ſuſpend at least your judgment, ſince this other Princeſſe hath ſomewhat to ſay thereon. Hearken better to her than <hi>Tancred</hi> did hearken: for in truth ſhe is too worthy of compaſſion to be ſuffered to die for a dead one, or at least for not hearing of her.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="text">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:119710:61"/>
            <head>ERMINIA TO ARSETES. The Fifth HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>AFter that <hi>Tancred</hi> had killed <hi>Clorin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> as you have ſeene before; the Prince appeared inconſolable: and hardly could that famous Hermit which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes <hi>Godfreys</hi> army ſeparate him from that fair body, whoſe ſoul himſelf had ſeparated; ſo that <hi>Erminia,</hi> daughter to the King of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who had a long time loved that generous, but affllicted Prince, deſpaired of ever ſeeing her affection recompenced. I was in that unhappy condition, that meeting one
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119710:62"/>of <hi>Clorinda's</hi> Domeſticks, who maintained that <hi>Tancred</hi> had reaſon to do ſo; ſhe ende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make him confeſſe, to eaſe her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>That the affection ought not to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the grave.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:119710:62"/>
               <head>ERMINIA TO ARSETES.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe which ſay as you ſay, that the power of death ought not to deſtroy love: that one muſt love in the dark regions of the air thoſe whom we lov'd whilſt they enjoy'd the light of the Sun; that not to conſerve our affections very pure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, is to be unfaithful; that 'tis inconſtancy to be capable of any other flames after they are ſeparated from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; and that in fine, whoever is ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, as to ſee his Miſtris enter into the Monument, never ought to have any thoughts of making any other conqueſt. Thoſe people (I ſay) are equally ignorant, both how far the power of death, and the power of love do extend. They know not
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119710:63"/>what that is which we call love: they know neither fidelity nor conſtancy; and judge of things either by their own capritious fancies, or for their own intereſt. As for you, ſage and faithful <hi>Arſetes,</hi> I have no reaſon to find it ill, that you beſtow your tears to the memory of the valiant <hi>Clorin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da:</hi> I conſent likewiſe, that the generous <hi>Tancred</hi> mingle his with yours; and I ſhall further teſtifie to you by my ſighes, that the deſtiny of that illuſtrious perſon hath caus'd grief in me; and that I was her Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, but not her enemy. But I will alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you, that without being either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant or unfaithful, that Prince who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her during her life, might now recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence my affection by his own, ſince ſhe does ceaſe to live. Death (that fearful mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that deſtroys all that breaths upon earth) wil not that love ſhould enterprize any thing againſt his power: thoſe which he once bears away are no longer obliged to any thing: he ſeparates thoſe amities that are the cloſeſt united; and unties the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt alliances. In making Kings to tumble from the Throne into the Sepulchre, he diſpences their ſubjects from all obedience; their power ends with their life, and there
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119710:63"/>remains no more of thoſe Monarchs, but the memory of their vices, or of their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. If they have been evil, they are bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with boldneſſe; and if they have been good, they are praiſed without ſuſpi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of flattery; their Tombs are carefully looked to, their names are immortaliz'd by the Hiſtories which are made of their Reigns and their Heroick actions; but the ſervices which they were wont to require of their ſubjects are not rendered to them: So true it is that death brings a change in all things. That which I ſay of Kings may be ſaid of thoſe whom love had made Queens over their Lovers, and whom death hath ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo to its Empire; as they are not in a condition to command any more, we are diſpenſed from obeying them; the lawes of Reaſon and Nature will have us weep their loſs, and cheriſh their memory, that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forget them, that we raiſe ſtately Tombs for them, and that we forget not any thing which may adde to their glory; but Reaſon and Nature will likewiſe tell us, that time cures the ſharpeſt ſorrowes; that the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſpring of tears muſt be dried up at length, and that all afflictions muſt dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. In effect, there is no means to be found
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119710:64"/>in theſe occaſions; we muſt enter into the grave with the beloved perſon, or we muſt keep within the limits which wiſdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to the moſt violent griefs. All the ornaments of the proudeſt Mauſoleums are but extinguiſh'd torches, and ſad marks and tokens that thoſe that reſt in them have now no ſhare in the light; and that by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, the living ſhould have no ſhare in their aſhes and urnes. That eternall ſleep which reigns in the graves, and which the tears and the ſighes of the moſt paſſionare lovers cannot diſpell, evidences enough, that 'tis not to the deceaſed we owe our love and conſtancy. The change which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens in them juſtifies that which happens to others; and then to ſpeak truly, the moſt deſpairing do abuſe themſelves, when they think yet to love the ghoſts of their Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as if they were ſtill alive. That which can cauſe no longer, neither deſire, nor hope, nor diſquiet, nor jealouſie, cannot be called love: They ceaſe to love therefore, and yet do not apprehend it, and miſtake an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of their grief, and ſometimes of their temperature for a mark of paſſion. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is abſolutely impoſſible, that love and death can ever reign together;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119710:64"/>they think to love their Miſtreſſes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they love only their memory; they ſay they are faithful and conſtant, and yet all their ſentiments are changed: for of all the tenderneſſes which true affection inſpires, there remains nothing in portion to them but grief; beſides that with time does or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily become onely a melancholy habit, rather than an effect of their loſſe, or the reſſentment they have of it, they accuſtome themſelves to ſadneſſe, as to joy; their fighes do eaſe them, their tears fall without bitterneſſe; and the recital of their ill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, inſtead of increaſing their torments, and renewing their diſpleaſures, ſerves them for a paſtime and a pleaſing divertiſement. Believe me, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> thoſe are not the ſigns of a violent paſſion: Nevertheleſſe it is certain that the wiſdome of nature works in us, whether we will or not, this advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous change. Death is an evil too inevitable and too common amongſt men to be left without a conſolation for the loſſes it brings; and indeed we finde it to be ſo: and reaſon hath not left us without giving the juſt limits to the greateſt ſorrow. Ever ſince the beginning of ages death hath made men ſhed tears, which time hath wiped off
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119710:65"/>again: all the children have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted for the death of their fathers; all the fathers have not deſpaired at the death of their children; the moſt faithful huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands have attended their wives to their graves, without deſcending therein them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: and the moſt conſtant women have buried their husbands, and yet did not lie down with them in the ſame bed of earth. In fine, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> as there is no joy permanent in this life, there ought to be no eternal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. You will tell me, that the bands of blood and thoſe of love are things very different; and that for the moſt part the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the perſon beloved has more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in our hearts than any other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You will adde to this, that we would forſake our Countrey, and all our Parents to ſerve her; and that likewiſe when it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that we loſe her, ſhe cauſes as much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, ſhe alone, as if we loſt all together, both our Parents that gave us birth, and our fortunes; and in ſhort, all that is left us to loſe in the world. Though I ſhould agree touching that, yet we muſt ſtill come to my argument, which is, that either we muſt comfort our ſelves after the death of the perſon whom we love, or we muſt die
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119710:65"/>with her. For to think that love is a thing compatible with the darkneſſe of the grave is a belief of ſmall appearance; 'tis a thing without reaſon, and without example; and which can never happen, unleſs they loſe their ſence and underſtanding with their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes. As we do not affect what we never ſee, neither ought we to love what we ſhall never behold more; one may preſerve the remembrance, but we cannot love the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſince they are no longer in being: one may ſtill love the chains and ſhakels which they wore; but as theſe chains and bands are broken for ever, we may without incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy or infidelity retake ſome others, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they be not unworthy of the firſt. We muſt not break down a golden Statua, to put a braſs one in the place: But amongſt ſome Chriſtians it is uſual to adorn the place with more than one Image. I do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire that <hi>Tancred</hi> ſhould raze out that of his <hi>Clorinda</hi> intirely from his heart; I have more reſpect to her, and more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence for him: I would only have him, ſince he has not renounced all humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, for we know he does both give and receive Orders, go to the wars, defend his life, and imploy the ſame hand, with
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119710:66"/>which he cut the bands that tied him to the ſervice of <hi>Clorinda,</hi> againſt thoſe whom <hi>Clorinda</hi> has alwayes ſerved; I would (I ſay) that having never ceaſed to be faithfull to his party, having never ceaſed to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant in battels, and having never forgotten to be generous, he may not now omit to be an acknowledger of my affections. In the ſtate as things now are he owes nothing but compaſſion to <hi>Clorinda,</hi> but he owes love to <hi>Erminia. Clorinda</hi> can now no more either love or hate him; and <hi>Erminia</hi> has not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lov'd him before he knew <hi>Clorinda,</hi> but ſhe loves him ſtill, even whilſt he prefers <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s aſhes before <hi>Erminia</hi>'s chaſte flames. Heavens be my witneſſe, if I nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the leaſt thought of hatred againſt that illuſtrious perſon: as long as ſhe lived, I held as great an eſteem of her vertue, as I had affection for the Prince whom I loved: no, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> her death did not rejoyce me; on the contrary, it did grieve me. I honour'd her enough to weep her loſs; and I loved <hi>Tanered</hi> enough, to deſire almoſt that he might not have ſuch a ſad misfortune, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though according to appearance, it might be advantageous to me; and if after their intereſt I may have leave to think of my
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119710:66"/>own, I dare avouch again, that I believe, that I ſhould be leſs unhappy, if <hi>Clorinda</hi> were not dead, than I am now, though ſhe be equally incapable to give either love or jealouſie. Did ſhe yet live, I ſhould not take it ill, if <hi>Tancred</hi> would give me but his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and friendſhip, and preſerved his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire love and paſſion for her; I would ſay in his defence, he loves that which cannot be beloved too much; <hi>Clorinda</hi> is young, fair, vertuous, and valiant, and his inclination does prompt him to adore her: let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan our fortune then without accuſing her that cauſes it, ſince we can finde nothing to object againſt his choice. But now that <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> is no more but a little duſt, that her youth does ſubſiſt no more, that her beauty is deſtroyed, that her vertue cannot appear, but only by the relations of thoſe that know her, that her valour can be no more either uſeful or hurtful to her friends or enemies; and that in fine, ſhe is as far diſtant from us as if ſhe had never been. It is not juſt, that <hi>Tancred</hi> ſhould have more fidelity for the aſhes of his enemy, than acknowledgment and regard for her who began to love him from the firſt inſtant ſhe ever beheld him, although that firſt inſtant caſt her from the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119710:67"/>Throne to ſlavery; and that the hands which enchained her had torne a Crown from off her Fathers head, yea a Crown which ſhould have been placed upon her own temples. But perhaps, generous <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> you do not know all the rights which I have in <hi>Tancreds</hi> affection, by the birth of that love which I have for him: it will not then be out of our diſcourſe and way, if I tell it you in a few words; that ſo if it happens one day, that he hear my reaſons with more ſweetneſs than you believe, you may not accuſe him of infidelity and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, if he do prefer <hi>Erminia</hi> before the ghoſt or ſhadow of <hi>Clorinda.</hi> It is likewiſe neceſſary for my own glory, that you ſhould know, that without ceaſing to be vertuous &amp; reaſonable I could begin to love <hi>Tancred,</hi> though he were my Fathers conquerour; that I might continue to wiſh him well, though he have not anſwered my amity; and that I am in the right at preſent to wiſh from him, that he would be content onely to honour the memory of <hi>Clorinda,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to love <hi>Erminia.</hi> You muſt know then (ſage and wiſe <hi>Arſetes</hi>) that when the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had pull'd down <hi>Antiochus</hi> his throne, and that they had taken away both his ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119710:67"/>and life who gave me life: you may know (I ſay) that by the fortune of war I fell into the hands of the Conquerour, who (as you cannot but know) was the ſame <hi>Tancred</hi> of whom we now ſpeak. But alas! why was it that the Conquerour was not more rigorous to me at that time, ſince he will not be merciful now? wherefore was it that he did not treat me like a ſlave then, if it be true that he will not treat me like a Miſtris now? Wherefore was it that he rendred me all the treaſures of the King, my father, then, if he will not now render me my own heart again, or give me his in exchange? and why did he give me my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ſo freely and graciouſly, ſince he now refuſes ſo cruelly to accept theſe chains, which are leſs <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude and heavy? Yes, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Arſetes,</hi> I acknowledge with ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, I began to love <hi>Tancred</hi> then, when in appearance I ſhould have begun to hate him. His vertue, his moderation, and his clemency touched my heart ſenſibly: I was his Captain, and he reſpected me as a Queen: by the right that Conquerors have over the conquered, all our treaſures were his, and he reſtored them to me, or rather gave them: I was his priſoner, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119710:68"/>me to liberty: 'tis true, that looſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe chains which I wore, he put me on ſome others more ſtrong than thoſe which I was freed from. I beheld my liberty as an evil, and regreted my ſervitude as a great good; and though I did not know my ſelf (in thoſe times) wherefore I had ſuch thoughts which ſeemed ſo void of reaſon, I know now that the extraordinary generoſity of <hi>Tancred</hi> had already uſher'd love into my heart, although I were then of an age, in which love is unknown. Since that, what have I not done, ſometimes to love him no more, ſomtimes to love him dearlier? I have beheld him ſomtimes as an uſurper; I have conſidered him as an enemy, who had taken away <hi>Antiochus</hi>'s Crown; and which is more, who had taken away all the quiet of my life by a paſſion which his generoſity had bred in my ſoul, and which I could not overcome. But ſhall I tell it, faithful <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes?</hi> after I had beheld him as an uſurper and an enemy, I always loved him, becauſe he was both vertuous, and my deliverer, and my beloved. I have ſeen him from the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhedding the blood of our ſouldiers, without ſhedding a tear my ſelf: I deſired the victory, but however
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119710:68"/>would not have <hi>Tancred</hi> be conquered. I had found him too mercifull a Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, not to deſire to have him ſtill in a condition, to make known his vertue by doing good, rather then in ſuffering evil. Nor could I hear of the peril he was in, by reaſon of his hurts, without having a deſign to ſave his life, who had ſaved my honour, and had given me my liberty. You know as well as my ſelfe, that I made uſe of the valiant <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s armes to get out from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to execute my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize: But in taking her armes and weapons I did not put on her courage, ſo that I was quickly forced to quit my ſword, and betake me to the ſheep-hook to ſecure my ſelfe. I have then been Cavalier and Shepherdeſſe for the inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Tancred:</hi> I was alſo <hi>Armida</hi>'s pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in his conſideration: and that which I finde to be more happy for me, is, that by that marvellous art, which all the Kings, my Predeceſſors, have left me in poſſeſſion; I have had the ſatisſaction to render and ſave the life of my deliverer, to dreſſe his wounds, and to heal him, in ſuch a time when none but ERMINIA could
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119710:69"/>relieve him. You ſee then, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> that the birth of my affection is not criminal, ſince <hi>Tancreds</hi> ſole vertue did breed it. You may judge likewiſe that its continuation is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable and the deſign of ſaving him did contribute much to it: and you ſhould alſo know, that <hi>Clorinda</hi> not living any longer, he is obliged to recompence my amity with his owne. <hi>Clorinda,</hi> who at this preſent cauſes all his grief, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all his thoughts, had never imployed her armes, but to aſſault him, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him: and I ſtole the armour of <hi>Clorin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> but onely to ſave his life. <hi>Clorinda,</hi> from whom he had taken neither Crown, nor Scepter, has alwayes beheld him as an enemy: and I, from whom he had raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all, even to my very liberty, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beheld him as a Prince, which could and ſhould be my lover. I have already told you, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> that if your illuſtrious Miſtris did live yet, I would not ſo much as have a thought to diſpute her conqueſt; but her misfortune having laid her in her grave, you may judge after all that I have ſaid, whether it be reaſonable to prefer the ſepulchre of <hi>Clorinda</hi> before <hi>Erminia?</hi> for in fine, tis not unfaithfulneſs to abandon
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119710:69"/>thoſe which do abandon us for ever. What <hi>Arſetes,</hi> can you apprehend that one may keep a love for that which cannot receive it any more? That pleaſing interchange of will and deſires, which is made betwixt lovers, can that be made between <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s Tomb and the Prince <hi>Tancred?</hi> No, <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that cannot be ſo; all things in the world have their limits: ſo long as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved perſon is living, we muſt follow her over all the earth, we muſt partake of her fortune how unhappy ſo'ere it be; nay, we muſt even die for her, if there be occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but if it happens that ſhe dies, we muſt (as I have already ſaid) either ceaſe to live, or ceaſe to love her; 'tis ſo abſolute a neceſſity that nothing can oppoſe it; all the ages have ſhewed us examples of what I ſay; all that deſpaired have kill'd themſelves with their own hands; and thoſe that were wiſe have comforted themſelves with their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. In effect, there would be great inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in the order and courſe of nature, if every time that death does caſt one perſon into the Grave, there ſhould be another that muſt renounce intirely all the ſociety of the living, and paſs the remainer of his dayes in ſhedding of fruitleſs tears, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119710:70"/>vainly walking about the margent of the grave; for truly to ſpeak with ſincerity, there are ſcarce any people that die, which ſhould not expect thoſe laſt devoirs, either from their friends, or from thoſe for whom they had any affection, if it were true that reaſon did authorize ſuch a ſtrange procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: by this means ſuch a thrid of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows would run through all the world, as would render the lives of all men unhappy, and deſtroy the Univerſe. Or elſe we muſt (not to be expoſed to ſuch troubleſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures) refuſe the amity of all honeſt men; never have any love for any, nor be obliged to any, but take all care to make our ſelves become hated, and rather look to the health of thoſe for whom we have any good wil, than to their deſerts or worth: for fear, leſt their conſtitutions being weak, the end of their dayes happening it may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore old age, ſhould oblige thoſe which love them to ſpend the reſt of their dayes in mourning about their graves. Seriouſly, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> it is not to be eaſily imagined, that there are rational ſouls, which believe that death does not deſtroy love; time and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, which have nor ſo much power as that, do every day make too many become
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119710:70"/>conſtant, to leave a belief, that after death hath raviſhed the object away which gave birth to that paſſion, we ſhould yet preſerve a love for it. We cannot continue to love that object, ſince it is deſtroyed; nor ought we to do it, ſince we ſhould equally reſiſt both Reaſon and Nature, which will not have it ſo. Thoſe who are ſaid to have been in love with a fair <hi>Statua,</hi> or a Picture, are more excuſable than thoſe that love a grave, or the aſhes which it incloſes: the eyes which are wont to ſeduce the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and will by the advantage of all fair objects, betray them, and gives them ſome kind of delight in ſweetly deceiving them; but to preſerve a love for an object that is ſo horrid, for that which can never behold without tears and affright, nay for that which we ſhall never behold again, tis that which cannot, which ought not to be, and tis that which makes me with boldneſs maintain, <hi>That the love ought not to laſt but to the grave.</hi> All men that have not loſt their judgements, neither do, nor ought to do any thing without a deſign: Tis ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral a rule, that there are hardly any which miſſe it; the covetous know wherefore
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119710:71"/>they guard their treaſures; all the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous know whither they would climb; all that are of vindicative ſpirits know for what end they moleſt their enemies; nor are the lovers ignorant what they intend, when they weep and ſigh at the feet of their Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. They know (I ſay) that love is the price of love; and that in fine, we love to be beloved again. But ſhould we ask the Prince <hi>Tancred,</hi> what he pretends by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to love the ghoſt of <hi>Clorinda,</hi> as much as he love her perſon; I believe he would be ſomewhat troubled for an anſwer. To ſay that his tears and ſighes have for their principall deſign, to touch and move her heart, would not be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſince tis impoſſible it ſhould be ſo. Or elſe to think, that he preſerves his firſt flames to animate the aſhes of his Miſtris, he is too wiſe to have ſuch a thought: or again to imagine, that he has no other end in what he does, but to make himſelf unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py needleſly, is a thing without all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Nevertheleſſe it is certain, that the love which you ſo much praiſe in this Prince can produce no more advantage to him, nor to me, but either my own death or his. Ha! if it were poſſible, that the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119710:71"/>illuſtrious <hi>Clorinda</hi> could hear his moanes, and my reaſons; and that from the midſt of her grave ſhe could make him hear her commands; how ſhe would blame his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and mourn my unhappineſſe! ſhe was other-while too generous, to think it now juſt, that <hi>Tancred,</hi> being no longer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to be faithful to her, ſhould be ſtill ingrateful towards me. You may tell me, perhaps, that her laſt deſires were not as I perſwade: But, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> ſhe then lived yet, when ſhe declared them to <hi>Tancred.</hi> That imbecillity which is common to all thoſe that are dying, is not to be found in them after they are dead; all their paſſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tranquil in the grave; the deceaſed deſire neither the love nor the conſtancy of any, they have no ſhare in our fortunes, they do not care whether others meddle with their deſtiny; and as they are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from all things, they do not trouble themſelves whether we ſeparate alſo from them, or yet ſtill follow them. Believe me, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> tis enough to be conſtant during our lives, without being ſo after death: tis (I ſay) enough to do what we ought, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing what we ought not: and then, to ſay things as they are, ſo long as we
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119710:72"/>are alive we are obliged to ſerve to the publick ſociety; it is not permitted us to be ingratefull; it is not permitted us to be unjuſt; and this being ſo, it is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Tancred,</hi> to love <hi>Erminia</hi> no more, and to love <hi>Clorinda</hi> ſtill, though <hi>Clorinda</hi> be no more, and that <hi>Erminia</hi> be in a condition to love him to his grave. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if we do likewiſe but rightly expound the laſt deſires and will of your illuſtrious Miſtris, one ſhall finde that they were ill underſtood by this Prince: for whatſo'ere commands ſhe gave him to reverence her memory, ſhe made him none more preſſing than thoſe by which ſhe injoyn'd him to be comforted. Now what means is there for this Prince to be ever comforted, if he retain the love he had for her? What <hi>Arſetes,</hi> can a true lover live happily, and know that he can never be ſeen, nor be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved by his Lady? Ha! no, no, let's not abuſe our ſelves in expounding <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s laſt ſpeeches; for without doubt ſhe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to what I ſay, ſhe will willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in <hi>Tancreds</hi> memory, but ſhe will not be angry, if I reign in his heart; ſhe will be willing to have him reſpect her name, but ſhe will not be diſpleaſed if he love my
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119710:72"/>perſon; ſhe was willing that he ſhould ſhed ſome tears upon her grave, but ſhe will not murmur, if reaſon, time, and <hi>Erminia</hi> dries them up againe; ſhe has conſented that her death ſhould make him unhappy for ſome few dayes, but ſhe will conſent likewiſe that he ſhould make me happy for all my life. Do not therefore, <hi>Arſetes,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s will: perſwade the Prince, her lover, that which I would perſwade you; tell him he diſobeys his Miſtris and yours, in not comforting himſelf; and that if it be permitted for any one to pretend a part in his affection, it can be onely to me. As a friend to <hi>Clorinda,</hi> I have ſome right to the amity he had for her; as his ſlave, which I have been, he ſhould let me wear his fetters; as a Queen, which I ought to be, he ſhould give me the Empire of his heart, inſtead of the Crowne which he hath made me loſe: and, as his lover, he ought to leave <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s grave to follow me even till my death. That is the term that I preſcribe to the love which I will have him have for <hi>Erminia;</hi> I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that he ſhould forſake <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s tomb to come and walk about mine, if I happen to die before him: No, my pretentions
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119710:73"/>are not ſo unjuſt; if he die not for the ſorrow of my death, I will have him live, and be comforted. For in fine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I hearken to reaſon or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I finde, that the love ought not to indure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the grave, or after death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:119710:73"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>AS <hi>Taſſo</hi> hath not told us, whether <hi>Tancred</hi> were comforted, and whether he had pity of <hi>Erminia;</hi> ſo neither can I tell it you: and becauſe <hi>Arſetes</hi> was an ancient Domestick of <hi>Clorinda,</hi> I dare not neither aſſure you, whether he did agree to this Diſcourſe. You have the reaſons of the one and the other. Conſider them at leaſure, and judge ſoveraignly, if you are ſo bold as to judge of Queens, and ſo diſ-intereſted as to undertake it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:74"/>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:119710:74"/>
            <head>CARICLIA TO THE AGENES. The Sixth HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>WHen after the ſuffering of all thoſe illuſtrious misfortunes, which compoſe the Ethiopian Hiſtory, <hi>CARICLIA</hi> and <hi>THEAGENES</hi> beheld themſelves on the Throne; that love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and famous Heroine, in a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation which ſhe had with her lover, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called to her memory all her past troubles; and comparing them to her preſent felicities, it ſeemed to her that that pleaſing remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119710:75"/>did in ſome manner increaſe them: So that in her tranſportation of joy, ſhe ſpake in this ſort to <hi>THEAGENES,</hi> to prove to him, That thoſe that never had evil, do not know true pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:119710:75"/>
               <head>CARICLIA TO THEAGENES.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N fine, my dear and beloved <hi>Theagenes,</hi> we have run a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Race, at the end of which we finde a Crown, which is no leſs glorious: 'tis good to remember the ſtorm, when we are in a ſafe harbour; and amidſt the reſt and tranquility of the earth, with what pleaſure we revolve in our minds the fury and agitation of the Sea. Thoſe images, though troubled and tumultuous, do nevertheleſs pleaſe the mind: they are diſordered and confuſed, but tis delightful; and as diverſity is the greateſt charm of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thoſe marvellous events which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſo intricate and croſs a life as ours hath been, never fails to excite joy in that ſoul that remembers its former ſadneſſe and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119710:76"/>misfortunes. Tis certain every thing appears beſt by their contraries: and tis only by the oppoſition that their differences are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and their advantages ſenſibly diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The light owes its luſtre to the ſhade; and 'tis from the night that day does draw its brightneſſe; the Sun makes known the ſplendour of its rayes by the tenebreous darkneſs; tis the rigorous ſharpneſs of the Winter that heightens the amiable ſweetnes of the Spring; the prickles makes the roſe more eſteemed; and briefly, tis from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes without doubt that felicities do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe; it being very true, that thoſe who have not undergone ſome evils, can never truly know what pleaſure is. In effect, thoſe who have never had but fortunate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures; who never have proved the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of fate; and whoſe moſt ſenſible contentments have never coſt them a ſigh, nor made them ſhed a tear, do poſſeſs them without being poſſeſſed; enjoy them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enjoyments; and make that an object of their froideur and diſdain, which might be the object of all the worlds deſires. They are rich, and know it not; they have treaſures, and cannot tell their value; they have good things, and do not taſt them; and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119710:76"/>their abundance makes them poor. Such a long ſeries of felicities does benum a ſoul rather than rouze it: and the frequency does no leſſe take away the delicacy of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, than it does take away the ſharpneſſe of pain. One is accuſtomed to a Scepter, as well as to an iron chain; the Throne is no better to thoſe people than an ordinary chair; and there are thoſe that wear a Crown upon their heads, who yet hardly know whether they have it on, or are adorned with it or no. Thoſe Princeſſes, who being born in the purple, and have alwayes worn a Royal Mantle; who, even from their cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles to their graves, have alwayes ſtood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Canopy of ſtate, within the Balli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and amidſt the Pomp and Majeſty, cannot compare their ſatisfaction to <hi>Cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clia</hi>'s; ſhe who was expos'd at her birth, ſhe who was not known to any, ſhe who did not know her ſelf, ſhe who was not adornd but with her natural graces; and ſhe in fine, who from extream miſery has paſt in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the ſupreameſt grandeur. For my part (I acknowledge to you <hi>Theagenes</hi>) it ſeems to me, that I have conquered the Kingdome which Fortune reſtores to me; it ſeems to me, that I hold it by my vertue,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119710:77"/>and not by my birth; and it ſeems to me, that my merit has given to me, all that which my love will make me give your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Now as that which we gain by our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, or generoſity, is infinitely more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, than that which we hold from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; you muſt not wonder, if I prefer a glory which hath coſt me an hundred la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to that glory which others have without trouble; and if I finde that tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through difficulties, that we attain to ſoveraign happineſs. No, my dear <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes,</hi> it has been by my diſgraces that I have obtained my welfare; 'twas only by my baniſhment that I got your acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and onely my leaving <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> which ſaw my birth, hath made the birth of my affection to be ſeen in the temple of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> at <hi>Delphus.</hi> Thus cannot any deny, but that my good hath proceeded from my evil, and that my repoſe is ſprung from my traverſes. Who would not have ſaid, when we left the Grecian rivage, and that the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat <hi>Trachinus</hi> had made himſelf Maſter of our Veſſel, that there was no more any fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity for us? Who would not have ſaid, when that Pirat became enamoured of me, that we muſt have loſt our reaſon, if we had
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119710:77"/>had the leaſt hope left? who would not have ſaid, when there roſe ſo great a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, that the waves lifted us even to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and afterwards let us ſink again to the very center of the earth, that the Sea was going to ſwallow us, and that its fury was going to daſh our ſhip againſt the points of the Rocks? who would not have ſaid, when thoſe infamous Pirats were arrived at the mouth of a great River; and that they began a combat amongſt themſelves, of which I ſhould have been the prize, that Fortune was going to decide their difference, and give to one of the parties both the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory and <hi>Cariclia?</hi> who would not have ſaid, ſeeing me upon that deſert ſhore, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt ſo many ſlaine, and claſping your wounded ſelf in my armes, almoſt as dead as they and you were; that we were going to finde our graves, on that part of an arm of the River <hi>Nylus,</hi> called <hi>Her acleetick;</hi> and that the illuſtrious race of <hi>Perſeus,</hi> from whom I am deſcended, and the noble blood of <hi>Achilles</hi> from whence you ſprung were at the point to periſh inevitably in a ſavage, and not inhabited place? Notwithſtanding, by the goodneſs of the gods which protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, nothing of all this befell us, but we
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119710:78"/>are yet in a condition to comfort our ſelves for thoſe misfortunes paſt, or rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce for our preſent felicities. But lovely <hi>Theagenes,</hi> tell me the truth, I conjure you, and do not diſguize it, no more than I do theſe thoughts of mine; can you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the horrid countenances and minds of thoſe firſt robbers which ceaſed on us, or the extravagant equipage of the ſecond which took us from the firſt, without feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome joy in your ſoul, for being freed from ſo eminent peril? Do you not yet behold them as well as I, iſſuing from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe Rocks, their faces tann'd and Sun-burnt, their hair long and tangled, their bodies half armed and half naked; and do they not now give you as much pleaſure, as they then gave me fear? Tis here that we may now with liberty conſider, without any affrights, that fair Iſle of Shepherds, which ſo long a ſpace of Marſhy earth, &amp; which ſo great a quantity of Reeds and Canes ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates from the firm ground, hiding it from the ſight of thoſe which are there. Did you ever ſee any thing more pleaſing, or more induſtrious than that labyrinth of water, which ſo many ſmall enterlaced paths does form amongſt thoſe Reeds and Canes,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119710:78"/>through which the veſſels of thoſe Thieves make their paſſage, and can find out a way, which none other but they can diſcover? Did you ever behold a Ruſtick object, that was more grateful than that Iſland was, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had in a boat trac'd out all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed turnings of which I ſpeak, which ſeems as it had hid it ſelfe amidſt ſo many aquatick herbs, and ſo many plants which never grow but in Marſhes? Did you ever ſee any thing more artificial and more pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty together, than were thoſe Cabbins, made with enterlaced branches of Palmes, and covered with other long branches mixed with laurel? and this object being joyned to ſo many different armes and weapons which thoſe theeves hung on all the trees about, would it not make one think, that that little mountain were one of thoſe great and proud Trophies, which the Grecians raiſe when they are victorious? I know that you will tell me, that thoſe innocent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures could not poſſibly be ſenſible to us, and that the love which <hi>Thyamis</hi> conceived for me, (he who was chief of thoſe robbers) made us ſuffer ſtrange troubles; I know that you will tell me, that I ſaw my ſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from you, and buried alive in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119710:79"/>Cave; I know that you will tell me, that when the Egyptians and the Perſians came to aſſault thoſe Theeves: <hi>Thyamis</hi>'s jealouſie had almoſt made me loſe my life, and that he would without doubt have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived me of it, if the obſcurity of that den had not made him take the unhappy <hi>Thisbe</hi> for me; I know that you will tell me, that the flame devoured almoſt in an inſtant all the Canes, the Reeds; all the Plants, the herbs, all the arms and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins of thoſe Robbers: and that one would have ſaid, that by ſome enchantment that pleaſant object vaniſhed, and left nothing in its place but flame, aſhes, and ſmoke: I know that you will tell me, that you were infinitely troubled, when you thought me loſt, and that was redoubled, when taking <hi>Thisbe</hi> for me, you thought me dead: but I muſt tell you, that that ſorrow could not come neer to that joy of yours and mine, when you beheld me living, and that I found you ſafe. Recall, my dear <hi>Theagenes,</hi> recall to your memory, I conjure you, my raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and your tranſports in that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; trace well in your memory that image which time and a long ſeries of other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes have perhaps blotted out: Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119710:79"/>your heart well, as I examine mine; and tell me after that, if you ever felt a more ſenſible content; if the paines you had ſuffered did not augment your felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and in fine, whether it be not true, as I maintain, that thoſe who have not felt ſome evil, cannot tell what pleaſure is? but perhaps you may reply again, that thoſe felicities were ſo ſhort, that they could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſs but for a pleaſing dream: that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune which had re-united us did re-ſeparate us preſently again by <hi>Mitranes</hi> cruelty; and that that laſt ſeparation, finding our ſouls wholly diſpoſed to ſadneſſe, that ſadneſſe enter'd our ſouls with all the fury of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Conquerour, who ravages and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts all in the place he ſurprizes. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, (and I acknowledge) that nothing can compare with the ſence of thoſe afflictions we then felt; and that to know them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, one muſt have prov'd them; for the greateſt and moſt perſuaſive Eloquence can trace but an imperfect draught of them. I beheld my ſelf ſeparated from all that I loved; you ſaw your ſelf ſeparated from all that you paſſionately deſired, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated for ever. You beheld me in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a Barbarian; and I ſaw you under a
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:119710:80"/>cruell Maſter; and immediately after (which was the moſt inhumane) you ſaw me no more, <hi>Theagenes,</hi> nor could I ſee you. Without doubt thoſe funeſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were ſo ſad both to you and my ſelf, that thoſe themſelves who ſuffered it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have ſo much art as to relate it: and if from this woful adventure I paſs again to the apparition of that dead Corps which I ſaw both move and ſpeak by the power of Magick, and by her mothers impiety, whoſe unnatural tenderneſs troubled the repoſe of her grave, and violated the laſt of natures lawes; I doubt not, but that I do almoſt affright you as much as I was at that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, and make you participate of my fear. For imagine to your ſelf a Maiden, and the good <hi>Calaſiris,</hi> alone in the midſt of a great plain, covered all over with broken weapons and armes, with Chariots o'retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſprinkled with blood, dead ſouldiers, and all others tragical objects, which are wont to be ſeen in thoſe ſad places where a battel hath been given. Imagine (I ſay) that you beheld me, &amp; that you beheld all theſe doleful objects by the gloomy light of the Moon, whoſe weak beams did ſometimes pierce the clouds, and made us confuſedly
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119710:80"/>perceive all theſe things: and ſometimes wrapping its ſelf in thoſe clouds again, left nothing in thoſe <hi>Campanias</hi> but horror and obſcurity. Repreſent to your ſelf, that you ſaw me amidſt this fearful diſorder, and that from amongſt thoſe maſſacred ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers you behold on a ſudden a dead body, with motion as quick as unnatural, ariſe as one ſhould raiſe a <hi>Statua,</hi> and ſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time upright. Twice I beheld it ariſe, as if alive; twice I beheld it fall as if dead; twice I beheld her face pale and disfigured; twice I beheld her eyes quite extinguiſh'd and turn'd inwards, though they appeared open; twice her mouth opened it ſelf, dead as ſhe was; and twice ſhe ſpake, but with fewer words than ſighs, and with an accent capable to appal with horrour the ſtouteſt ſoul. Nevertheleſs, my dear <hi>Theagenes,</hi> all this affliction and all this fright ſerved af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards but to augment our joy, when by the bounty of the gods we met one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the walls of <hi>Memphis.</hi> 'Twas there that I once more experimented, that they which never had no evil, do not know pleaſure: 'twas there that I knew ſenſibly that the abſence makes us afterwards find the ſight of the beloved object the more
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119710:81"/>pleaſing: and it was there, my dear <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes,</hi> that I learn'd by experience, that thoſe which are alwayes happy, are not half happy. In effect, thoſe who never loſt a treaſure, are ignorant of the joy there is in finding it again, and hardly know that which its poſſeſſion gives. It belongs only to unfortunate ones to ſpeak of a good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: and as we muſt be in the profound and deep vallies to judge well of the heights of mountains; ſo we muſt have been in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and afflictions, to know perfectly what is felicity and abundance. In ſuch a happy moment of an unlookt for accident, there paſſes certain inviſible beams from one lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers eyes to the others, which carry with them into the hearts a certain I know not what, not to be expreſs'd. The words of content, of joy, of ſatisfaction, and of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, are too poor to expreſs ſo tender and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate a ſentiment; and the eloquent ſilence of thoſe two happy perſons does tell it far better than can any words, or than it can be repreſented by all the figures of that impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous art, which vaunts it ſelf to be the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all free ſpirits, and the Tyrant of the will. But <hi>Theagenes,</hi> as I have ſaid, that the eyes of a lover are eloquent,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:119710:81"/>and that they can make themſelves be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; ſo yours do confirm me in my opinion; and I underſtand, though I do not ſpeak a word, what they would have me comprehend, and what they would remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me of. No, no, I have not forgotten the unworthy love of that object worthy of my hatred and your diſdain: in a word of <hi>Arſace,</hi> that cruel ſiſter of the Perſian King, who caus'd ſo much trouble to us, and thought to make us periſh; I know that in her I had a Rival to be feared; I know that ſhe made you wear iron chains, you who deſerved to hold a Scepter; I know that having diſcover'd our innocent paſſion, her guilty artifices would conſtrain me to eſpouſe <hi>Achemenes,</hi> one of her ſlaves; I know her fury caus'd you to be buried alive in the obſcurity of a deep dungeon; I know you received ſuch outrages as ſtruck me with horrour, and which highly ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd your love and conſtancy; I know that the deſpair of that inraged woman expoſed my life to poyſon; and that if the Juſtice of the Gods had not made <hi>Cibele</hi> to take it her ſelfe, who would have given it to me, your <hi>Cariclia</hi> had been loſt; I know that the fearful ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119710:82"/>of that Perſian accus'd me of that death of which ſhe was the cauſe, and of which I was innocent; I know that I found my ſelf a priſoner as well as you, and that I did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of your chains; I know that men who were at once both Judges and Slaves, did condemn me to the fire, to content that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious woman; I know that I beheld my ſelf upon the pile of wood, ready to be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; I know that the flames encompaſs'd me round about, and that love and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency were never expoſed to ſo hard a trial; but I likewiſe know, that by the aſſiſtance of the gods, and the vertue of that ſtone I wore about me, which you Grecians call <hi>Pantarbe,</hi> I marched upon the brands, as on a bed of flowers; and that that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous pile of wood became the Throne of my glory. O my dear <hi>Theagenes,</hi> tell me (I conjure you by our amours) whether my triumph were not cauſed by my condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? and whether after your mourning for me as dead, any thing ever equall'd your contentment, when you beheld me alive; or to ſay better, riſen again from death? for my part, I confeſs to you, that after that Miracle, which the gods, and love, and nature wrought together in our favour, I
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:119710:82"/>was ſo tranſported with joy, that I cannot expreſſe it: and I was liberally recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by them, for all the pains which I had undergone; yea, even for all troubles that I was yet to ſuffer. You know moreover, that as felicities are ordinarily linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as well as misfortunes; ſo this ſame (although very great) did not happen alone to us: for we came from <hi>Arſaces</hi> priſon, by the order of <hi>Oroondates,</hi> to whom by a ſpirit of jealouſie, of deſpight, and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <hi>Achemenes</hi> was gone to, to advertize him of his wives impudicity. You know alſo, that we had the ſatisfaction to learn that heavens juſtice had made uſe of <hi>Arſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> own hand, to puniſh her crimes, in the fear ſhe had that her husband would puniſh her: and that thus all our traverſes increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our contentments, and ſerved onely to make us know their grandeur the better: and if you tell me that preſently after we found a new affliction, being ſurprized by unknown people, who took us away from <hi>Bagoas,</hi> and would have conducted us to his Maſter <hi>Oroondates;</hi> I ſhall reply, that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately afterwards we alſo found a new joy, ſince thoſe ſouldiers who took us were of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> where we deſired to go. In effect,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119710:83"/>they preſented us to <hi>Hydaſpes,</hi> who at firſt ſeemed as if he would favour us, ſince by his order our chains of iron were changed for chains of gold, and we were entertained with much reſpect. Nevertheleſſe, my dear dear <hi>Theagenes,</hi> tis here I muſt confeſs that our hopes were deceitful, and that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held our ſelves anew in ſuch diſpleaſures, which had nothing equal to it, but the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which we underwent. For in fine, if they adorn'd us, it was but like victims, which they meant to ſacrifice; and if they had any reſpect for us, 'twas but becauſe we were the offerings which they had alotted for their Deities. Truly, I cannot deny but that in this occaſion my trouble was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable; and I could not but murmur a long time againſt the Oracle which had ſent me from <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> and which abſolutely ſeemed to be falſe, ſince we found a grave there where it had made us hope that we ſhould finde a Throne. But <hi>Theagenes,</hi> how marvellous and concealed is the providence of the gods! and how weak is humane reaſon in diſcovering it! at the moment that we were at the foot of the altars, where we were ready to be immolated; at the point when <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> had his arm lifted
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119710:83"/>up to ſtab his own daughter, thinking to do a pious act; briefly, at the very point that we were both going to die, and to die in ſo pitiful a manner; fate changed the face of things, I was diſcovered and known to be what I was before the City of <hi>Meroe;</hi> my Sacrifier was found to be my Father; the victime was found to be his daughter, <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> and <hi>Perſina</hi> found and heireſs, the Ethiopians found a new Queen; and <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> and <hi>Cariclia,</hi> who know that thoſe which have not had any evil cannot know what pleaſure is, found themſelves almoſt happy. I ſay almoſt, (generous Prince) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our apprehenſions did not yet ceaſe; and that my fathers ſcrupulous devotion believ'd that nature was too weak, to hinder him to acquit himſelf of what he owed to the gods. But if that too nice zeal did give us trouble, the publick cry which made it end, did no leſs rejoyce us. You will tell me (perhaps) that this unhop'd for good concern'd me only; that that which ſaved me, did not ſave you; that the hand which ſpared me, would yet ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice you; that you combated a Bull, whoſe rage was terrible; that you fought a Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, whoſe ſtrength was no leſſe; that
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119710:84"/>they would conſtrain me to marry <hi>Meroebe;</hi> that at the ſame time in which they put the royal Bandeau about my temples, they would have put the mortal Scarf over your eyes; and that I was fain once more to walk on burning coals, wiehout any other aſſiſtance than my own purity, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore left my <hi>Pantarbe.</hi> But in fine, <hi>Theage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> this happineſs became equal to us; you were ſpared, as I was ſaved; the hand which ſhielded me did not ſtrike you; the Bull neither frighted nor hurt you; the Gyant did but encreaſe your glory; <hi>Meroebe</hi> was the captive that adorned your triumph; the flame by its luſtre imparted ſome both to your vertue and mine; <hi>Cariclia</hi> and <hi>Siſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thres</hi> finiſhed our proſperities; and from the feet of thoſe altars of the gods where we then were, we preſently were raiſed up gloriouſly to the Kings Throne, where we now are. Acknowledge then (my dear <hi>Theagenes</hi>) as well as I, that it belongs not but to thoſe that have been unfortunate, to ſay they are happy; that 'tis but only after our diſgraces that our felicties are ſweet; that by troubles onely we can come to judg of quiet and reſt: and that thoſe who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have undergone any evil, cannot truly
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119710:84"/>know what pleaſure is. For my part, I find ſo much ſatisfaction in remembring my troubles, and the memory is ſo grateful and ſo precious to me, that far from baniſhing it from my ſoul, I wiſh not onely that it may be always there, but that this glorious Image may alwayes be in the memory of all men. Let there be found a Painter, both faithful and skilful, and happy enough to trace a picture of it, that Poſterity may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it; that our adventures may be known wherever the Sun gives light; that our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours be talked of in all the languages of the world; that the Ethiopian Hiſtory be not hid from any; that we may have an hundred Imitators of our pleaſures and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; that we may be the rule &amp; model of all other lovers; and that from age to age the whole Univerſe may alwayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Cariclia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:119710:85"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>TRuly one may ſay, that theſe last wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es have obtained the effect of this <hi>Harangue;</hi> ſince the reputation of this brave Romance will never have an end, and that there are few others which do not owe ſomething to it. Its Authour, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd the preſervation of this pleaſing Book before his Biſhoprick, did no bad office to thoſe who ſince himſelf have medled to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the like: and they and I are obliged to acknowledge, that though we have not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily imitated him, it is never theleſſe certain, that we owe much to this great example.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="text">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:119710:85"/>
            <head>POLIXENA TO PYRRHUS. The Seventh HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>As the Grecians were returning to their Countrey, after the taking of <hi>Troy,</hi> the ghoſt of <hi>Achilles</hi> appeared to them, which with a fearful and threatening voice reproached their ingratitude and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe; and in fine, demanded of them for recompence of his grand exploits, and the life which he had loſt in that long &amp; famous ſiege of <hi>Illium;</hi> that <hi>Polixena,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Priam,</hi> of whom he had been enamour'd, ſhould be ſacrificed upon his Tomb. Though
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119710:86"/>this demand were infinitely cruel, the fear of a dead man, whom the Grecians had ſo much dreaded living, made him obtain what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; ſo that <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> his ſon went and took her, to immolate her to his fathers pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ghoſt; and 'twas at that ſad inſtant that we do ſuppoſe, that this beauteous and generous Princeſs made this diſcourſe to him, as you are going to ſee, by the which ſhe pretended to prove to him, <hi>That death is better than ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:119710:86"/>
               <head>POLIXENA TO PYRRHUS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ear not that the deſire of life will make me have recourſe to tears, thereby to excite compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in your ſoul: <hi>Polixena's</hi> heart is too great to fear death; and her ſpirit is too reaſonable and too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, not to prefer it before ſlavery. Thoſe who are forced to deſcend from the Throne withviolence ought not to apprehend their deſcent into the grave: it is better they ſhould ceaſe to live, than that they ſhould begin to become ſlaves; and it is better to become nothing at all, than to ſurvive their glory and their happineſs. Do not fear therefore, that the Victime will eſcape from the foot of the altar; ſhe deſires her death which you are going to give her; ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119710:87"/>without horrour the knife which muſt pierce her breſt; nor does <hi>Achilles</hi> ghoſt demand the end of her life with more are dency, than ſhe her ſelf does crave it. What do you ſtay for then to perform this funeſt ceremony? there is no need you ſhould buſie your ſelves with all the preparations of an ordinary ſacrifice; for I do not think there is any one of the gods that can favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably receive that which you are going to offer this day. The Victime is pure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, I confeſs; but if I am not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it will ſtain that hand that ſhall ſhed its blood; the Sacrifier will become crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and the ſacrifice will be of no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage but only to the oblation it ſelf. But what ſhall I do in this occaſion! it ſeems hearing me ſpeak in this manner, that I would with-hold the arm that ſhould ſtrike me! No, <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> 'tis not my deſign; on the contrary, I ſeek to irritate you, thereby to haſten my death. 'Tis with impatience and diſquiet that I perceive, that my birth, my youth, and my preſent condition inſpires you with ſome ſence of tenderneſs; nay I fear alſo that my conſtancy does make you take ſome compaſſion; and apprehend in fine, all that one leſſe generous than my
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119710:87"/>ſelf would deſire. But remember not to let you bow to any pity, that you are a Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, and I a Trohan; that you are <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> ſon, that I am daughter to <hi>Priam,</hi> and <hi>Paris</hi> ſiſter; who, to revenge the death of generous <hi>Hector,</hi> kill'd that cruel <hi>Achilles,</hi> your father, and my enemy. For let them not tell me, that he was become my lover ever ſince the ſad day wherein he ſaw me at my brothers funeral; or that 'tis yet through a ſentiment of affection that his ghoſt will have me ſacrificed upon his Tomb: No, <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> no, <hi>Achilles</hi> was but my enemy, and never was my lover; however I ſhall ſay, that for my own part at leaſt, I had rather be his Victime, than to have been his Miſtris. <hi>Polixena</hi>'s eyes would be guilty, if they could have infuſed love into her brothers murtherer; and ſhe would eſteem her ſelf very unhappy, if any could ſuſpect her to have contributed any thing to ſuch a kind of conqueſt. I have wiſh'd to pierce his heart, I confeſs, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſubdue it to me; I have deſired his death, but not his love; and I in fine, have had all the hatred that one can have, for the enemy of ones blood, the deſtroyer of ones Countrey, and for <hi>Hectors</hi> murderer. That
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119710:88"/>if nevertheleſs you will publiſh to all the world, that the great <hi>Hectors</hi> vanquiſher has been vanquiſhed, not by the beauty of <hi>Polixena,</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by her ſorrow only; proclaim alſo that <hi>Polixena</hi> has not been orecome by the ſubmiſſions of <hi>Achilles;</hi> that the tears he has ſhed hath not waſhed off the blood her brother loſt by his hand; and that when <hi>Priam,</hi> and all the Trojan Princes would for the publick good have immola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her to <hi>Achilles</hi> paſſion, thereby to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a peace; proclaim, I ſay, that ſhe did oppoſe it with all her ſtrength, that ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſented, and that the death ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares her ſelf to receive this day is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complacence ſhe hath ever had for <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> paſſion. O gods! who ever beheld ſuch a token of love, as that I ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive? <hi>Achilles</hi> (as tis ſaid) was <hi>Polix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ena</hi>'s lover; but let us ſee a little what te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies he has given her of that paſſion and reſpect he hath had for her. So long as he lived, he has imployed his valour onely againſt all whom ſhe did love, and againſt all thoſe whom ſhe ought to love; I have ſeen him, that cruel <hi>Achilles,</hi> purſue all my friends with ſuch ſpleen, that it had more of fury than of true courage. I have ſeen him
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:119710:88"/>an hundred times from the top of our Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers bathe his hands in my blood. But, ô pitiful ſpectacle! I have ſeen him fight the valiant <hi>Hector:</hi> or to ſay better, I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held all the gods incens'd againſt us, making uſe of his arm to ſurmount him, who ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted all others. Yes, I have ſeen the invincible <hi>Hector</hi> fall to the duſt, by the will of heaven only, and by the only cruelty of <hi>Achilles;</hi> I have ſeen that <hi>Achilles,</hi> not only ſight my brother, not only make him loſe his life, but I have ſeen him by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity which never could be parallel'd uſe many outrages on that body of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, quite dead as it was: I have ſeen him load himſelf with his ſpoils; I have ſeen him give him ſeveral wounds, when he had no more ſence of feeling; I have ſeen him tie him to his Chariot, he who ſhould never have gone but in a Chariot of triumph; I have ſeen him compaſs our wals about three times, dragging that illuſtrious Hero, bound by the feet, his head hanging in the duſt &amp; blood. But what do I ſay; could <hi>Polixena</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all theſe things without dying! or that which is moſt ſtrange, could <hi>Polixena</hi> cauſe any love in the cruelleſt of her enemies? Yes, <hi>Polixena</hi> has lived, and her tears, as
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:119710:89"/>tis ſaid, have ſoftned the heart of the piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Achilles;</hi> he wept with her at <hi>Hectors</hi> funeral; he deſired a peace with <hi>Priam,</hi> and demanded his daughter of him. But at the ſame time (ô prodigie of extravagance as well as cruelty!) he did yet once more waſh his hands in that unfortunate womans own brothers blood, whom he intended to make his wife; he hath ſlain <hi>Troilus</hi> with the ſame hand with which he ſlew <hi>Hector;</hi> and with that ſame hand he would after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards have taken <hi>Polixena</hi> for his ſpouſe, if ſhe had been ſo unworthy as to conſent to it: Are thoſe the marks of love, or of hatred? Is it a lover, or an enemy that acts in this manner? Or to ſpeak more truly, are not thoſe the actions of a man furious and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted? For my part, I confeſs to you, all theſe things are incomprehenſible to me: for if <hi>Achilles</hi> were but my enemy, why ſhould he weep at <hi>Hectors</hi> funeral? and if he were become my lover, why did he yet tear in pieces one of my brothers with a Tygers cruelty? But that which aſtoniſhes me, and wrongs me moſt, is, that he could imagine that I was capable to hearken to his complaints and ſighs, to forget the deaths of my brothers, to be their enemies Miſtris,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119710:89"/>and their murderers wife. This thought is ſo injurious to <hi>Polixena,</hi> that ſhe cannot poſſibly comprehend it ſhould ever enter into the heart of <hi>Achilles,</hi> how inhumane ſo'ere he was. She cannot imagine, I ſay, that he could have believed that <hi>Hectors</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter were ſo unworthy to do it: for, had he been but her adverſary, as all other Greeks are, ſhe would not eaſily have believed, that he had any love for her, nor would ever have conſented to his unjuſt paſſion. Judge then, if after that which I have told you ſhe could have been perſwaded that <hi>Achilles</hi> was her lover, and far leſſe conſent to his affection? But let's ſee a little the ſentiments he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves for her in his grave; tis there that the Grecians and the Trojans ſhould end their differences; tis in the grave that all the world becomes of one party, &amp; that love and hatred ought to ceaſe. Notwithſtanding it ſeems that <hi>Achilles</hi> is not ſatiſfied with the utter ruine of <hi>Priams</hi> whole Empire. The burning of <hi>Troy</hi> is not a ſufficient pile for his funeral, nor is his ghoſt contented with all the blood the Trojans have loſt: His aſhes muſt be ſprinkled with <hi>Polixena</hi>'s; and for a token of the love he had for her, his ſon muſt needs become her executioner;
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:119710:90"/>and ſince he could not have her for his wife ſhe muſt now become his victime: Truly, to love in this manner one muſt be both a Grecian and <hi>Achilles</hi> together. Do not think how'ere that I complain of this cruel proceeding: on the contrary, I render thanks to the gods for their bounty in ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my thrid by this means: in the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my preſent fortune death cannot but be advantageous to me: and to make it welcome, they could not chooſe better than to make me loſe my life on the tomb of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles.</hi> To die in this manner is to die tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant; 'tis to behold ones enemy at ones feet; 'tis to be revenged for all the outrages and affronts one hath received; and tis to climb the Throne, when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend thus into the Grave; and if againſt my will you perceive ſome marks of ſorrow in my countenance, do not believe it is any effect of my fear, or of the trouble I have in loſing my life: on the contrary, I feel joy in it. But if it be permitted me to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all that I feel, the onely thought of the affliction which the unhappy <hi>Hecuba</hi> will receive, is that which cauſes all my grief. She brought me forth on the Throne, and I leave her to die in chains: I goe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:119710:90"/>my liberty, and I leave her in ſlavery; and even now whilſt I am to her in lieu of Husband, Children, and Empire; I deprive her of all things, in depriving her of the conſolation he found alone in me, and which ſhe can find no where elſe. Ah! would the Heavens meaſure out her conſtancy to her ſufferings; or ſhorten her dayes, to ſhorten her misfortunes. Alas! is it poſſible, that I can wiſh no better advantage for her that brought me into the world, but to ſee her in her grave? No, there is no power on earth that can make her leſs unhappy: and the Gods themſelves, ſince they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call things paſt, cannot afford her a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable deſtiny, than to give her her death before ſhe hears of mine. For I do not doubt, though I were aſſured to paſſe my life in ſlavery, but that unfortunate Princeſs will regret me with as much affliction, as if in loſing the light I loſt all the diadems of the world. The ſentiments of nature will be more prevalent in her than the power of reaſon; and the deſire to increaſe her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will make her that ſhe will find nothing which may comfort her for my loſs, but the hope of her own. At leaſt, Prince, to whom I ſpeak, be not ſo inhumane to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:119710:91"/>her the body of her daughter, or not to let her have it without paying a ranſome. For what can a Queen give you, whoſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is deſtroyed, whoſe City is conſumed, and to whom there is onely left in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the aſhes of her children? So long as ſhe had treaſures, ſhe has beſtowed them prodigally, to redeem the bodies of her ſons from the hands of the cruel <hi>Achilles;</hi> but now that ſhe hath nothing remaining of all what ſhe hath had, but onely the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of her paſs'd happineſs, thereby to encreaſe her preſent miſery, be ſatisfied with her tears. 'Tis the only ranſome you ſhould exact from her; and that onely which ſhe can give you. So that if all compaſſion be not intirely extinguiſh'd in your ſoul, you will eſteem the tears of an unhappy Princeſs to be ineſtimable; you will think the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers they make when they are even loaden with fetters, ought not to be refus'd when they are not injuſt: and thoſe ſlaves who have worn Crowns ought not to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with inhumanity. Suffer then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>Hecuba</hi> to put all thoſe in their graves whom ſhe hath brought forth into the world: return <hi>Polixena</hi>'s corps to her, when <hi>Polixena</hi> ſhall be no more; and do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:119710:91"/>this ſad courteſie and grace, to her whoſe Kingdome you have invaded, ſlain her children, and ſtabb'd her husband. Have a care, leſt abuſing of your Victories, you one day merit to find as harſh Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours as your ſelves have been. The gods who oppreſs us at this time, will be perhaps awearied of protecting you and puniſhing us; and it may be alſo that the blood which I am going to loſe may be more favourable, to the Trojans than to the Grecians. Do not therefore deſpiſe the counſels which I give you, although I be your enemy; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in the perſons of thoſe whom you have vanquiſhed, thoſe who aſſuredly had been your Conquerours, if the Heavens had ſeconded their courage. For my ſelf, who have no longer portion in this life, but onely to die with conſtancy, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner not unworthy of ſo many illuſtrious <hi>Hero</hi>'s, from whom I am deſcended: I ask you, wherefore you do not ſuddenly finiſh that which you intend to execute? Do you wait till the Ghoſt of cruell <hi>Achilles</hi> come once more forth from Hell to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demand <hi>Polixena?</hi> or do you think to make my death the more cruell, in making me expect it a long time? whatever it be, haſten
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:119710:92"/>you to ſatisfie both <hi>Achilles</hi> and <hi>Polixena</hi> together. If you ſtay longer, perhaps pity may ſurprize you; perhaps all the Trojan ſlaves may break their chains to deliver me; perhaps alſo that the Grecians will love ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſee me captive, than to ſee me die; lift up your arm therefore, and plunge your ponyard into my heart: I preſent my breſt to you; and without fear, as without regret, I am reſolved for my loſs. Do not prepare therefore neither irons, nor cords to hold me: I ſhall not (ſurely) fly that which I would goe to ſeek for; nor is it difficult to ſacrifice a Victime which willingly offers it ſelf, and which would ſacrifice her ſelf, if ſhe had the power.</p>
               <p>'Tis the leaſt favour which you can grant to a Princeſs, to die freely: As daughter to <hi>Priam,</hi> and as <hi>Hectors</hi> ſiſter, I ought to obtain this which I demand: for what avails it <hi>Achilles</hi> Ghoſt, whether I have any bonds, or whether I have none, if ſo be I loſe all my blood, if ſo be I expire on his aſhes, and that in fine, I remain in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death? But let not that cruel ghoſt imagine, that mine ſhall be his companion in the dark regions of the grave: No, I ſhall alwayes be his moſt mortal enemy.
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:119710:92"/>Ile goe (if the Gods will permit it) from grave to grave about the ruines of <hi>Troy,</hi> to ſeek the ſepulchres of my parents: and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niting my ſelf inſeparably to <hi>Hectors</hi> ghoſt, <hi>Achilles</hi> ſhall then know whether <hi>Polixena's</hi> heart were generous or not; whether it were capable to liſten to his complaints, and to anſwer to his paſſion; or if rather, ſhe were not a worthy ſiſter to <hi>Hector,</hi> and a worthy daughter to <hi>Priam.</hi> Alas! why muſt <hi>Illium</hi>'s aſhes cover the aſhes of ſo many illuſtrious perſons? O would the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortals, that the blood which <hi>Polixena</hi> is going to ſhed, could withdraw them from underneath thoſe famous ruines, and that her death could give them life again. But 'tis no time now to make theſe fruitleſs wiſhes; the Gods change not their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, nor can the fate of <hi>Troy</hi> be revoked. It belongs to us onely to ſubmit to what our deſtiny ordains: and whether we be conquered or conquerours, we are equally obliged to obey without murmuring, and with an equal viſage to receive either happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or misfortune. Tis by theſe ſentiments (ô Prince and Prieſt together) that I remain ſo tranquil at the approaches of death; and if I do not deceive my ſelfe, I diſcover
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:119710:93"/>more trouble in your looks than you can behold in m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne. For there is this difference betwixt what you are going to do, and what I do now; that I obey Heaven, and you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Ghoſt of the cruel <hi>Achilles,</hi> who will have her ſacrificed to him, whom he pretended he loved, during his life. But, O Gods, what could his hatred be, ſince even his love produces the death of her whom he loved? Was ever ſuch a thing heard of before? without doubt 'tis, if not a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, yet at leaſt an ordinary and natural ſentiment, not to be ſorry for the death of an enemy: but to deſire it to thoſe whom we love, that's a thing againſt both reaſon and nature, and a thing which no age nor people ever ſaw: and indeed I am ſtrongly perſwaded, that 'tis more thorow hatred than love that I am ſent to my grave. So long as <hi>Achilles</hi> lived he hath deſired that I ſhould be his ſlave, and now he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to live he will have me for his victime. Lets ſatisfie this laſt deſire, ſince we may do it without ſhame; and lets rejoyce that we have neither been his wife, nor his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, hor his ſlave. Whoever goes out of this life with glory, ought ever to eſteem themſelves happy; principally, if
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:119710:93"/>we leave a chain in leaving this world; what matter is it whether they unloſe the chains that binds us, or whether they break them? however it is, tis ſtill to ſet us at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               <p>Be then my deliverer, and fear not for your particular that I ſhall wiſh you any hurt. The hand that frees me cannot but be grateful to me; and he that hinders me from being a captive, cannot be hated by me. But what do I! and what is't I ſay, unhappy that I am! I do not think to whom I ſpeak. He whom I behold is not onely a Grecian, not only my enemy, not onely my ſacrifier, but he was likewiſe the executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my father. No, <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> 'tis neither as Grecian, nor as my enemy, nor as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> ſon, nor as my ſacrifier that I look on you, even when I change my thoughts, and that I make imprecations againſt you; but tis becauſe you were my fathers mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer. What <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> could you ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully purſue that venerable old man to the very feet of the altar, where his ſought his refuge, to thruſt a dagger even into his heart! Did your hand not tremble at the aſpect of that great Prince, Father of ſo many <hi>Heroes,</hi> truly it ſhould have done ſo;
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:119710:94"/>but thoſe that do not revere the gods, have no reaſon to reſpect men. Ha! truly that act hath acquired you a great deal of glory: and tis a difficult thing to kill a Prince worn out with age, feebleneſſe, and miſery; and who ſeeks his defence onely by the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe ſacred places, which ought to be inviolable. Methinks there was no need of ſtaining your arm and name by ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous an action: the flames which have conſumed our City would have ſufficed to take away the life of that deplorable King, and the leaſt you could do was to let his Palace be his Funeral-pile to be conſumed in. But you are too nice an obſerver of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> his cruelties, not to obſerve them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly: 'Twas not enough to have uſurped an Empire, and to ſet <hi>Illium</hi> all in one flame: the altars muſt be prophan'd, they muſt be ſprinkled with humane blood; and that not onely with the blood of vulgar ones. It muſt be the nobleſt blood in all the earth that muſt be ſpilt; it muſt be a royall perſon that muſt be trampled under foot, deſpiſing in him, and with him all that was holy, or ſacred in our Palaces, and in our Temples: after ſuch an unnatural action, I was in the wrong to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:119710:94"/>fear leſt any pity ſhould enter your ſoul, and defer my death: that's a ſentiment which the Grecians in general are unacquainted with, and of which the ſon of <hi>Achilles</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be capable poſſibly. That dagger which I behold in your hand, and with which you are a going to pierce my heart, is perhaps the ſame which hath gone through the King, my Fathers heart. O ſad ſpectacle! O too cruel torment! why is it that I did not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the flames which have devoured ſo many illuſtrious perſons; and that I have been reſerved to behold ſuch horrid things? am I guilty of <hi>Helena's</hi> crimes, or of <hi>Paris</hi> his failings? No, <hi>Polixena</hi> is innocent, and if ſhe have outlived ſo many misfortunes, tis to die with more conſtancy, and with more glory alſo: tis to let the Grecians which did not come to this ſiege know, what the ſons of <hi>Priam</hi> might be, ſince e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his daughter dare encounter and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front death, without any the leaſt fear.</p>
               <p>If thoſe flames which conſum'd <hi>Troy</hi> had put a period to my deſtiny, I ſhould have had no witneſſes of theſe laſt ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my ſoul: Poſterity might have doubted of <hi>Polixena</hi>'s vertue; and might have believed, that ſince <hi>Achilles</hi> had had
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:119710:95"/>the temerity, after he had made her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey deſolate, and ſlain her brothers, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand her for his wife, and to ſay, that he was in love with her; that ſhe had not done as ſhe ſhould in ſo ſtrange a buſineſs. But as things are now, I die in publiſhing, that I am an utter enemy to <hi>Achilles,</hi> that I have ever been ſo, and that I ſhall be ſo eternally; let the ghoſt of that cruel one come once more forth of his ſepulchre; let it appear to all the Grecians, and let it declare whether <hi>Polixena</hi> does erre from the truth. To juſtifie what ſhe ſayes, you need but conſider the animoſity which he retains for her, even after his death: and one may eaſily know that which ſhe had for him ſo long as he lived. For although what ever comes from the Grecians ought to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Trojans; this apparition of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> is not one of <hi>Uliſſes</hi> deceits, as that was, whereby our City was betrayed. No, tis a perfect hatred, which makes him come forth of his grave, to make me enter into mine; and this ſanguinary ghoſt did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behold the day, onely to make me loſe the light for ever. Why do you ſtay then, O Prince! unworthy of that title? and why do not you end this woful ſacrifice? Do you
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:119710:95"/>reſpect the daughter more than you have done the Father? and does your hand rather tremble to ſtab <hi>Polixena,</hi> than when you maſſacred the deplorable <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am?</hi> hearken to that ſubterranean voice which iſſues from the hollowneſſe of that grand ſepulchre with an horrid ſound, and which with threats commands you to immolate me to his fury.</p>
               <p>Behold that earth which opens it ſelf, behold the ghoſt of <hi>Achilles,</hi> which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me; or rather <hi>Achilles</hi> himſelf, who is leaving his grave. He is pale, and disfigured; a terrour inflames his eyes, even dead as they are; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him juſt ſuch as he appeared to me on the ſad day when he fought with <hi>Hector;</hi> unleſſe death (or perhaps the remorſe for his crimes) have changed his skinne and colour.</p>
               <p>Behold, <hi>Phyrrus,</hi> behold that hideous ſpirit, which ariſes little by little; and who to his threatening actions, joyning his horrid voice, does for the laſt time ordain you to ſacrifice <hi>Polixena</hi> to him. Make this Ghoſt to vaniſh by obeying it; the Victime is ready prepared, the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:119710:96"/>poyniard is in your hand, and you are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to ſhed the Blood Royall. Strike then; as your Slave, I conjure you; and as the Daughter of a King, I command you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:119710:96"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>This fair and unhappy Princeſſe drew the tears of all the Grecians: <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus</hi> himſelf was moved; nor could his eyes behold the crime which his hand committed. He ſtruck her nevertheleſs, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous man that he was; and that young and deplorable creature had ſo much modesty, that even in falling, ſtruck with the deadly blow, ſhe was careful to lay her hands upon her lower garments, for fear leſt after her death ſome indecent action ſhould offend her modeſty.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119710:97"/>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:119710:97"/>
            <head>PENELOPE TO LAERTES: The Eighth HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PENELOPE,</hi> that vertuous wife to <hi>ULISSES,</hi> whoſe reputation yet lives after ſo many ages past, and who from the borders of that ſeldome frequented Iſland where ſhe lived, has made her renown ſpread over the whole world, finding her ſelf one day extreamly afflicted for the abſence of her Husband, who after the ſiege of <hi>Troy</hi> had ſtrayed almoſt ten years, at the mercy of the windes and waves, without poſſibility of ſeeing his Countrey; would eaſe her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:119710:98"/>by her plaints, and make her dear Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Father acknowledge by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe you are now going to ſee, <hi>That abſence is worſe than death.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:119710:98"/>
               <head>PENELOPE TO LAERTES:</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that undertakes to maintain that death is the moſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and greateſt of all evils, is ſurely ſuch a one, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther never loved at all, or at leaſt hath never under one the unhappineſſe of being abſent from the perſon beloved. No, my Lord, that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter which deſolates all the earth; who by the ſucceſſion of time changes the face of the whole Univerſe, who treats alike both vice and vertue; who ſtrikes with the ſame fatal dart the Kings and Shepherds, and whoſe very portraiture alone fills the ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſoul with horrour and amazement, is not yet that thing which I believe we ought the moſt to apprehend. Abſence, which we
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:119710:99"/>may truly ſay is the commencement of all ſorrowes, and the end of all joyes, hath in it ſomewhat that is more harſh and inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable: for if the firſt be that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes our proſperity, the ſecond is that which makes us unhappy, even in the midſt of abundance, yea, on the Throne it ſelf. There is nevertheleſſe a great deal of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them, for death raviſhes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually from us, both our felicities and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; if it rob us of any flowers, it does not leave us the prickles behind them, it cruſhes with the ſame hand both our Crowns and fetters: and in a word, when it deprives us of life, it likewiſe utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhes in our hearts all the flames of love and anger, all the reſentments of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, vengeance; and in fine, all other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. It cauſes, I ſay, both our joy and trouble to expire together at the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whereas abſence not onely robs us of all the good that ever death deprives us of, but likewiſe cauſes all thoſe evils to fall on <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, to which the other puts a ſudden pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod. Our life it ſelf in this occaſion is left us, but onely to make us the more ſenſible of the moſt piercing pain that can be felt: and if there be ſometimes ſuch people, who
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:119710:99"/>prefer the abſence of the beloved perſon ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than death; 'tis becauſe they ſuffer themſelves to be deluded by falſe appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; tis becauſe that mournful dreſs in which it is repreſented affrights them; tis becauſe they contemplate it more with their bodily ſight than the eyes of the ſoul; tis becauſe they only conſider it in what is moſt terrible; and tis in fine, becauſe they love themſelves better than they doe their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, and prefer the rayes of the Sun a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the luſtre of her eyes, and had rather not ſee her at all, than be deprived of their ſight. Ha! how ignorant thoſe people are of the true ſentiments which love inſpires! But (you will ſay to me, my Lord) perhaps you do not ſeriouſly conſider, how great that violence muſt needs be which ſeparates ſo cloſe an union, as that of ſoul and body: But I ſhall anſwer you, you do not truly conſider, your ſelf, what a greater violence that muſt be, which for a long ſeaſon ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates that which love, reaſon, and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeem to have joyned with an eternal and immortal chain. Death, ſage <hi>Laertes</hi> (as you know better than my ſelf) is as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to us as life: if it be an evil, 'tis at leaſt an evil that ſhould not ſurprize us: as ſoon
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:119710:100"/>as we begin to live, we ought to begin to learn to die; at the firſt opening of our eyes, we ſhould already look on the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our graves; and every Monarch in the world that hath not renounced common ſence, cannot be ignorant, that as he mounts up to his Throne, ſo he ſhall once deſcend into his ſepulchre. 'Tis not thus in the things of love; that paſſion being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther divine, ſeizes ſo imperiouſly on thoſe whom ſhe poſſeſſes, and the ſight of the beloved perſon does ſo abſolutely fill all the ſoul of her adorer, that this abſence is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil which ſtill ſurprizes him, and comes ſo unawares, that by conſequence it renders him more unhappy than death can, which we ought alwayes to expect. That amazing inſtant, which parts two perſons perfectly loving one another, is a ſadneſſe beyond my expreſſion, though I have proved it more cruelly than any other; but to make you in ſome manner comprehend it, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to your ſelf, my Lord, that you were ambitious, and that your Crown were torn from you; imagine your ſelf were extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coverous, and that your treaſures were all ſtol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from you; imagine you were vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, and that your victory were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:119710:100"/>out of your hands; imagine you were ſhakled with chains, whoſe very weight were inſupportable; imagine you loſt all that is dear to you in the world; imagine you were deprived of the light of the day, and that you remained in horrid darkneſſe; imagine your heart were torn forth of your boſome, and you not yet dead: and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine in fine, that I not onely ſuffered all theſe pains, but that even death, how terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo'ere it be, was the utmoſt of all my wiſhes, at that ſad moment of <hi>Uliſſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture. Ha! my Lord (yet once more) how grievous that funeſt minute was to me! death is rather the lulling aſleep of all our troubles, than any ſenſible evil, and it has nothing troubleſome but the way that leads to it. But abſence is a chain of misfortunes which finds no end, but at the end of our lives, or the return of the beloved perſon. The firſt ſigh which death does make us breath, hath alwayes the advantage of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt: but the firſt, which abſence obliges us unto, is followed with ſo many others, and accompanied with ſo many tears, ſo many diſturbances, ſo many tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; or to ſpeak better, ſo many deaths, that its evill ſuffers no compariſon: and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:119710:101"/>then to ſpeak rationally, death and abſence may be taken for one another, ſince both the one and the other equally deprives us of all that we can love: but as tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the loſs of all the riches in the world can be ſo ſenſible to us, as the abſence of the perſon whom we dearly love, ſince ſhe is in the ſtead of all unto us; ſo alſo it is impoſſible, but that that which deprives us of it, muſt be more harſh than death it ſelf, which can only take away that good from us which we eſteem farre leſſe than ſhe. But (you will ſay again) that death which ſnatches away a Crown, which puls down your Throne, which deprives you of the light, does alſo rob you from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom you love: ſhe does not forſake you (tis true) but you leave her; and in this manner you do as well loſe the ſight of her, as in abſence, and likewiſe loſe her for ever. I acknowledge (ſage <hi>Laertes</hi>) that this objection is ſtrong; nevertheleſs it is not impoſſible to clear it. To die before the eyes of thoſe we love, is ſomewhat more comfortable than to remain alive, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from ones lover and husband toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to mingle our laſt tears together with his, is leſs inſupportable than to be left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:119710:101"/>to weep continually: and to leave ones ſoul betwixt thoſe armes, is rather a ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er union with him, than a ſeparation. In fine, (to ſay all in a word) after the having given him the laſt adiew after the having had the ſatisfaction of knowing the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his amour, by the greatneſſe of his ſorrowes; after the having (if it be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpeak ſo) reſigned our ſoul into his hands; we have alwayes this advantage, to ceaſe to live, in ceaſing to ſee him; loſing the light for ever with his preſence; and to become inſenſible of grief, as well as of joy. The repoſe and obſcurity of the grave are better in this occaſion than life &amp; the light of day: that funeſt and mortal Lethargy which for ever rocks all our ſences into a deep ſleep in the cradle of the Tomb, is the only remedy which could charm all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils I now ſuffer for the abſence of my dear <hi>Uliſſes;</hi> and as ſleep does every night make the happy and miſerable to become equall and alike, as it does the greateſt Princes and the meaneſt Subjects; So death likewiſe places in the ſame rank thoſe lovers which injoy the preſence of their Miſtreſſes, with thoſe which are deprived of it. The thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thoſe ſhades we meet withal in the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:119710:102"/>grave, hinders us for evermore from diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing any of the things of this world; and death, how pitileſs ſo'ere tis deſcribed to us, is not ſo cruel, but that it promptly heals us of all the evils it cauſes. If it make an ambitious man loſe his Crown, it deprives him at the ſame inſtant both of the diadem and the ambition which rendered it ſo pleaſing to him: if it rob the treaſures from the poſſeſſion of the covetous, it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſteals away that avarice from his heart which made him cheriſh wealth ſo much: and if it diſunite two perſons dearly loving, the leaſt unhappy is he without doubt who loſes his life, ſince in loſing that he loſes both his ſence, knowledge, and memory at the ſame moment. It is not thus in abſence; we die thereby indeed unto all pleaſures, but it is only to live unto all pains. As ſoon as ere we loſe the ſight of the perſon that reigns in our ſouls, all other paſſions throng in to tear and torture it; Love, Hatred, Anger, Vengeance, Jealouſie, Fear, and Hope it ſelf, does perſecute and war againſt us. We never love more, than when we loſe the ſight of the object of our affection; we never hate any thing with ſo much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence as that which robs us of our beloved:
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:119710:102"/>we are never more irritated, than when our felicity is deſtroyed, we never wiſh more ardently to revenge our ſelves, than when we are reduced to the terms of deſpair: we are never more jealous, than when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the witneſſes of their actions who owe all their fidelity to us: we never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo much to be pitied, as when we fear the death of our lovers; and one may likewiſe ſay, that we are never more unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, than when we are reduced to that point of having no other conſolation, than an uncertain and doleful hope, which ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerves rather to increaſe our miſeries, than to aſſwage them; ſo true it is, that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is a terrible and fearful evil; and ſo true it is, that it converts all the remedies which are preſented to it into poyſon. Do not you imagine (my Lord) that I have learn'd what I now ſay, either from the example of others, or from reaſon, which oft-times teaches us many things, which we have never experienced. No, my Lord, I tell you nothing, but what my own trial hath verified: and would to heaven I were yet ignorant of ſuch ſad truths, and that death were the only evil which I might apprehend. When my dear dear <hi>Uliſſes</hi> was
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:119710:103"/>reſolved to part, and that overſwayed by the power of his deſtiny, he ſeparated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from me; love (to render this ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the more cruel to me) repreſented him more lovely to me than ever I had beheld him: his ſorrow augmenting his charmes, his ſilence cauſed by the affliction he indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in leaving me, rendered him more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me, than his ſweeteſt eloquence had ever done, although that eloquence have inchanted all the earth: in fine, ſage <hi>Laer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> I then know better than ever I had known till then, the price and value of what I had poſſeſſed, and of what I was then ready to be diſpoſſeſſed of. My love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, I acknowledge it; and though I had believed all my life, that I could not poſſibly love my husband more ardently and tenderly than I did love, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I cannot deny but that I found my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection redoubled in that ſad inſtant. But when after I had loſt his ſight, the Image of <hi>Menelaus</hi> preſented it ſelf to my mind, who had cauſed his departure, hatred ſeized ſo powerfully on me, that there are no unjuſt wiſhes which I made not for him. Anger followed hatred, and the deſire of revenge immediatly ſtept in after hatred: I deſired
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:119710:103"/>he might not regain <hi>Helena;</hi> I wiſhed he might ſuffer all his life-time that which I now ſuffered by his means; and I think likewiſe, that in the heat of my reſentment I ſhould have made prayers, to obtain from heaven, that he might have been beaten, and his army defeated by the Trojans, had I not remembred that he could not be vanquiſhed, but that my dear <hi>Uliſſes</hi> muſt be ſo to, ſince he was ingaged in the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. But, my Lord, will you think is well, that I ſhould ſhew you all my troubles and diſcover all my imbecilities? Yes, ſince it is onely by that means that I can prove to you, that abſence is worſe than death. After then that I had reſented all the moſt violent effects of love, anger, hatred, I found my ſelf again aſſaulted by Jealouſie: <hi>Uliſſes</hi> went to a place, where they might take ſuch priſoners as were capable to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chain their vanquiſhers and maſters, as the examples of <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Achilles</hi> has ſince taught us. Imagine then the trouble that this thought excited in my heart: it was ſo great, that if the fear of <hi>Uliſſes</hi> death in ſo dangerous a voyage had not modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted its violence, I believe I ſhould have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed him in my thoughts, as if he had
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:119710:104"/>been already guilty: I ſhould have made him ſome reproaches, and perhaps for ſome inſtants ſhould have hated him. But the conſideration of the perils he was going to expoſe himſelf unto, did no ſooner come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my mind, but that tumult was appeaſed: but I was not the leſs unhappy for all this, ſince there is no danger which I did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend for him, and which by conſequence I did not undergo. I imagined that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him ready to make ſhip-wrack; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him in the combats; I beheld him wounded; I ſaw him a priſoner; I beheld him ready to expire; and I think truly, that the onely fear of his death had made me die, if hope more to make me ſuffer than to eaſe me had not preſerved my life. I hoped then, my Lord, but to ſay truly, 'twas ſo feebly, and with ſo much uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that that hope was rather a trouble than an help unto me. That ill founded hope had no ſooner inſpired my heart with ſome pleaſing thought, but preſently my fear quenched it again: if the one made me i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine <hi>Uliſſes</hi> returned victorious, the other perſctaded me, he might be then periſhing in the waves: if one made me behold the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the other ſhewed me nothing but
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:119710:104"/>tempeſts and wracks: in fine, I alwayes thought him either inconſtant or dead: and the ſucceſſive raign of two ſuch contrary ſentiments tyrannized ſo fiercely in my ſoul, that to be in a condition not to fear any more, nor to be flattered again with hope, I wiſhed more than an hundred times for death. You may know from thence (if I do not deceive my ſelf) that abſence is more to be feared than that, ſince tis deſired as a remedy for thoſe evils, which this laſt makes us ſuffer. Truly, my Lord, they are ſo great and ſo ſenſible, that if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comprehend, that there could be a ſharper pain, or a greater misfortune, than the death of the beloved perſon, we might yet ſay, that ſuch a loſſe cauſed leſſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than the torment of an abſence, whoſe duration is incertain. Yes, my Lord, thoſe which do not love their husbands ſo well as to follow them into their graves, and who have courage enough; or to ſay better, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility enough, to ſuffer that ſeparation without deſpairing, have more reſt than I have: they have this advantage, to know that they are unhappy alone, and that thoſe whom they mourn are at quiet: they fear neither their inconſtancy, nor their death,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:119710:105"/>which is already happened: nor can they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more apprehend ought, either from that pitileſs monſter, nor from inconſtant for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, ſince there remains no more for them to loſe but their own life, which is no longer pleaſing to them. But what do I ſay, inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as I am! No, no, my Lord, do not give ear to what my ſorrow makes me ſpeak, nor believe, that I could ever prefer the death of my deareſt <hi>Uliſſes</hi> before his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, how rigorous ſo'ere it is unto me. May he live, and may he alſo live happy, though diſtant from his <hi>Penelope,</hi> rather than I ſhould hear that he lives no more: I had rather never behold him, than to behold him die; and I had rather hear he were incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, than to hear of the end of his life. O heaven, to what a ſtrange neceſſity do you reduce me, to make wiſhes againſt my ſelf! Now, my Lord, is not abſence worſe than death? and have I not reaſon to ſay, that I am the moſt unhappy perſon of all my ſex? thoſe that die have this ſad conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in loſing their lives, that they may conſider that from the beginning of ages all men have undergone what they do, and as long as the world ſhall laſt, all thoſe that are born muſt undergo the very ſame: but
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:119710:105"/>of all the Grecian Princeſſes, whoſe huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands have followed <hi>Menelaus,</hi> I am the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe that have heard no news of mine; I am the onely ſhe that yet doth ſigh; I am the only ſhe that have no ſhare in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick joy; and the onely he alone, that dares not prepare Crowns, not knowing whether thoſe Crowns ſhould be made of Lawrel or of Cypreſs branches. The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory has been woful only to me alone; and <hi>Polixena,</hi> yea <hi>Hecuba</hi> her ſelf (though the unhappieſt amongſt the Trojans) are not yet ſo unhappy as poor <hi>Penelope.</hi> The firſt died with conſtancy, and by conſequence with glory: and laſt had at leaſt this advantage, that ſhe could weep over the bodies of her children, and revenge the death of her ſon; whereas I weep, and do not know what object my tears ſhould have. Perhaps alas! thinking onely to weep for the abſence of my dear <hi>Uliſſes,</hi> I am obliged to weep for his inconſtancy, or it may be for his death. For, my Lord, how can I think him living, and not criminal, ſince he does not come? he knowes he is King of this Iſland, and that his ſubjects have need of him; he knowes you are his Father, and that you wiſh for his return; he knows <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemachus</hi>
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:119710:106"/>is his ſon, and that he deſires to know him, he being ſo young when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, that time has effaced the memory of him; he knowes in fine, that <hi>Penelope</hi> is his wife, and that upon that happy return de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends all her felicity; nevertheleſs it is now almoſt twenty years ſince he went; it is neer ten years ſince the Grecians conquered, and yet we do not know whether we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan him as unhappy or guilty. However it be, 'tis certain that I have cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and to deſpair; on what ſide ſo'ere I turn, I ſtill finde new ſubjects of ſorrow; your old age afflicts me, my ſons green years diſquiets me; thoſe that would comfort me increaſe my troubles; thoſe which bear no part with me in my woes, anger me; and both the diſcourſes of the one, and the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the others are equally inſupportable to me. But that which nevertheleſs is the moſt cruel to me, is, that neither time nor affliction hath ſullied that little beauty on my face, which hereaofore charmed <hi>Ulyſſes:</hi> 'tis not but that if I muſt ſee him again, I ſhall be joyful to have preſerved it; but in the condition I am, I finde that tis ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me to be yet able to make any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts. Nevertheleſs you are not ignorant,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:119710:106"/>what a number of importunate perſons do perſecute me, though I deſpiſe them: for my part I am in doubt whether I ought to hide from them, my perſon or my tears: for to ſay truth I think verily I have now no other amability, nor any thing worthy of eſteem, but only my exceſſive regrets and ſorrow for the abſence of my deareſt Husband; and yet <hi>Helena</hi> hardly ever had more ſlaves than I have capt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves, though <hi>Helena</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelope</hi> are perſons very different, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I take as great care to break their chains, as ſhe did to manacle them. O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens! who ever heard ſuch amorous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, as theſe indiſcreet people make, to court me to an approbation of their fond paſſions, and to gain my belief that their intentions are legitimate? <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> is dead, (ſay theſe impatient men) and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence our love does not offend you: ha! if <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> be dead (do I reply then with tears) nothing but a grave is fit for <hi>Penelope;</hi> and if he be not, you are cruel, and not judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to come and ſigh at her feet, who ſighs for his abſence, &amp; who can never behold you but as her cnemies, rather than her lovers. Judge after this, my Lord, if any thing can be added to the troubles I ſuffer? leave me
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:119710:107"/>then the liberty to preferre death before abſence; the one makes the body ſuffer more than the ſpirit, and the other torments the ſpirit more than the body; the one puts a period to all misfortunes, the other gives birth to all miſerios; the one is an evil which indures but an inſtand, the other is a deſpair which may laſt all the life; the one does but extinguiſh all our paſſions, the other is a Tyrant which makes them rule ſucceſſively in our ſouls: in fine, death is but onely death, and abſence is a ſeries or chain of murders, torments, diſquiets, fears, jealouſies, angers, deſpairs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual deaths. In abſence we make vowes which contradict one another; ve make wiſhes, for which we repent again; we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect alwayes to behold that which we fear we ſhall never ſee again; we hope and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend at the ſame time; we fancy dangers which never were; we accuſe with unjuſtice thoſe whom we bemoan and cheriſh with reaſon; we ſometimes hate our ſelves; we blame our own ſorrow, and yet will not be comforted; we hide our tears, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not that time ſhould wipe them from our cheeks, we envy anothers happineſs, we fly from ſociety, and ſolitude is inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable;
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:119710:107"/>portable; we behold all what we would not ſee, and cannot be ſo bleſſed as to ſee that which we would ever behold; we ſeek after that which we are aſſured not to find; and in a word, we finde our ſelves in a condition to wiſh for death, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it before abſence; yea, to make ſupplications to obtaine that which all the world fears, and from which all the world does flie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb n="206" facs="tcp:119710:108"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>ONe may believe that <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> return was the effect of this <hi>Harangue,</hi> and that the Heavens did grant it to ſuch tender and paſſionate ſentiments: ſince after he had ſtrayed ſo many years on the Sea and Land, he returned to the imbraces of his wife <hi>Penelope,</hi> his father <hi>Laertes,</hi> and <hi>Telema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> his ſon; and this wiſe and illuſtrious perſOn beheld him again in that Iſladnd where ſhe ſo much longed for him.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="text">
            <pb n="207" facs="tcp:119710:108"/>
            <head>BRISEIS TO ACHILLES. The Ninth HARANGUE.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AChilles</hi> becomming inamoured with <hi>Polixena</hi> at <hi>Hectors</hi> funeral, would, to facilitate the happy ſucceſs of his love, make a peace betwixt the Trojans and Greeks; and that he might behold his new Miſtris upon ſo fair a pretext, he came even into <hi>Troy</hi> whilſt the truce laſted. So ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary a thing cauſed all the people to murmur in the Camp, an rendered him ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to the whole Army: but amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Briſeis</hi> a captive Princeſs, whom <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:119710:109"/>had much loved, before this infidelity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thereby an affliction beyond compare. So that for her own interest, and likewiſe the Princes, whoſe glory ſhe was obliged to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, ſhe took in fine, the conſidence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent unto him the wrong he would do her, and that which would likewiſe accrue unto himſelf. Now as he was of a violent humour, and a ſpirit apt to be moved, this remonſtrance did but ſtir his anger; inſomuch that he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Briſeis</hi> as a ſlave, and ſpake to her with a Magiſterial accent, that's to ſay, very imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. This unjuſt proceeding brought this Lady to deſpair; and as deſpair makes wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of all things, and that from exeream ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity, one runs ſometimes even to audacity; ſhe undertook to maintain in his preſence, <hi>That one may be both Slave and Miſtris.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="harangue">
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:119710:109"/>
               <head>BRISEIS TO ACHILLES.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Es, yes, cruel <hi>Achilles,</hi> I ſee my chains, and feel a ſlave: though I had never beheld the one, and had alwayes been ignorant of the other, the uſage I have received this day would teach me but too much what my condition is, and alſo both what the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune is that accompanies it, and the ſhame that waits upon it. You are without doubt my maſter, your actions and your words do teſtifie it enough: and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing very far beyond the limits of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate power of my Maſter, you become my Tyrant, and make me ſuffer a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unworthy both of your ſelf and me. But what ever Pride you have, and what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver humility you would have me to have,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:119710:110"/>I cannot forget in wearing your fetters, that I ſhould wear a Crown; that I was not born ſuch as you would have me die; that my hand was deſtined for a Scepter, not for a chain and that in taking away my Throne you have not taken down my heart; as we receive Kingdomes and Empires from the hands of fortune; ſo ſhe being avaritious and capritious, can take away again what ſhe had beſtowed: but as we have our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity onely by nature, who is too wiſe to change her counſels, and too liberal to take away her gifts again; ſo we preſerve that even to our graves; we can ſhew that at liberty in the midſt of ſlavery; &amp; make it, in fine, triumph over tyrants as well as tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny. Do not expect therefore, that I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to complain poorly of your infidelity; that I ſhould let fall any ſhameful teats; or that I ſhould ſhed them needleſly; that I ſhould give ſuch ſatisfaction to my Rival, as to behold my ſhame in the day of her glory, and my ſorrow amidſt her pleaſures: Or briefly, that I my ſelf ſhould add to my diſgraces, that of not being able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe them. No, <hi>Achilles,</hi> no, I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain no more of your inconſtancy, I will call you ingrateful no more, I will not ſay
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:119710:110"/>you are wavering; nor will I any more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach you, that either you heard not, or that you heard but in fury. Continue to betray me, if you think good, paſſe from the Grecians to the Trojans Camp, from our Trenches over their Ramparts; and if this be not yet enough, adore your enemies: Kiſs (I ſay) <hi>Polixena</hi>'s hand, if ſhe be ſo unworthy as to incure, that his who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered her brother <hi>Hector,</hi> dare to approach ſo neer hers: neither forget any thing that can ſatisfie her of whatſo'ere may cauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to me, or diſhonour to your ſelf. I conſent, <hi>Achilles,</hi> I conſent. whether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, or voluntarily, no matter, if ſo be you are pleaſed; if ſo be you appear my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet, if ſo be I appear your ſlave; and that I voluntarily indure your inconſtancy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out murmuring. But do not expect that I will ſuffer you to goe on from inconſtancy to pride, and from pride to diſdain; that you ſhould reproach me of my chains, which onely your cruelty makes me wear; and that you ſhould treat me unworthily, becauſe I am not free, becauſe you are not generous, and becauſe I am unfortunate. No, I tell it you once more, and ſhall tell it you more than a thouſand times; I cannot
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:119710:111"/>ſuffer that baſeneſs; and though your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity ſhould condemn me to torments, I had yet rather fuffer than deſerve them. What, <hi>Achilles!</hi> doe you remember no more already, that I have ſeen you kiſs my chains with reſpect, and not dare to kiſs the hand that ware them? that I have known you think it a glory to obey her, whom you might have commanded? that I have found you entertaining her as a Queen, whom now you uſe as a Slave? and finally, that I have beheld you captivated by your own cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive? whence comes then ſo ſtrange an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration? was I more at freedome than I am, or am I more a ſlave than I was? were you leſſe Soveraign than you at preſent are, or are you more abſolute than you were then? have we interchanged our conditions one with another, or have I changed my vifage? were you blinde, barbarous <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> or are you now become ſo? did you want judgment at that time when you ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, or do you want it now, ſince you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore me no more? In a word, were you an Idolater then, or are you impious now? Ha! no, no neither of all theſe things hath happened ſo; I am ſtill what I was, you are ſtill the ſame you were, at leaſt, for your
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:119710:111"/>fortune: and if there had happened no more change in your heart, than in my face, and in your condition, I ſhould yet behold him at my feet, who would hardly ſuffer me to caſt my ſelf at his; I ſhould yet hear him make his Petitions, who now pronounces nought but injuries againſt me; I ſhould yet receive ſubmiſſions from him, from whom I now receive affronts; I ſhould yet behold his humility, and not perceive his pride; and briefly, I ſhould yet have in you a reſpectful lover, and not a vaunting Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. You believe then (as I comprehend by your pitileſs and haughty anſwer which you have made me) you believe (I ſay) that command and ſervitude are things incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible in love, as well as they are in war; that one cannot give lawes, and receive them; and that one cannot ſerve and raign together, But how you are abuſed, if you have that belief! and how little do you know the power of love, if you make it to riſe from the power of fortune! if thoſe from whom I had my birth had onely car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſheephooks, and never ſeen the ſcepter but in anothers hand; if I had been born in a Cottage, and not within a Palace; yea more, had I been born with theſe chains on
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:119710:112"/>me, in which you will make me die; if I were not only a ſlave, but the daughter of a father that had been ſuch himſelf; and on the contrary, though your Empire were as great as the whole Earth, though your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince were the Miſtris of the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; and that <hi>Peleus,</hi> or <hi>Achilles</hi> himſelf did command all men, as they do the Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mydons, that could not hinder but that <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis</hi> would be Soveraign, if <hi>Briſeis</hi> were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved; and <hi>Achilles</hi> would obey her, if <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> could truly love. 'Tis one of the moſt illuſtrious marks of love puiſſance, to abaſe Thrones, and elevate Shepherdeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; to place the Crown upon a fair head, whoſe temples never kiſſed but onely gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands of flowers; and in a word, to make us behold Queens in fetters, as well as Kings in chains, when two amiable perſons are truly touched with this noble paſſion; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor other has any thing which does not become common to both; they make a glorious exchange of the marks of the ones misfortune, and the others gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, that ſo nothing may be ſeparated, nor any thing render them different. The lover takes his Miſtreſſes fetters, the Miſtris takes her lovers ſcepter; he who commanded,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:119710:112"/>obeys; and ſhe that obeyed, commands: and as the obedience is voluntary, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is not rigorous. He trembles now himſelf, that Conquerour that made whole Provinces tremble, he obſerves the leaſt glances of this elective Queen; he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placent, he is humble, yea even reſpectful; he fears to offend her, he ſeeks to pleaſe her; and as he loves, ſo he deſires onely to be rewarded with love again. He prefers the leaſt of her favours above the gold of his Scepter, and the jewels of his Crown; he believes himſelf rich, when he beſtowes all; and briefly, he thinks he raignes, when he thus ſerves. Thus, proud and haughty <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles,</hi> thus do true lovers live, and ſuch as are truly generous. They never let fall any reproaches, no aigreur ever mingles with their diſcourſes: on the contrary, the leaſt injury would ſeem blaſphemy unto them, and the leaſt inſolence a ſacriledge beyond all pardon, and worthy of death; and if any other had the boldneſſe to dare to anger their Miſtris, far from offering it themſelves, one paſſion would excite another, love would lead them to hatred, hatred would draw them unto fury, &amp; fury would prompt them to revenge: they would be prodigal
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:119710:113"/>of their deareſt blood, as they had been of their greateſt riches; they would expoſe themſelves for her glory, and believe they ventured for their own; and though they ſhould loſe both their Scepter and life to defend her, they would yet believe they gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that loſs, and triumph in their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, as having done what they could and ought; ſo true it is that love renders thoſe equals that were different, and confounds particular intereſts. In effect, as wiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould nor cheriſh a blind affection, but ever love with knowledge, as well as incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; the beauty of vertue ſhould raviſh them, as well as the beauty of a lovely face; and the perfections of the mind charm them as powerfully as the perfections of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; their hearts ſhould be touched more by the qualities of the ſoul than by the gifts of fortune; wherefore then, after they have loved that which they judged worthy of their love, ſhould they ceaſe from loving her ſtill? wherefore do we ſee them change, ſince vertue changes not? and wherefore ſhould they loſe even their reſpect, ſince that ſame beautie which made them reſpectful, hath loſt nothing of its luſtre? believe me, <hi>Achilles,</hi> whether vertue either reign or obey,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:119710:113"/>whether ſhe be on the throne or in fetters, or whether it have its birth in the purple or in rags, it is alwaies alike lovely, and alwaies e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually worthie of reſpect and veneration. None but the dull and ſtupid multitude will iudg of things by the luſtre that invirons them, and dazles the ſight; or will make the difference of perſons according to their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent conditions. All thoſe borrowed orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have nothing that is either eſſential or ſolid; &amp; if it be only the gold or diamonds in the Crown that renders one eſteemable, we ſhould rather eſteem the Goldſmiths or Lapidaries, which make them ſo gliſtering; or at leaſt, the earth which produces them. Ha! no, no, all thoſe things which the vulgar call precious, are too poor to be the objects of a great and reaſonable underſtanding; and that which comes from fortune is too low of value to make vertue be leſs eſteem'd, though ſhe be no longer adorned with it, or with anie juſtice to hinder, but that one may be both ſlave and Miſtris. But let us ſuppoſe (though falſly, and without reaſon) that her birth muſt needs be illuſtrius, that wil prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the glorie of retaining him ſtill an illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous priſoner, who is already become ſo to his ſlave, that the chains of that happy captive
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:119710:114"/>muſt have been forged of the ſame gold the ſcepter was of, which otherwhile her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ruled; what do you finde in this, that can make <hi>Briſeis</hi> unworthy of <hi>Achilles</hi> love, or worthy of his hatred? You are the ſon of a King, I confeſs, but was not my father a King likewiſe? there are Crowns in your family, I acknowledge it, but hath there not been ſome in mine alſo? you ought to aſcend the Throne, I cannot deny it, but have you not made me deſcend from one your ſelf? you have overcome us, 'tis true, but might not we have vanquiſhed you? I am become your ſlave, that's certain, but was it not poſſible you might have been ours? I wear your fetters, all the world ſees it but ſo might you have worne our chains? you may treat me cruelly, I do not doubt it, but will it not be barbarous if you do? you may abandon me indeed; but are you not unfaithful if you do? you may love <hi>Polixena,</hi> I know it but too well, but would it not be unreaſonable that you ſhould love your enemies? you may goe into Troy, I grant it, but will it not be a madneſs to truſt the Trojans? you may likewiſe betray the Grecians, who does not know it; but will it not be a baſeneſs to betray them? Ha! I
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:119710:114"/>perceive, cruel <hi>Achilles,</hi> that this laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach is more inſupportable to you than all the reſt; that you can hardly ſuffer it; and that tis not without ſome difficulty, that you in ſome manner retain that fury which is ſo natural to you. Tis no matter, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, tis no matter, for though you ſhould let the cloud of your anger break upon my head, yet the care I have for all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you, obliges me not to conceal from you that which others dare not reveal unto you. Know then (if you be ſo blind as not to perceive it) that the whole Camp mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs againſt you, that <hi>Agamemnon</hi> whom you have offended, makes uſe of this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to revenge himſelf, and to cry you down amongſt the Grecians; that <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſes</hi> imployes his eloquence upon no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubject, and his facility of ſpeaking, and ſpeaking well is a dangerous enemy to you; that the ſage <hi>Nestor</hi> loudly blames you, though in all other occaſions he hath ever teſtified much reſervedneſſe; that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jax</hi> himſelf, who is no ſmall friend, is redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the ſorry neceſſity, either of not ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to defend you, or to quarrel for want of better reaſons with thoſe that condemn your proceedings; that <hi>Therſites</hi>
                  <pb n="220" facs="tcp:119710:115"/>by biting jeſts ſtrikes at your reputation, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all the world merrie at your coſt; and <hi>Idomeneus, Diomedes,</hi> and all the other Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Princes are reſolved not to indure ſo unreaſonable a thing. Everie one obſerves you watchfully, each one remarks all your words, everie one conſiders all your actions; and you are now eſteemed in our Camp, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar a ſpie for the Trojans, than as one of the chief commanders of the Grecians. I perceive that you will anſwer me, by the fury which inflames your eies, that you know the art to make them hold their peace; that your hand is more to be feared than their tongues; and that if they can affront you, you can yet better puniſh them, and revenge your ſelf. But <hi>Achilles,</hi> you muſt then hew in pieces all our Troops, combate all our Captains, and ſlaie all our ſouldiers; that is to ſay, you muſt do that which the Trojans cannot, nay dare not undertake; you muſt goe and take <hi>Hectors</hi> place; you muſt goe and diſhonour your ſelf. Perhaps you have no ſuch guiltie thoughts, perhaps you will onelie retire your ſelf into your tents, as you did heretofore; that ſo by the diſadvantage which the Grecians ſhall have, when they muſt fight without you, they may know and
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:119710:115"/>feel the wrong they do themſelves by vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, and not approving all that pleaſes you. O <hi>Achilles!</hi> are theſe fit actions for an Hero, who hath no other object but his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp; who by a thouſand brave performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aſpires to immortalitie? Should anie one prefer his particular intereſt before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, or his unjuſt paſſion above equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf, or the enemies good beyond his own countreys? ſhould anie one believe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wiſer than all others, when indeed he has no wiſdome at all? ſhould any one be Judge in his own cauſe? ſhould anie one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to his own deſires, &amp; not give ear to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelf? and if it be ſo that one had trulie loved (which I cannot believe) ſhould he proudly maintain afterwards, that one cannot be both ſlave &amp; miſtris? certainly, <hi>Achilles,</hi> there is ſomewhat that is ſo ſtrange in your proceedings, that one cannot wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend it; the more one conſiders it, the leſs tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; &amp; I think you hardly underſtand it your ſelf. For my part I acknowledg that tis inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceivable to me, nor can I imagin by what fantaſtical motives you can be drawn to do ſo: for wherefore ſhould you quarrel ſo out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly with <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> when he plucked me out of your hands, if you do not find me
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:119710:116"/>wherefore retreat within your Pavilions, and ſigh bitterly there, ſince you do not love the cauſe of your retreat? wherefore did you behold our Battslia's defeated, and not aſſiſt them, if they onely took away from you what you have a minde to loſe? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did you ſuffer <hi>Hector</hi> to break down our barracadoes, and not oppoſe him, if this cauſe of your difference be ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to you? wherefore did you ſuffer him to fire our Navy, without haſtening to quench it, if that flame of affection which you had for me be extinguiſhed in your heart? wherfore did you expoſe <hi>Patroclus,</hi> the deareſt of your friends, and be the cauſe of his death, if my life be not dear to you? and wherefore in fine, did you take me out of <hi>Agamemnons</hi> hands, if I am no longer welcome to you? anſwer, <hi>Achilles,</hi> anſwer to what I deſire you: I intreat you with humility, if I be yet your ſlave onely; and if I am yet both your Slave and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, I command you. Have you taken me to your own ſelf again but only to imploy me about mean and ſervile offices? Have you many captives that wears chains, whoſe fathers have worne crowns? do you believe that an hand ordained for a Scepter can help
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:119710:116"/>its ſelf with a needle? or that ſhe that was accuſtomed to command, can accuſtome her ſelf to obey? Do you believe when you treat me thus, that I can ſee it, and live? Do you believe I am deſtitute of courage, as you are of reaſon and pitie? Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your fetters can enchain the ſoul as they do the bodie; or that a generous ſtab cannot free me from this ſlaverie and your Tyrannie? Ha! if you believe thus, how little do you know your own cruelties, and how ill are you acquainted with <hi>Briſeis!</hi> how little do you conceive what death is; or how little do you confider what I ſuffer! Though it ſhould preſent it ſelf to my ſight in all that funeſt &amp; bloudie equipage, which the moſt barbarous Tyrant can dreſs it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; though I ſhould meet it accompanied with executioners, with ſcourges, and with flames; though there were new tortures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented to pleaſe you, and to afflict me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; I ſhould yet prefer all theſe before the miſerable condition I am now in: and ſhould ſooner reſolve to ſuffer them all, than to ſuffer your outrages and diſdain: for in fine, one may be both Captive and Miſtris; bur one cannot remain a captive without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miſtris, after the once having had the
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:119710:117"/>glorie of being ſo. I could have lived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that glorie, but I cannot live and loſe it; I could have reſolved to have lived in your chains, but I cannot reſolve now to return to them again; I could have indured the anger of my Conquerour, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not indure the diſdain of my lover; I could then have remembred that I was your ſlave, but now I cannot forget that you have mine: in a word, you may be barbarous and inconſtant, but I cannot be inſenſible and have no reſentment. O cruel and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable <hi>Achilles!</hi> are you not alſo cruel enough to believe, that I ſhould be yet too much honoured in ſerving the new and fairer object of your flames? have you not ſo much blindneſs as to hope that I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her captive, as you ſay I am yours? do you not expect from my complacence and willingneſſe, that I ſhould take the care to chuſe her an habit that may adorn her, and the pains to curl her hair, to imbroider her head-attire with jewels; and to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour beſides to adde new graces to thoſe ſhe received at her birth, that thereby art may finiſh in her that which nature has ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly begun? will you not have me extol her perfections, tell you of her charmes,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:119710:117"/>make you remark the luſtre of her eies, the pureneſs of her skin, and beauteous face, thereby to increaſe your affection and your delight together? will you not after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards make me goe and entertain that faire Phrigian of the rare qualities that are in you? muſt I not vaunt of your courage, and ſpeak to her of your skill, and above all value your conſtancy which I know ſo well, that ſo I may inkindle her ſoule with the bright flame which conſumes yours? But will you not have me tell her, to prove your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that you have beſieged <hi>Troy,</hi> that you have vanquiſht the Trojans a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, and that you took away her brothers life? Will you not have me declare aloud your liberality, when you took money for <hi>Hectors</hi> corps; and your civility, when you threatened <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> who came to your Tents to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it of you? O barbarous man that you are! are thoſe your intents? but ô faint-hearted as I am my ſelfe! am I not aſhamed of what I do? and ſhould I not bluſh, ſince contrary to my deſigne and firſt dicourſe my verie
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:119710:118"/>anger it ſelfe is become a token of my paſſion, or rather of my errour? No, no, do not liſten to me any more, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liſten to love, who ſpeaks to you even as I do; nor to reaſon, which ſayes the ſame that love does: Be gone, ſince you will goe, and paſſe from this Camp to the other, where glorie waits for you, as well as <hi>Polixena:</hi> Leave your ancient friends, and runne to the imbraces of thoſe whom you have fought withall, and whom you ought to fight withall again: forget the intereſt of your own Nation, and loſe all even to your very honour, to behold your Miſtris a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; look upon <hi>Briſeis</hi> tears with ſmiles, and ſcoffe at her troubles, if at leaſt her troubles doe not provoke your anger: Joyn her chains to <hi>Hectors</hi> armes, and carry both the one and the others to that Trojans feet: and in fine, goe and marrie an unworthie ſiſter upon the tombe of her moſt generous brother. You will have it ſo, and Fate will have it ſo likewiſe; and although I would not, if I could help it, yet I muſt needs conſent to it; for who can withſtand
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:119710:118"/>Fate and <hi>Achilles</hi> his obſtinacy? But remember, cruel and blinde as you are, that a God hath told you by my mouth, (yes I ſwear, that I feel a God inſpiring what I now tell you) that you ſhall finde hatred, where you hope to meet with love; that you ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but regret, where you expected nothing but pleaſure; that you ſhall be betrayed by the Trojans, as you now betray the Grecians; that they ſhall have as much craft, as you have ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity; that if <hi>Polixena</hi> do wait for you, death does wait for you alſo neer her; that if you approach neer <hi>Troy,</hi> your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal houre does approach likewiſe; that the firſt day of that fatall Marriage ſhall be the laſt of your dayes, and that your death muſt quickly make me die.</p>
               <p>Behold what Heaven has inſpir'd me with, and this is that which you ought to believe; this is that which you will not believe; and this is that inſenſible and mad man, which will be the cauſe both of your ruine and mine. Juſt Gods, he hears me no more, he is going! the power
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:119710:119"/>of his deſtiny drags him away; I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him no more; nor ſhall he 'ere ſee me again; he leaves me, he is going to die, and I my ſelf am going to die likewiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="effect">
               <pb n="229" facs="tcp:119710:119"/>
               <head>The effect of this HARANGUE.</head>
               <p>THe unfortunate <hi>Briſeis</hi> obtained no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the patileſſe <hi>Achilles,</hi> but her prediction was not untrue. He went to ſee <hi>Polixena,</hi> that he might ſee the day no longer; and every one knows, that one of <hi>Paris</hi>'s arrows ſent him to his grave, for not having believed this lovely ſlave, who without doubt deſerved to be together both Slave and Miſtris.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
